<articles><article><title>Suspected Russian Intelligence Operative Extradited from Estonia to Face Charges Related to Providing American-Made Electronics and Ammunition to Russian Military</title><url>https://justice.gov//opa/pr/suspected-russian-intelligence-operative-extradited-estonia-face-charges-related-providing</url><text>A Russian citizen with alleged ties to Russia&#8217;s Federal Security Service (FSB) will be arraigned today on an indictment charging him with conspiracy and other charges related to a global procurement and money laundering network on behalf of the Russian government.

According to court documents, Vadim Konoshchenok, 48, of Tallinn, Estonia, was arrested in Estonia on a provisional arrest warrant issued from the Eastern District of New York and extradited from Estonia to the United States on July 13.

&#8220;This defendant, who is suspected of having ties to the FSB, smuggled hundreds of thousands of illicit munitions in support of Moscow&#8217;s war machine, using front companies to conceal his criminal enterprise,&#8221; said Assistant Attorney General Matthew G. Olsen of the Justice Department&#8217;s National Security Division. &#8220;The Department of Justice remains steadfast in its mission to counter Russian aggression and we will give no quarter to those who violate U.S. sanctions to further fuel its war effort.&#8221;

&#8220;In early December, I met with Estonian counterparts in Tallinn regarding the pending U.S. request to arrest Vadim Konoshchenok,&#8221; said Assistant Attorney General Kenneth A. Polite, Jr. of the Justice Department&#8217;s Criminal Division. &#8220;I would like to pay tribute to Prosecutor General Andres Parmas&#8217;s team, and to the Estonian Internal Security Service, for their prioritization of this case, and for their close coordination with the Department of Justice&#8217;s Office of International Affairs on the provisional arrest and extradition of Konoshchenok.&#8221;

&#8220;As alleged, the defendant was a critical participant in a scheme to provide sensitive, American-made electronics and ammunition in furtherance of Russia&#8217;s war efforts and weapons development, violating U.S. export controls, economic sanctions and other criminal statutes,&#8221; said U.S. Attorney Breon Peace for the Eastern District of New York. &#8220;Let this case serve as the latest example that no matter where you are in the world, if you violate U.S. export controls or evade U.S. sanctions, we will not rest until you face justice in a U.S. courtroom.&#8221;

&#8220;The FBI and our partners work diligently to bring to justice those who assist Russia&#8217;s military interests and put national security at risk,&#8221; said Assistant Director Suzanne Turner of the FBI&#8217;s Counterintelligence Division. &#8220;According to the allegations in the indictment, Konoshchenok helped the FSB smuggle military grade ammunition and a range of nuclear and computer equipment which could be used as instruments of war. Today&#8217;s indictment is a fierce reminder of the lengths Russian intelligences services will go to advance Russia&#8217;s military capabilities. The FBI is deeply committed to disrupting and dismantling these actions.&#8221;

According to the indictment and court filings, Konoshchenok and his co-defendants were affiliated with Serniya Engineering and Sertal LLC (the Serniya Network), Moscow-based companies that operate under the direction of Russian intelligence services to procure advanced electronics and sophisticated testing equipment for Russia&#8217;s military industrial complex and research and development sector, some of which can be used in the development of nuclear and hypersonic weapons, quantum computing and other military applications. Following Russia&#8217;s invasion of Ukraine in February 2022, the U.S. Department of the Treasury&#8217;s Office of Foreign Assets Control (OFAC) and the Department of Commerce (DOC) Bureau of Industry and Security (BIS) levied sanctions against Serniya, Sertal and several individuals and companies engaged in the scheme, calling them &#8220;instrumental to the Russian Federation&#8217;s war machine.&#8221;

As alleged in the indictment, the Serniya Network was licensed to conduct highly sensitive and classified procurement activities by Russia&#8217;s FSB, Russia&#8217;s principal security agency and the main successor agency to the Soviet Union&#8217;s KGB. According to court documents, in electronic communications, Konoshchenok explicitly identified himself as an FSB &#8220;Colonel&#8221; and enclosed a photograph of himself wearing his FSB uniform. Additionally, a review of electronic communications equipment recovered from Konoshchenok revealed saved contacts beginning with the prefix &#8220;FSB&#8221; and email addresses from &#8220;FSB[.]ru&#8221; domains. One of Konoshchenok&#8217;s calendar entries referenced an &#8220;FSB order.&#8221;

As described in the indictment, Estonia was a popular transshipment point, where Konoshchenok would smuggle U.S.-origin items across the border into Russia. On Oct. 27, 2022, Konoshchenok was detained by Estonian authorities while attempting to cross into Russia from Estonia with approximately 35 different types of semiconductors and electronic components, including several U.S.-origin and export-controlled items. Konoshchenok has also been repeatedly stopped by Estonian border officials attempting to smuggle hundreds of thousands of American-made and export-controlled rounds into Russia, including 6.5 mm, 7 mm, .338 and .308 magnum rounds, which are commonly used by snipers, as well as military-grade .223 rounds.

Konoshchenok used an Estonian front company called Stonebridge Resources and communicated frequently with other co-conspirators about sourcing, transporting and paying for controlled items. In electronic communications, Konoshchenok is clear that his fee is &#8220;10%&#8221; because he &#8220;can&#8217;t do less. Sanctions . . . Sanction item for 10%.&#8221;

To date, over half a ton of military-grade ammunition linked to Konoshchenok has been recovered or interdicted before being smuggled into Russia.

If convicted, Konoshchenok faces a maximum penalty of 30 years in prison.

The FBI is investigating the case. The Justice Department&#8217;s Office of International Affairs and the Estonian authorities, including Estonian Internal Security Service (KAPO) and the Prosecutor General&#8217;s Office of the Republic of Estonia, provided significant assistance in securing foreign evidence, the arrest and extradition of Konoshchenok.

Assistant U.S. Attorneys Artie McConnell and Matthew Skurnik for the Eastern District of New York and Trial Attorney Scott A. Claffee of the National Security Division&#8217;s Counterintelligence and Export Control Section are prosecuting the case.

This case has been coordinated through the Justice Department&#8217;s Task Force KleptoCapture, an interagency law enforcement task force dedicated to enforcing the sweeping sanctions, export restrictions, and economic countermeasures that the United States has imposed, along with its allies and partners, in response to Russia&#8217;s unprovoked military invasion of Ukraine. Announced by the Attorney General on March 2, 2022, and under the leadership of the Office of the Deputy Attorney General, the task force will leverage all the Department&#8217;s tools and authorities against efforts to evade or undermine the economic actions taken by the U.S. government in response to Russian military aggression.

</text></article><article><title>Seven More Individuals Charged in Connection with Illegal Gambling Businesses in Ohio</title><url>https://justice.gov//opa/pr/seven-more-individuals-charged-connection-illegal-gambling-businesses-ohio</url><text>A federal grand jury in Cleveland, Ohio, returned five indictments, unsealed today, charging a total of ten individuals, three of whom were previously charged, with illegal gambling, tax and/or other related offenses.

According to the indictments, nine defendants owned or operated illegal gambling businesses (&#8220;IGBs&#8221;) in Canton, Ohio, including Skilled Shamrock, Redemption, Plaza 777, Gametastic, Gametastik, Belden Connection 777, Caf&#233; 62, Got Skillz, and Skillz 777.&#160;

Stephanie Condric

One indictment charges that Stephanie Condric of Canton, Ohio, allegedly co-owned and operated Gametastic.&#160; Condric and others allegedly concealed their ownership of Gametastic by putting the business in the name of a nominee and reported some of its payroll under the name of a nominee business. &#160;According to the indictment, Condric and her co-conspirators failed to report all of Gametastic&#8217;s payroll on employment tax returns filed with the IRS.&#160; Condric also allegedly failed to report her share of Gametastic&#8217;s profits on her individual income tax returns for 2016 and 2017.

Christos Karasarides, Christopher Karasarides, Ronald DiPietro, Thomas Helmick

In May 2021, a grand jury returned a superseding indictment charging Ronald DiPietro (a Certified Public Accountant), Thomas Helmick, and Jason and Rebecca Kachner with tax and gambling offenses. In 2022, a second superseding indictment charged DiPietro with tax evasion and added Christos Karasarides who worked with DiPietro to provide false information to the IRS.&#160; Jason and Rebecca Kachner, who are married, pleaded guilty in July 2022.

A third superseding indictment now adds Christopher Karasarides. Christopher Karasarides and his father, Christos Karasarides, both of Canton, Ohio are charged with, among other violations, conspiring to defraud the United States. The indictment alleges that Christos Karasarides fraudulently attempted to compromise and settle his more than $3.1 million tax debt with the IRS by (1) submitting false information to the IRS about his interest in and income from IGBs, (2) filing false income tax returns, and (3) hiding his income and assets, including his ownership and income from Skilled Shamrock, Redemption, and Plaza 777. &#160;Christos Karasarides allegedly spent millions in cash between 2013 and 2019 for cars, golf and other expenses at a country club, credit card charges, and purported loans for businesses with which he was associated&#160; The indictment alleges that Christopher helped conceal his father&#8217;s assets from the IRS by serving as a nominee owner of some of his father&#8217;s businesses&#160; In addition, Christopher allegedly filed false individual tax returns for 2017 through 2020 reporting that he was the shareholder in a particular business when, in fact, Christos Karasarides was the true shareholder.

Melissa Bragg

Melissa Bragg of Canton, Ohio, is charged in a separate indictment with conducting Belden Connection 777, an illegal gambling business, from approximately 2013 to July 11, 2018.

Michael Moneypenny

Michael Moneypenny of Norton, Ohio, is charged in a separate indictment with four counts of conducting illegal gambling businesses, arising from his involvement in Skilled Shamrock, Redemption, Gametastic, and Gametastik.&#160; Moneypenny allegedly operated a business repairing and selling slot machines, and also leased slot machines to gambling businesses in Ohio and Florida.

Isaiah Worlow, Steven Fluharty, and Tiffany Kerekes

Isaiah Worlow, Steven Fluharty, and Tiffany Kerekes are charged in a fifth indictment with conducting illegal gambling businesses related to Got Skillz, Skillz 777, and Caf&#233; 62.

Stephanie Condric made her initial court appearance today before U.S. District Magistrate Judge Amanda M. Knapp of the Northern District of Ohio.&#160; If convicted, Condric faces a maximum penalty of five years in prison for conspiring to impede and impair the functions of the IRS, five years for conspiring to own and operate an illegal gambling business, five years for conducting an illegal gambling business, and three years for subscribing a false return.

Christopher Karasarides made his initial court appearance today before U.S. District Judge Donald Nugent of the Northern District of Ohio. If convicted, Christopher Karasarides faces a maximum penalty of five years in prison for the conspiracy count and three years in prison for each false tax return count.&#160;

Melissa Bragg made her initial appearance today before U.S. District Court Judge John R. Adams of the Northern District of Ohio.&#160; If convicted, she faces a maximum penalty of five years in prison for owning and operating an illegal gambling business.

Michael Moneypenny made his initial appearance today before U.S. District Court Magistrate Judge Amanda M. Knapp of the Northern District of Ohio.&#160; If convicted, he faces a maximum penalty of five years in prison for each count of owning and operating an illegal gambling business.

Christos Karasarides,&#160;Tiffany Kerekes, Isaiah Worlow, and Steven Fluharty will make their initial appearances at a later date.

A federal district court judge will determine any sentence after considering the U.S. Sentencing Guidelines and other statutory factors.&#160;

Acting Deputy Assistant Attorney General Stuart M. Goldberg of the Justice Department&#8217;s Tax Division and Interim U.S. Attorney Rebecca C. Lutzko for the Northern District of Ohio made the announcement.

IRS-Criminal Investigation, the Stark County, Ohio, Prosecutor&#8217;s Office, the U.S. Department of Treasury Office of Inspector General, Homeland Security Investigations, the Ohio Casino Control Commission, and the Ohio Organized Crime Investigations Commission &#8211; Major Crimes Task Force are investigating the case.

Trial Attorneys Sam Bean and Richard M. Rolwing of the Justice Department&#8217;s Tax Division and Assistant U.S. Attorney Aaron Howell of the Northern District of Ohio are prosecuting the case. &#160;

An indictment is merely an allegation and all defendants are presumed innocent until proven guilty beyond a reasonable doubt in a court of law.

</text></article><article><title>Man Arrested for Cyberstalking and Making Antisemitic Threats Targeting Synagogues and Jewish-Owned Businesses</title><url>https://justice.gov//opa/pr/man-arrested-cyberstalking-and-making-antisemitic-threats-targeting-synagogues-and-jewish</url><text>Donavon Parish, 28, of Hattiesburg, Mississippi, was arrested today and charged by indictment for allegedly engaging in cyberstalking and communicating interstate threats. The indictment alleges the defendant targeted his victims based on their actual or perceived religion, that is, the Jewish faith.

According to the indictment, in April and May 2022, the defendant used a voiceover internet protocol service to make a series of phone calls to synagogues and Jewish-owned businesses in the Eastern District of Pennsylvania. In these calls, Parish allegedly spoke to individuals answering the telephone calls on behalf of their respective institutions, at which time he repeatedly referenced the genocide of approximately six million Jewish people during the Holocaust, stating, among other things, &#8220;Heil Hitler,&#8221; &#8220;all Jews must die,&#8221; &#8220;we will put you in work camps,&#8221; &#8220;gas the Jews,&#8221; and &#8220;Hitler should have finished the job.&#8221;

If convicted, Parish faces a statutory maximum sentence of 50 years in prison. A federal district court judge will determine any sentence after considering the U.S. Sentencing Guidelines and other statutory factors.

Assistant Attorney General Matthew G. Olsen of the Justice Department&#8217;s National Security Division, U.S. Attorney Jacqueline C. Romero for the Eastern District of Pennsylvania and Assistant Director Robert Wells of the FBI&#8217;s Counterterrorism Division made the announcement.

The FBI is investigating the case.

The Eastern District of Pennsylvania and National Security Division&#8217;s Counterterrorism Section are prosecuting the case, with assistance from the Justice Department&#8217;s Civil Rights Division and the U.S. Attorney&#8217;s Office for the Southern District of Mississippi.

An indictment is merely an allegation. All defendants are presumed innocent until proven guilty beyond a reasonable doubt in a court of law.

</text></article><article><title>Two More Dublin Federal Correctional Officers Plead Guilty to Sexually Abusing Multiple Female Inmates</title><url>https://justice.gov//opa/pr/two-more-dublin-federal-correctional-officers-plead-guilty-sexually-abusing-multiple-female</url><text>As part of its ongoing investigation into Bureau of Prisons (BOP) officials at Federal Correctional Institution (FCI) Dublin, two more federal prison correctional officers were charged for sexually abusing multiple female inmates.

Nakie Nunley, 48, of Fairfield, California, and Andrew Jones, 35, of Pleasanton, California, were each charged by information with multiple counts of sexually abusing female inmates and then lying about the abuse to federal investigators. Both Nunley and Jones were employed as federal correctional officers at the time of the abuse. Both have agreed to plead guilty in written plea agreements, which were filed concurrently with the charging documents.

&#8220;The sexual abuse charges and guilty pleas announced today are the result of the Department of Justice&#8217;s sustained commitment to rooting out sexual misconduct at the Bureau of Prisons,&#8221; said Deputy Attorney General Lisa O. Monaco. &#8220;As these guilty pleas reflect, we will continue to hold accountable correctional officers who abuse their positions of trust and fail to humanely care for those in their custody.&#8221;

&#8220;The FBI&#160;is unrelenting in its protection of the civil rights of all individuals, including those who are&#160;incarcerated,&#8221; said FBI Deputy Director Paul Abbate. &#8220;No matter where these crimes&#160;occur, violence of any type&#160;destroys the&#160;safety&#160;and protection that every person deserves.&#160;We will&#160;continue to&#160;pursue investigations into&#160;any Bureau of Prisons official who abuses their position and&#160;assaults those in their care.&#8221;

&#8220;This office&#8217;s ongoing investigation into the conditions at FCI Dublin has revealed significant wrongdoing by multiple correctional officers at that facility,&#8221; said U.S. Attorney Ismail J. Ramsey for the Northern District of California. &#8220;The Department of Justice will not tolerate misconduct in the care of incarcerated persons. Correctional officers have an obligation to ensure the safety of incarcerated persons, and all Bureau of Prisons employees should view these latest two prosecutions as confirmation that the Department of Justice will do its part to ensure that those who stray from these obligations are held accountable.&#8221;

&#8220;Nunley and Jones are the seventh and eighth individuals charged with sexually abusing inmates at FCI Dublin. Five individuals, including the Warden and Chaplain, have been convicted of sexual abuse of inmates,&#8221; said Inspector General Michael E. Horowitz. &#8220;The Department of Justice Office of the Inspector General&#160; (DOJ-OIG) is continuing to investigate these heinous allegations at FCI Dublin and is aggressively pursuing justice for victims of sexual abuse at the hands of rogue BOP employees.&#8221;

&#8220;Incarcerated individuals should be able to serve their sentences without fear of being sexually assaulted by correctional institution staff,&#8221; said Special Agent in Charge Robert Tripp of FBI San Francisco Field Office. &#8220;Nakie Nunley and Andrew Jones abused their positions and will be held accountable. Protecting civil rights stands among the FBI&#8217;s highest priorities, and we will continue to investigate such claims as they come to light.&#8221;

Nunley was charged with engaging in sexual acts and sexual contacts with five women who were serving prison sentences at FCI Dublin at the time of the abuse. He was also charged with lying to federal investigators about the sexual abuse and writing sexually explicit notes with one of his victims. Jones was charged with engaging in sexual acts with three women who were serving prison sentences at FCI Dublin, as well as lying to federal investigators about sexually abusing one of these victims.&#160;

Nakie Nunley

Nunley was employed as a correctional officer at FCI&#160;Dublin where he supervised prisoners who worked in UNICOR, a trade name for the federal prison industries. All of Nunley&#8217;s victims worked at the UNICOR call center at the time of his abuse. According to his plea agreement, Nunley admits that between March 2020 and November 2021, he engaged in sexual acts with two prisoners, including having oral and vaginal sex with one victim and digitally penetrating another victim on multiple occasions. He also admitted that he engaged in illegal sexual contacts with three other prisoners and that he lied to federal investigators about sexually abusing his victims and about sending one of his victims sexually explicit notes.

In addition to the five victims, Nunley also admitted in his plea agreement that he sexually abused two other prisoners who worked at UNICOR. Nunley admitted that he digitally penetrated one victim&#8217;s vagina and caused her to touch his penis under his pants, resulting in him ejaculating in her hand. Nunley admitted that he caused another victim to perform oral sex on him.

Nunley also admitted that he engaged in other inappropriate behavior. For example, Nunley agreed that he wrote sexual notes to one of his victims and made sexual comments to multiple victims. Moreover, when one of his victims approached him about his conduct towards another victim, Nunley threatened her by raising with her the potential that she could be transferred to another facility and that she could lose her job. Similarly, Nunley admitted that he told another victim that if she wanted to keep her job at UNICOR, she needed to pull down her underwear and bend over. When she complied, Nunley slapped her buttocks several times.

Andrew Jones

Jones was employed as a correctional officer at FCI&#160;Dublin where he supervised prisoners who worked in the Food Services Department. According to his plea agreement, between July 2020 and June 2021, Jones admitted that he received oral sex from, or had sexual intercourse with, three female prisoners who worked for him in the FCI&#160;Dublin kitchen. Jones admitted that he sexually abused these prisoners in multiple places near the FCI&#160;Dublin kitchen, including a staff bathroom, a warehouse, and a room where kitchen utensils were kept. In addition, like Nunley, Jones admitted in his plea agreement that he engaged in improper conduct in addition to the conduct for which he was charged in the Information. Specifically, Jones admitted that he also had sexual intercourse and received oral sex from an additional victim on multiple other occasions between July and December 2020, and that he had sexual intercourse with yet another victim multiple times between March and June 2021.

FCI Dublin Investigation

As part of the Justice Department&#8217;s ongoing investigation into FCI Dublin, eight FCI Dublin correctional officers, including the former Warden, have been charged with crimes related to the sexual abuse of the female prisoners at the facility. In December 2022, former Warden Ray J. Garcia was convicted by a jury of sexually abusive conduct against three female victims and was sentenced to 70 months in prison for his crimes. To date, the tally of correctional officers charged with misconduct as part of the Justice Department&#8217;s investigation are as follows:









NAME





CASE NUMBER





STATUS









Warden Ray J. Garcia





4:21-cr-00429-YGR





Convicted on all counts by jury on Dec. 8, 2022; sentenced to 70 months in prison









CO John Bellhouse





4:22-cr-00066-YGR





Convicted on all counts by jury on June 5; sentencing scheduled for Oct. 27









Chaplain James Highhouse





4:22-cr-00016-HSG





Pleaded guilty on Feb. 24, 2022; sentenced to 84 months in prison









CO Enrique Chavez





4:22-cr-00104-YGR





Pleaded guilty on Oct. 27, 2022; sentenced to 20 months in prison









CO Ross Klinger





4:22-cr-00031-YGR





Pleaded guilty on Feb. 10, 2022; sentencing scheduled for Dec. 13









CO Darrel Smith (aka &#8220;Dirty Dick Smith&#8221;)





4:22-cr-00110-YGR





Indicted on April 13; status conference scheduled for Aug. 3









CO Nakie Nunley





4:23-cr-00213-HSG





Information and Plea Agreement filed on July 13









CO Andrew Jones





4:23-cr-00212-HSG





Information and Plea Agreement filed on July 13









DOJ-OIG and the FBI investigated the case.

Assistant U.S. Attorneys Molly K. Priedeman and Andrew Paulson for the Northern District of California, with the assistance of Madeline Wachs, Sara Slattery, Christine Tian, Claudia Hyslop, Leeya Kekona, and Kay Konopaske, are prosecuting the case.

</text></article><article><title>Co-Director of Think Tank Indicted for Acting as Unregistered Foreign Agent, Trafficking in Arms, Violating U.S. Sanctions Against Iran, and Making False Statements to Federal Agents</title><url>https://justice.gov//opa/pr/co-director-think-tank-indicted-acting-unregistered-foreign-agent-trafficking-arms-violating</url><text>A dual U.S.-Israeli citizen who serves as the co-director of a Maryland-based think tank was indicted today for allegedly engaging in multiple international criminal schemes.

According to court documents, Gal Luft, 57, is charged in an eight-count indictment with offenses related to willfully failing to register under the Foreign Agents Registration Act (FARA), arms trafficking, Iranian sanctions violations and making false statements to federal agents. Luft was arrested on Feb. 17 in the Republic of Cyprus based on the charges in the indictment. Luft subsequently fled after being released on bail while extradition proceedings were pending and remains a fugitive.

According to the allegations contained in the indictment, for years, Luft conspired with others in an effort to act within the United States to advance the interests of the People&#8217;s Republic of China (China) as agents of China-based principals, without registering as foreign agents as required under U.S. law. As part of this scheme, while serving as the co-director of a Maryland-based nonprofit think tank, Luft agreed to covertly recruit and pay, on behalf of principals based in China, a former high-ranking U.S. government official (Individual-1), including in 2016 while the former official was an adviser to the then-President-elect, to publicly support certain policies with respect to China without Luft or Individual-1 filing a registration statement as an agent of a foreign principal with the Attorney General of the United States, in violation of FARA.

Among other things, in the weeks before the 2016 U.S. presidential election, Luft and a co-conspirator (CC-1), who is a Chinese national and worked for a Chinese nongovernmental organization affiliated with a Chinese energy company, created a written &#8220;dialogue&#8221; between CC-1 and Individual-1, in which Luft wrote Individual-1&#8217;s responses and included information that was favorable to China. The dialogue was then published in a Chinese newspaper online and sent to, among others, individuals in the United States, including a journalist and professors at multiple U.S. universities. When Luft was writing the dialogue, CC-1 told Luft that &#8220;[i]n these articles, we do not want to spill all the beans yet, just enough to let &#8216;people&#8217; know he [i.e., Individual-1] is in the corridor of power to be. Just broad stroke policy consideration that leaves plenty of room for interpretation and imagination to be filled in later.&#8221; After the purported &#8220;conversations&#8221; were published, Luft told CC-1 that certain information, favorable to China, had been &#8220;tucked between the lines.&#8221; Shortly after the 2016 election, Luft and CC-1 also discussed possible roles Individual-1 might have in the incoming U.S. administration, and discussed Individual-1 taking a &#8220;silent trip&#8221; to China. Luft responded that &#8220;[w]e are debating about his role in the new admin. There are all kinds of considerations . . .We should talk ftf [i.e., face-to-face] as there can be a supremely unique opportunity for china.&#8221;

Second, Luft conspired with others and attempted to broker illicit arms transactions with, among others, certain Chinese individuals and entities. In his role as a broker or middleman, Luft worked to find both buyers and sellers of certain weapons and other materials, without a license to do so as required under U.S. law, in violation of the Arms Export Control Act. Among other things, Luft worked to broker a deal for Chinese companies to sell certain weapons to Libya, including anti-tank launchers, grenade launchers and mortar rounds (which Luft and his associates referred to in coded language as &#8220;toys&#8221;). Luft also worked to broker deals for certain weapons to be sold to the United Arab Emirates, including arial bombs and rockets. Luft further worked to broker deals for certain weapons to be sold by a Chinese company to Kenya, including unmanned aerial vehicles (UAVs) &#8211; and specifically &#8220;strike&#8221; UAVs, which Luft acknowledged &#8220;[t]he US doesn&#8217;t want to sell[, . . .] hence the opportunity.&#8221; Luft also discussed brokering a deal for weapons to Qatar, and told CC-1 that Israel was &#8220;not a good fit&#8221; as the middleman for the deal because it had the &#8220;[s]ame problem the [] Q [i.e., Qataris] have w uncle [i.e., the United States]. Need a third party. . . . I will activate.&#8221; In his role as a broker for illicit arms deals, Luft worked on a commission basis, and traveled to meetings and received and passed on documentation needed to secure the deals. During a voluntary interview with U.S. law enforcement in which he was asked questions about his involvement in arms trafficking, Luft made multiple false statements, including that he had just been checking prices for a friend and had not sought to engage in or profit from arms deals.

Third, Luft conspired with others and attempted to broker deals for Iranian oil &#8211; which he directed an associate to refer to as &#8220;Brazilian&#8221; oil in an effort to conceal the activity and evade sanctions &#8211; in violation of U.S. sanctions against Iran and the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (IEEPA). In his role as a broker or middleman, Luft solicited buyers and passed on pricing and other information. One offer letter for Iranian oil that Luft received noted that the &#8220;origin&#8221; of the oil was &#8220;Iranian / It can be presented as UAE origin without Iranian papers.&#8221; He also assisted in setting up meetings between Iranian representatives and a Chinese energy company for the purpose of discussing oil deals. During a voluntary interview with U.S. law enforcement in which he was asked about his role brokering deals in Iranian oil, Luft made multiple false statements, including that he had tried to prevent oil deals with Iran and had not been present during meetings with the Chinese energy company and Iranians.

Luft is charged with the following offenses, which carry the maximum prison terms listed below. A federal district court judge will determine any sentence after considering the U.S. Sentencing Guidelines and other statutory factors.









Count&#160;





Charge





Maximum Prison Term









One





Conspiracy to violate the Foreign Agents Registration Act





Five years









Two





Conspiracy to violate the Arms Export Control Act





Five years









Three





Violation of the Arms Export Control Act (relating to Libya)





20 years









Four





Violation of the Arms Export Control Act (relating to the United Arab Emirates)&#160;





20 years









Five





Violation of the Arms Export Control Act (relating to Kenya)





20 years









Six





Making false statements





Five years









Seven





Conspiracy to violate the International Emergency Economic Powers Act





20 years









Eight





Making false statements





Five years









The FBI New York Field Office and FBI&#8217;s Counterintelligence Division are investigating the case, with valuable assistance provided by the IRS-Criminal Investigation (IRS-CI) and the Justice Department&#8217;s Office of International Affairs.

Assistant U.S. Attorneys Daniel C. Richenthal and Catherine Ghosh for the Southern District of New York and Trial Attorney Scott Claffee of the National Security Division&#8217;s Counterintelligence and Export Control Section are prosecuting the case.

If you have any information about Luft&#8217;s whereabouts, please contact your local FBI office or the nearest American Embassy or Consulate. Tips can be reported anonymously and can also be reported online at tips.fbi.gov.

An indictment is merely an allegation. All defendants are presumed innocent until proven guilty beyond a reasonable doubt in a court of law.

</text></article><article><title>Deputy Attorney General Lisa O. Monaco Delivers Remarks at the Plenary Session of the ASEAN &amp; G-7 Justice Ministers&#8217; Interface</title><url>https://justice.gov//opa/speech/deputy-attorney-general-lisa-o-monaco-delivers-remarks-plenary-session-asean-g-7-justice</url><text>Remarks as Prepared for Delivery

I am honored to represent the United States and the Department of Justice, and to join distinguished colleagues from the ASEAN nations and the G7.

Together we share a commitment to upholding the rule of law, and keeping our citizens safe &#8212; safe from an ever-evolving set of threats, including: &#160;cybercrime; transnational organized crime and drug trafficking; and the misuse of critical and disruptive technologies in a manner to threaten human rights and undermine democracy.

We cannot face these threats alone.

We gather today to join forces against unprecedented threats; with resolve to strengthen our partnerships &#8212; partnerships that are critical to protecting those we serve.

I want to start by discussing cybercrime. Transnational cyber criminals and nation-state cyber actors have become more aggressive, more sophisticated and more brazen.

This blended threat of nation-state cyber actors and criminal groups poses a significant threat to the functioning and stability of our societies and our economies.

In the U.S., our prosecutors and agents are working with partners across the globe to take down cybercriminals, seize the proceeds of their crimes, and disrupt the criminal ecosystem that allows them to flourish.

In all of this, our international partnerships are critical &#8212; there is not a cyber investigation today that does not involve an international component.

For example, earlier this year, working with partners across the globe, we disrupted Bitzlato, a cryptocurrency exchange, and Chipmixer, a service designed to obscure cryptocurrency on the blockchain. These platforms were used by criminals to launder $3.7 billion in illicit proceeds.

Similarly, in January, we went after the Hive ransomware group by engaging in what I&#8217;ve referred to as a &#8220;21st Century digital stakeout.&#8221; By infiltrating the Hive ransomware group&#8217;s key servers, we were able to capture its decryption keys and provide them to victims around the world. As a result, we prevented more than $130 million in ransom payments.

These actions, to take down major cybercriminals and their networks that operate and claim victims across the globe, depend on international cooperation, with partners like you.

We are now on our front foot in the fight against cybercrime. But we must maintain the momentum.

Only through international teamwork can we turn the tables on malicious cyber actors.

The threats we face don&#8217;t stop at the keyboard or take place only in cyberspace.

Just as we have gone on the offensive against cyber criminals around the globe, the Department of Justice continues to wage a relentless campaign to disrupt the violent drug cartels that fuel violence and threatens the rule of law around the world.

Today, the greatest drug threat we face in the United States is from illicit synthetic drugs &#8212; the most deadly of which is fentanyl.

Last year our Centers for Disease Control estimate that more than 110,000 Americans died from overdose &#8211; 70% of those from fentanyl.

Fentanyl is a uniquely deadly drug. It poses a singular threat not only because the smallest of doses can be lethal, but because fentanyl does not occur in nature &#8211; it is entirely man-made, and in potentially limitless supply.

The cartels responsible for trafficking this poison originated in Mexico &#8212; but make no mistake &#8212; they operate globally.

To my colleagues &#8212; I urge you to recognize that while you may not see this deadly killer now &#8212; you will. Fentanyl trafficking is a serious threat to all of us and is an area ripe for future cooperation.

That means going after the chemical companies that manufacture and export fentanyl precursor chemicals &#8212; many of which are in China. It means taking down the network of illicit laboratories that use those chemicals to produce the drug; it means holding accountable the global cartel traffickers that peddle it to unsuspecting consumers across the globe and the sophisticated money-launders who enable it all.

In recent months, we have indicted criminals at every step in the supply and delivery chain: executives at Chinese chemical companies and Mexican drug cartel leaders, money launderers and hitmen; producers, suppliers and dealers in the U.S. and around the globe.

We&#8217;ve strengthened our partnerships around the world to enable us to better detect and disrupt distribution channels. This has been possible only through working with our foreign partners, including countries present here today.

We stand ready to work with all who will work with us to send a message to the transnational organized crime groups that poison our communities &#8211; there must be no safe haven.

I want to close with a threat over-the-horizon: the rise of disruptive technologies that, when misused, threaten the freedoms of our citizens, our values, and the rule of law.

To combat this threat, we&#8217;ve launched the Disruptive Technology Strike Force. It&#8217;s a collaboration of U.S. law enforcement agencies &#8211; led by the Justice Department and the Commerce Department. The Strike Force is focused on preventing the unlawful transfer of critical technologies that could be used to undermine our national security, to repress populations, to suppress dissent, and to fuel our adversaries&#8217; drive for a military and national security edge.

Our message is clear: We will not tolerate those who violate U.S. laws to use advanced technology to threaten our collective national security and undermine the rule of law around the world.

I am grateful to all of you for engaging with us to combat these threats through our traditional channels of cooperation &#8211; the sharing of law enforcement information, mutual legal assistance, and extradition.

I am grateful to join you today and look forward to our continued partnerships.

</text></article><article><title>Former Eastern Kentucky Correctional Supervisor Indicted for Covering Up the Assault of a Restrained Inmate</title><url>https://justice.gov//opa/pr/former-eastern-kentucky-correctional-supervisor-indicted-covering-assault-restrained-inmate</url><text>A former Eastern Kentucky Correctional Complex (EKCC) sergeant was indicted by a federal jury in Lexington, Kentucky, for three counts of obstruction based on his efforts to cover up the assault of a restrained inmate by multiple officers that he supervised.&#160;

The indictment alleges that on July 24, 2018, Sgt. Eric L. Nantell, 47, watched lower-ranking EKCC correctional officers assault a nonviolent inmate who was lying face-down, wearing handcuffs and leg shackles, and isolated in a prison shower cell. The indictment specifically alleges that Nantell, who at that time held the rank of sergeant, stood outside of the shower during the assault and that he later attempted to cover up what happened by lying to the EKCC supervisor assigned to investigate the incident, a Kentucky State Police (KSP) detective, and a special agent of the FBI.&#160;

Nantell faces a maximum of 20 years in prison for each charge alleging that he lied to Kentucky state officials. Nantell faces a maximum of five years in prison for lying to the FBI. A federal district court judge will determine any sentence after considering the U.S. Sentencing Guidelines and other statutory factors.

Assistant Attorney General Kristen Clarke of the Justice Department&#8217;s Civil Rights Division; U.S. Attorney Carlton S. Shier IV for the Eastern District of Kentucky; Assistant Director Luis Quesada of the FBI&#8217;s Criminal Investigative Division; Special Agent in Charge Jodi Cohen of the FBI Louisville Field Office; and Colonel Phillip Burnett Jr. Commissioner of the KSP made the announcement.

The FBI, the KSP and the Kentucky Justice and Public Safety Cabinet conducted the investigation.

Assistant U.S. Attorney Zach Dembo and Mary Melton for the Eastern District of Kentucky and Trial Attorney Thomas Johnson of the Civil Rights Division&#8217;s Criminal Section are prosecuting the case.

An indictment is merely an allegation. All defendants are presumed innocent until proven guilty beyond a reasonable doubt in a court of law.

</text></article><article><title>U.S. Army Financial Counselor Charged with Defrauding Gold Star Families</title><url>https://justice.gov//opa/pr/us-army-financial-counselor-charged-defrauding-gold-star-families</url><text>A Monmouth County, New Jersey, financial counselor with the U.S. Army and major in the U.S. Army Reserves who allegedly defrauded two dozen Gold Star families has been indicted.

Caz Craffy, aka Carz Craffey, 41, of Colts Neck, New Jersey, is charged by indictment with six counts of wire fraud and one count each of securities fraud, making false statements in a loan application, committing acts furthering a personal financial interest, and making false statements to a federal agency. Craffy is expected to make his initial appearance today before U.S. Magistrate Judge Tonianne J. Bongiovanni at the Trenton Federal Courthouse.

&#8220;Stealing from Gold Star families whose loved ones made the ultimate sacrifice in service to our nation is a shameful crime,&#8221; said Attorney General Merrick B. Garland. &#8220;As alleged in the indictment, the defendant in this case used his position as an Army financial counselor to defraud Gold Star families, steal their money, and enrich himself. Predatory conduct that targets the families of fallen American service members will be met with the full force of the Justice Department.&#8221;

&#8220;The families of our fallen service members have laid the dearest sacrifice on the altar of freedom,&#8221; said U.S. Attorney Phillip R. Sellinger for the District of New Jersey. &#8220;These Gold Star families deserve our utmost respect and compassion, as well as some small measure of financial security from a grateful nation. They must be off-limits for fraudsters. But, as the indictment alleges, this defendant took advantage of his role as an Army financial counselor to prey upon these families, using lies and deception to steer their investments in a way that would make him money. There is no room for those who seek to rip off families of fallen servicemembers to make a buck. We will use every means at our disposal to ensure that those who defraud military families are held accountable.&#8221;

&#8220;Those who prey on the family members of fallen soldiers, will be sought out and held accountable,&#8221; said Special Agent in Charge Joel Kirch of the Department of the Army Criminal Investigation Division, Northeast Field Office. &#8220;The hard work, long hours, and dedication of our partners within the Task Force, from the U.S. Attorney&#8217;s Office, Defense Criminal Investigative Service, FBI, Homeland Security Investigations, and our own investigative analyst, resulted in this investigation&#8217;s swift resolution.&#8221;

&#8220;The families of service members who lost their lives while serving their country deserve to be treated with compassion, dignity and respect by individuals entrusted to assist them in obtaining survivor benefits,&#8221; said Principal Deputy Director James R. Ives of the Defense Criminal Investigative Service (DCIS), the law enforcement arm of the DoD Office of Inspector General. &#8220;Today&#8217;s announcement reflects DCIS and our law enforcement partners&#8217; steadfast commitment to holding accountable those who use their official positions to take advantage of grieving military families.&#8221;

&#8220;Gold Star families are given a title no one would choose because it means they&#8217;ve paid the ultimate sacrifice for this country,&#8221; said Special in Charge James E. Dennehy of the Newark FBI. &#8220;The soldier, sailor, marine or airman they loved died during a time of conflict &#8211; defending this nation. They are given money and assistance to help ease the burden that comes with losing their loved one, however no amount of money can replace what they&#8217;ve lost. We allege Craffy took advantage of his position and defrauded families already going through a tremendous amount of suffering.&#8221;

&#8220;Craffy disgraced the position he was entrusted in to care for our nation&#8217;s military families when he allegedly took advantage of them during a vulnerable time of grief,&#8221; said Special Agent in Charge Ricky J. Patel Homeland Security Investigations Newark. &#8220;No family, especially our Gold Star families, should have to face further heartache after a loved one&#8217;s death by having their financial security ripped out from under them by fraudsters.&#8221;

According to documents filed in this case and statements made in court:

When a member of the Armed Services dies during active duty, his or her surviving beneficiary, now a member of a Gold Star family, is entitled to a $100,000 death gratuity and the soldier&#8217;s life insurance of up to $400,000. These payments are disbursed to the beneficiary in a matter of weeks or months following the servicemember&#8217;s death. To assist the beneficiaries in this time of need, the military provides a number of services to the servicemember&#8217;s family, including the assistance of a financial counselor.

From November 2017 to January 2023, Craffy was a civilian employee of the U.S. Army, working as a financial counselor with the Casualty Assistance Office. He was also a major in the U.S. Army Reserves, where he has been enlisted since 2003. Craffy was responsible for providing general financial education to the surviving beneficiaries. He was prohibited from offering any personal opinions regarding the surviving beneficiary&#8217;s benefits decisions. Craffy was not permitted to participate personally in any government matter in which he had an outside financial interest. However, without telling the Army, Craffy simultaneously maintained outside employment with two separate financial investment firms.

Craffy used his position as an Army financial counselor to identify and target Gold Star families and other military families. He encouraged the Gold Star families to invest their survivor benefits in investment accounts that he managed in his outside, private employment. Based upon Craffy&#8217;s false representations and omissions, the vast majority of the Gold Star families mistakenly believed that Craffy&#8217;s management of their money was done on behalf of and with the Army&#8217;s authorization.

From May 2018 to November 2022, Craffy obtained more than $9.9 million from Gold Star families to invest in accounts managed by Craffy in his private capacity. Once in control of this money, Craffy repeatedly executed trades, often without the family&#8217;s authorization. These unauthorized trades earned Craffy high commissions. During the timeframe of the alleged scheme, the Gold Star family accounts had lost more than $3.4 million, while Craffy personally earned more than $1.4 million in commissions, drawn from the family accounts.

The wire fraud and securities fraud charges are each punishable by a maximum of 20 years in prison. The charge of submitting a false statement on a loan application is punishable by a maximum of two years in prison. The charges of acts affecting a personal interest and false statements to a federal agent are each punishable by five years in prison. All counts but the securities fraud count are also punishable by a maximum fine of either $250,000 or twice the gain or loss from the offense, whichever is greatest. The securities fraud count is punishable by a maximum fine of either $5 million or twice the gain or loss from the offense, whichever is greatest.

The U.S. Securities and Exchange Commission (SEC) also filed a civil complaint against Craffy today based on the same and additional conduct. Craffy has been permanently prohibited from association with any member of the Financial Industry Regulatory Authority Inc. (FINRA).

U.S. Attorney Sellinger credited special agents of the Department of the Army Criminal Investigation Division, under the direction of Special Agent in Charge Kirch; special agents of DCIS, under the direction of Principal Deputy Director Ives; special agents of the FBI, under the direction of Special Agent in Charge Dennehy; and special agents of Homeland Security Investigations Newark, under the direction of Special Agent in Charge Patel with the investigation leading to the indictment. He also expressed appreciation for the Securities and Exchange Commission, under the direction of Gurbir S. Grewal, Director, Division of Enforcement, and FINRA, under the direction of Acting Head of Enforcement Christopher J. Kelly.

The government is represented by Assistant U.S. Attorneys Martha K. Nye of the Criminal Division in Trenton, and Carolyn Silane of the Criminal Division in Newark.

The charges and allegations contained in the indictment are merely accusations, and the defendant is presumed innocent unless and until proven guilty.

&#160;





Craffy Indictment





</text></article><article><title>Foreign National Indicted for International Drug Trafficking</title><url>https://justice.gov//opa/pr/foreign-national-indicted-international-drug-trafficking</url><text>A Mexican national made his initial appearance in the District of Columbia today to face international cocaine and marijuana trafficking charges.&#160; &#160;

According to court documents, between 2000 and 2010, Eleazar Medina Rojas, aka Chelelo, 51, was a high-ranking member of the Zetas, an international drug trafficking organization allied with the Gulf Cartel. Together, the Zetas and the Gulf Cartel, known collectively as &#8220;The Company,&#8221; was a violent, transnational drug trafficking organization based in Mexico that was engaged in the manufacture, distribution, and importation of ton quantities of cocaine and marijuana from Mexico, Colombia, Guatemala, Panama, and elsewhere into the United States. Medina Rojas was also the &#8220;plaza boss&#8221; for the city of Monterrey, Nuevo Leon, Mexico, controlling the Zeta&#8217;s drug trafficking activities in that area.

In May 2013, a grand jury in the District of Columbia returned a fourth superseding indictment against Medina Rojas. In December 2018, Mexican authorities arrested Medina Rojas pursuant to a provisional arrest requested by the United States. Medina Rojas remained detained in Mexico pending his extradition. He was extradited from Mexico to the United States on July 6.

Medina Rojas is charged with one count of conspiracy to manufacture and distribute five kilograms or more of cocaine and over 1,000 kilograms of marijuana intending and knowing that those substances would be imported into the United States.&#160; If convicted, he faces a mandatory minimum sentence of 10 years in prison and a maximum penalty of life imprisonment.&#160;

Assistant Attorney General Kenneth A. Polite, Jr. of the Justice Department&#8217;s Criminal Division and DEA Administrator Anne Milgram made the announcement.

The DEA Houston Division is investigating the case with assistance from the DEA Mexico City Country Office.

Trial Attorneys Kirk Handrich and Janet Turnbull of the Criminal Division&#8217;s Narcotic and Dangerous Drug Section are prosecuting the case. The Justice Department&#8217;s Office of International Affairs worked with law enforcement partners in Mexico to secure the arrest and extradition of Medina Rojas. The Office of Enforcement Operations also provided significant assistance.&#160;&#160;

An indictment is merely an allegation. All defendants are presumed innocent until proven guilty beyond a reasonable doubt in a court of law.

</text></article><article><title>Cooperation Between United States and Mexican Law Enforcement Leads to Significant Actions Against Transnational Drug Trafficking Organization</title><url>https://justice.gov//opa/pr/cooperation-between-united-states-and-mexican-law-enforcement-leads-significant-actions</url><text>Today, U.S. and Mexican law enforcement announced significant enforcement actions against a prolific transnational drug trafficking organization operating in Nogales, Sonora, along the U.S.-Mexico border.

After extensive bilateral cooperation between the United States and Mexico, Mexico&#8217;s Attorney General&#8217;s Office, Fiscal&#237;a General de la Rep&#250;blica (FGR) &#8211; conducted a significant enforcement operation on June 23, 2023, to dismantle a prolific transnational drug trafficking organization operating in Nogales, Sonora, along the U.S.&#8211;Mexico border. The operation resulted in the arrest of five people and the seizure of 120,000 fentanyl pills, 15 pounds of methamphetamine, 17 pounds of heroin, 15 pounds of cocaine, three assault rifles, one 9mm handgun, and a vehicle.

In addition, seven U.S.-based coordinators and operators with alleged ties to the same drug-trafficking organization have been arrested and indicted in the United States. Gerardo Bernal-Mazon, 29, Ashley Bernal, 31, Jessica Yesenia Valenzuela, 32, and Delyanira Lovio, 29, all of Nogales, Arizona, Juan Murillo, 48, of Rio Rico, Arizona, and Lilian Sugey Siegfried, 38, of Tucson, Arizona, were indicted by a federal grand jury on drug trafficking charges on Feb. 2. George Armenta-Vasquez, 45, of Nogales, Sonora, Mexico, was indicted by a federal grand jury on Jan. 25.

&#8220;Transnational drug trafficking organizations pose an unprecedented public safety threat to both the United States and Mexico,&#8221; said Attorney General Merrick B. Garland. &#8220;These coordinated law enforcement actions demonstrate the success our countries can have when we work together to meet that threat.&#8221;

This effort is part of an Organized Crime Drug Enforcement Task Forces (OCDETF) operation. OCDETF identifies, disrupts, and dismantles the highest-level criminal organizations that threaten the United States using a prosecutor-led, intelligence-driven, multi-agency approach. Additional information about the OCDETF Program can be found at www.justice.gov/OCDETF.

Drug Enforcement Administration (DEA) &#8211; Nogales led the investigation in the United States, in concert with the DEA Mexico City Country Office, Homeland Security Investigations (HSI) &#8211; Nogales, U.S. Customs and Border Protection&#8217;s U.S. Border Patrol, U.S. Customs and Border Protection&#8217;s Office of Field Operation, and the Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms and Explosives &#8211; Tucson. Support from DEA&#8211;Mexico City Country Office and FGR&#8217;s Agencia de Investigaci&#243;n Criminal (AIC) was critical in providing coordination between United States and Mexican law enforcement agencies. The U.S. Department of Justice&#8217;s Office of International Affairs provided assistance. The U.S. Attorney&#8217;s Office, District of Arizona, Tucson, is prosecuting the seven individuals named above.

</text></article><article><title>Deputy Attorney General Lisa O. Monaco Delivers Remarks at the Plenary Session of the G-7 Justice Ministers&#8217; Meeting</title><url>https://justice.gov//opa/speech/deputy-attorney-general-lisa-o-monaco-delivers-remarks-plenary-session-g-7-justice</url><text>Remarks as Prepared for Delivery July 7 at Approximately 2:40 p.m. local Tokyo time / 1:40 a.m. ET

As we gather today, rogue nation-states actively seek to undermine the global rules-based order.

From Ukrainian battlefields to online information domains, they seek new ways to hollow out our democratic institutions to entrench their power, subvert dissent, and sever the multilateral alliances that underpin global peace and security.

No country alone can defend these norms &#8211; the norms that, rooted in the rule of law, underpin every just and free society.

But by locking arms, and working together, we can hold these autocracies accountable and make the world a safer place.

The most challenging rebuke of the rules-based international order is without a doubt Russia&#8217;s continuing unjustified and brutal invasion of Ukraine.

For nearly 500 days, the Russian regime and military have executed a new campaign of brutality against the Ukrainian people.

They have bombed hospitals and apartment buildings; committed sexual violence against women, men, and children; carried out execution-style murders; and illegally removed thousands of Ukrainian children to Russia or Russian-occupied territory.

There can be no mistake &#8211; Russia has committed war crimes and crimes against humanity in Ukraine.

Russia&#8217;s unjustified and unprovoked actions seek to destroy a nation and its democratic institutions, because Russia sees those institutions as a threat.

Russia&#8217;s actions aim to discredit the entire premise that law &#8211; and global norms &#8211; matter.

Russia&#8217;s continued war against Ukraine poses a serious threat to global peace and stability. Thankfully, the countries gathered here are steadfast in their commitment to Ukraine&#160;&#8211; for as long as it takes&#160;&#8211; and to ensuring accountability for the atrocities committed by the Kremlin.

On accountability, we continue to collaborate effectively on investigations of war crimes. And with respect to aggression, with thanks to the leadership of Commissioner Reynders, earlier this week we saw the landmark opening of the International Center for the Prosecution of the Crime of Aggression against Ukraine &#8211; ICPA&#160;&#8211; under the auspices of Eurojust in The Hague.

I am pleased to announce that we have assigned a Department of Justice attorney as Special Prosecutor for the Crime of Aggression, who will serve as our representative to ICPA.

Together, we have also made important progress in fighting Russian illicit finance. The G7 has been a leader on limiting Russia&#8217;s access to the global financial system and degrading its ability to fuel its war machine.

REPO, the G7 Plus Russian Elites, Proxies, and Oligarchs Task Force &#8211; working with the EU&#8217;s Freeze &amp; Seize Task Force and our own Task Force KleptoCapture &#8211; are enforcing sanctions, export restrictions, and economic countermeasures in response to Russia&#8217;s aggression.

Since the start of the war, through the Justice Department&#8217;s Task Force KleptoCapture:

We have restrained over $500 million in assets of Russian oligarchs and others who prop up the Russian regime and have evaded U.S. economic countermeasures.

We have indicted over 30 individuals accused of sanctions evasion, export control violations, money laundering, and other crimes.

And, with the help of our international partners, arrests have been made in over half a dozen countries, with a view towards extradition to the United States.

And now, under the Japanese leadership of the G7, we are coming together to help Ukraine strengthen the rule of law and fight corruption&#160;&#8211; through the Anti-Corruption Task Force for Ukraine&#160;&#8211; or ACT for Ukraine.

As our friend and colleague, Ukrainian Prosecutor General Andriy Kostin, has so eloquently put it: &#8220;Ukraine has two enemies: one external, Russia, and one internal, which is corruption.&#8221;

We enthusiastically embrace the decision of the G7 to aid Ukraine&#8217;s commitment to fight the internal enemy of corruption.

We have long been committed to this task in partnership with Ukraine.

For more than a decade, including throughout the period of Russia&#8217;s invasion, our Department of Justice international police capacity building unit has been on the ground in Ukraine. They have been working with Ukrainian counterparts to build a police force that is community-focused and committed to democratic policing.

And I am very happy to say that just last month, we, at the U.S. Department of Justice, sent one of our veteran federal prosecutors &#8211; Jared Kimball &#8211; to be resident in Kiev, with a focus on rule of law and anti-corruption capacity building.

I urge each of us here today to nominate a representative to the new G7 Anti-Corruption Task Force &#8211; and the United States would propose that Mr. Kimball be our member. He is available to work with all of you.

Unfortunately, Russia is not alone in its effort to degrade the international rules-based system. China, Iran, and others harbor variations on the same ambition.

From plots to murder dissidents to campaigns of intimidation, unlawful imprisonment and violence, autocratic regimes work to extinguish dissent within their borders and around the globe.

In January, the Justice Department exposed a murder-for-hire plot directed against a prominent critic of the Iranian regime living and working in the United States. The plot was meant to silence her for speaking out against human rights abuses in Iran and for speaking up for the rights of women.

Likewise, the Chinese government also goes to great lengths to silence dissent outside of China.

Just last month, a federal jury in New York convicted three individuals for their role in China&#8217;s involuntary repatriation program&#160;&#8211; &#8220;Operation Fox Hunt.&#8221; The defendants engaged in a campaign of harassment and coercion to force the victims to return to China from the United States.

And we know that these malicious actors &#8211; in particular, the government of China &#8211; are also increasingly offering to help build the capacity, through training, facilities, and equipment, of the security sectors of other countries. &#160;

It is essential, as the Japanese Presidency has proposed at the Ministerial, that we coordinate our rule of law assistance to counter this threat. We know that what malign nation states are offering is not truly &#8220;rule of law&#8221; but rather a system designed to repress, not protect, human rights and fundamental freedoms. &#160;&#160;

And we must work together to deny repressive regimes the technology they abuse and exploit to monitor, harass, and intimidate.

Earlier this year, the Justice Department launched the Disruptive Technology Strike Force. A collaboration between the U.S. Department of Justice and the U.S. Department of Commerce, the mission of the Strike Force is to prevent foreign adversaries from obtaining critical advanced technologies that certain governments might abuse to repress their people.

But our focus is not only on the transfer of sensitive technologies, but also on how U.S. investment might be harnessed by autocratic regimes to develop those sensitive technologies, to fuel their military advantage, and to repress their own and other populations.

So, the United States is exploring how to monitor and, in some cases, restrict the flow of private capital in critical sectors. We will ensure that our own &#8220;outbound investment&#8221; in dual-use technology doesn&#8217;t provide our adversaries with a national security advantage, or new repressive powers. International partnerships will be absolutely critical if these new safeguards are to work.

In sum, our adversaries are not content with the status quo &#8211; they are increasingly creative, brazen, and malicious in their efforts to weaken democracies, to sow discord, and to spread corruption across the globe.

Only by defending the rule of law, protecting civil liberties, and holding fast to the values that underpin our countries can we defeat these autocratic regimes &#8211; and we can and must do so by working together.

I look forward to our continued partnership on these critical issues. Thank you.

</text></article><article><title>Texas Man Sentenced to 90 Consecutive Life Sentences for 2019 Mass Shooting at Walmart in El Paso, Texas, Killing 23 People and Injuring 22 Others</title><url>https://justice.gov//opa/pr/texas-man-sentenced-90-consecutive-life-sentences-2019-mass-shooting-walmart-el-paso-texas</url><text>A Texas man was sentenced to 90 consecutive life sentences in prison for carrying out a mass shooting at the Cielo Vista Walmart in El Paso, Texas, on Aug. 3, 2019, killing 23 people and injuring 22 more.

On Feb. 8, Patrick Wood Crusius, 24, pleaded guilty to a 90-count indictment with 45 counts of violating the Matthew Shepard and James Byrd Jr. Hate Crimes Prevention Act and 45 counts of using a firearm during and in relation to crimes of violence. The defendant was sentenced to one life sentence for each count in the indictment, including for hate crime acts that resulted in the deaths of Andre Anchondo, Jordan Anchondo, Arturo Benavides, Jorge Calvillo Garcia, Guillermo Garcia, Leonardo Campos, Angelina Englisbee, Maria Flores, Raul Flores, Adolfo Cerros Hernandez, Alexander Hoffmann, David Johnson, Luis Alfonso Juarez, Maria Legarreta Rothe, Maribel Loya Hernandez, Ivan Filiberto Manzano, Gloria Irma Marquez, Elsa Mendoza Marquez, Margie Reckard, Sara Regalado Monreal, Javier Amir Rodriguez, Teresa Sanchez, and Juan Velasquez.

Crusius was also sentenced for 22 counts of hate crime acts that caused bodily injury and involved attempts to kill 22 people injured in the shooting. In addition to the hate crimes, Crusius was sentenced for 45 firearms violations, including 23 counts of using a firearm in a federal crime of violence resulting in death, and 22 counts of using a firearm in a federal crime of violence.

&#8220;No one in this country should have to live in fear of hate-fueled violence &#8211; that they will be targeted because of what they look like or where they are from,&#8221; said Attorney General Merrick B. Garland. &#8220;The 90 consecutive life sentences announced today guarantee that Patrick Crusius will spend the rest of his life in prison for his deadly, racist rampage in El Paso. We are grateful to the victims and their family members who have spent the last three days bravely sharing the devastation and pain they endured because of Crusius&#8217;s horrendous crimes. The Justice Department&#8217;s commitment to combating hate crimes is unwavering.&#8221;

&#8220;We are hopeful today's sentence brings a sense of justice, but the memories of the victims and our support for their families and the survivors doesn't end here,&#8221; said FBI Director Christopher Wray. &#8220;FBI employees are members of the communities we serve, and in El Paso, we will continue to help our neighbors and friends heal for as long as it takes. When anyone in our communities is threatened with violence or hate, the FBI will work with them side by side to fight for justice and we will hold the perpetrators accountable.&#8221;

&#8220;We hope this sentence will bring some small measure of justice to those impacted by this massacre of innocent people targeted for no other reason than their Hispanic identity and national origin,&#8221; said Assistant Attorney General Kristen Clarke of the Justice Department's Civil Rights Division. &#8220;This hate crime, that extinguished the lives of 23 innocent people, stands as one of the most horrific acts of white nationalist-driven violence in modern times. We lift up the legacies of those who lost their lives and those who survived this tragedy and will ensure that they are never forgotten. Make no mistake, white nationalist hate crimes have no place in our country today and we must bring every tool at our disposal to confront this threat.&#8221;

&#8220;This defendant systematically targeted and killed 23 innocent people, injured 22 more, and forever changed the lives of so many others who witnessed this horrific event, leaving a haunting scar on the El Paso/Ciudad Juarez community and beyond,&#8221; said First Assistant U.S. Attorney Margaret Leachman for the Western District of Texas. &#8220;While today&#8217;s sentence cannot possibly replace the lives lost or undo the harm done to the survivors and those otherwise impacted by this horrific event, it is our hope this sentence of 90 consecutive life terms brings some finality and peace to those effected. The U.S. Attorney&#8217;s Office for the Western District of Texas will continue to aggressively prosecute those who commit violence because of bias or hate, seeking justice in the names of the victims and their loved ones.&#8221;

According to court documents, Crusius previously admitted that he killed and wounded people at the Walmart because of the actual and perceived national origin of the people he expected to be at the Walmart. He further admitted that he intended to kill everyone he shot.

Crusius also admitted he wrote a manifesto, titled &#8220;An Inconvenient Truth,&#8221; and uploaded it to the internet minutes before he commenced his attack. In it, he characterized himself as a white nationalist, motivated to kill Hispanics because they were immigrating to the United States. Crusius admitted to selecting El Paso, a border city, as his target to dissuade Mexican and other Hispanic immigrants from coming to the United States.

The FBI investigated the case, in partnership with the El Paso Police Department; the Bureau of Alcohol, Tobacco, Firearms, and Explosives (ATF); the Texas Department of Public Safety; the El Paso County Sheriff&#8217;s Office; the El Paso County Office of the Medical Examiner; the Allen Police Department; and the Dallas Police Department.

Assistant U.S. Attorneys Ian Hanna, Gregory McDonald, and Patricia Acosta for the Western District of Texas&#8217; El Paso Division and Trial Attorneys Kyle Boynton of the Civil Rights Division&#8217;s Criminal Section and Michael Warbel of the Criminal Division&#8217;s Capital Case Section prosecuted the case.

For more information about the department&#8217;s efforts to combat and prevent hate crimes, visit www.justice.gov/hatecrimes.

</text></article><article><title>Justice Department Announces Charges Against China-Based Chemical Manufacturing Companies and Arrests of Executives in Fentanyl Manufacturing</title><url>https://justice.gov//opa/video/justice-department-announces-charges-against-china-based-chemical-manufacturing-companies</url><text>The Justice Department today announced the arrest of two individuals and the unsealing of three indictments in the Southern and Eastern Districts of New York charging China-based companies and their employees with crimes related to fentanyl production, distribution, and sales resulting from precursor chemicals.

</text></article><article><title>Florida Man Indicted for Federal Sex Trafficking Offenses</title><url>https://justice.gov//opa/pr/florida-man-indicted-federal-sex-trafficking-offenses</url><text>A federal grand jury in Fort Pierce, Florida, returned an indictment charging a Florida man with 10 counts of sex trafficking.

According to court documents, between 2011 and 2019, Shannima Yuantrell Session, aka Shalamar, 46, of Lake Placid, trafficked seven women and three girls. Session allegedly recruited his victims through violence and threats, among other things; including offers of drugs, employment and romantic relationships. Once Session had gained compliance from his victims, he then trafficked them for sex primarily in rural areas of Highlands County for his own profit.

If convicted, Session faces a mandatory minimum sentence of 15 years in prison, with a maximum sentence of life imprisonment, as well as a maximum of lifetime supervised release. Session is being held in custody pending trial. A federal district judge will determine any sentence after considering U.S. Sentencing Guidelines and other statutory factors.

Assistant Attorney General Kristen Clarke of the Justice Department&#8217;s Civil Rights Division, U.S. Attorney Markenzy Lapointe for the Southern District of Florida, Special Agent in Charge Jeffrey B. Veltri of the FBI Miami Field Office and Sheriff Paul Blackman of Highlands County Sheriff&#8217;s Office made the announcement.

The FBI Miami Field Office investigated this case, with assistance from the Highlands County Sheriff&#8217;s Office.

Assistant U.S. Attorney Justin Hoover for the Southern District of Florida and Trial Attorneys Leah Branch and Elizabeth Hutson of the Civil Rights Division&#8217;s Human Trarfficking Prosecution Unit are prosecuting the case.

An indictment is merely an allegation. All defendants are presumed innocent until proven guilty beyond a reasonable doubt in a court of law.

</text></article><article><title>Assistant Attorney General Matthew G. Olsen Delivers Remarks at Hoover Institution Announcing National Security Cyber Section</title><url>https://justice.gov//opa/speech/assistant-attorney-general-matthew-g-olsen-delivers-remarks-hoover-institution-announcing</url><text>I&#8217;ve been in this job a little over a year and a half. Every day I sit with the Attorney General and FBI Director for the morning threat briefing and each day I read the Presidential Daily Brief. Day-after-day, week-after-week, the intelligence reporting details the astonishing pace, scale and sophistication of cyber threats to the United States.

Hostile nations are accelerating their use of cyber-enabled means to carry out a range of threatening activity. These countries are stealing sensitive technologies, trade secrets, intellectual property and personally identifying information; exerting malign influence and exporting repression; and holding our critical infrastructure at risk to destructive or disruptive attacks.

You don&#8217;t need access to classified intelligence to understand what we are up against from countries like China, Russia, Iran and North Korea.

Take just a few snippets from the Intelligence Community (IC)&#8217;s public Annual Threat Assessment for this year.

China has compromised telecommunications firms. It conducts cyber intrusions targeting journalists and dissidents in order to suppress the free flow of information. And the PRC is capable of launching cyberattacks that could disrupt U.S. critical infrastructure.

Russia is bolstering its ability to compromise critical infrastructure, such as industrial control systems, in part to demonstrate it has the ability to inflict damage during a crisis. Iran, too, continues to be an aggressive cyber actor, taking advantage of the asymmetric nature of cyberattacks.

And North Korea is turning to illicit cyber activities to steal the funds and technical knowledge it needs to further its military aspirations and Weapons of Mass Destruction (WMD) programs.

Our adversaries also imperil the United States by acting as safe havens for cyber criminals who carry out ransomware attacks and digital extortion for personal profit.

That&#8217;s what the intelligence community is willing to say in public about what we are up against &#8211; and it&#8217;s not a pretty picture.

The good news is that our response to national security cyber threats has gotten more effective in recent years. We are putting hard-earned lessons into practice.

One lesson we&#8217;ve learned from our counterterrorism efforts after 9/11 is the importance of ensuring agencies like FBI, Department of Homeland Security (DHS), the IC and Department of Defense (DoD), are working as one team, sharing information and deploying authorities in a coordinated manner.

We are also coordinating government actions with foreign partners and the private sector to empower technical operations, leverage sanctions and trade remedies, and join in diplomatic efforts with like-minded countries. And we are applying the key lesson that effectively combating nation-state cyber threats requires shoring up private sector cybersecurity to make us collectively less vulnerable.

In March, the White House released the National Cybersecurity Strategy in order to drive a &#8220;more intentional, more coordinated, and more well-resourced approach to cyber defense.&#8221; At the Department of Justice, we are putting that vision into practice. Federal law enforcement wields some of the most powerful tools in our arsenal. In recent years, we have achieved successes in deploying those tools &#8211; and we can build on this success.

The Justice Department has never been more effective in identifying, addressing and eliminating cyber threats affecting our nation&#8217;s security.

Here is the playbook that&#8217;s working. First, as you&#8217;d expect of prosecutors, we enforce U.S. criminal law &#8211; investigating and prosecuting individuals for illegal cyber activity, imposing costs on them and deterring others. Just a few examples from last year:

We charged three Iranians with conducting a ransomware campaign that targeted hospitals, local governments and organizations all over the world.

We secured a 20-year prison sentence for an individual who leveraged teams of hackers and insiders in a multi-faceted espionage campaign targeting American and European aviation companies on behalf of PRC intelligence.

Shortly after the Russian invasion of Ukraine, we unsealed indictments that publicly demonstrated how two different sets of Russian state-sponsored actors compromised devices at hundreds of critical infrastructure providers around the world, deploying malware designed to enable future physical damage.

We are holding individuals accountable, imposing consequences, and using our indictments to inform the public about the nature of the threats we face, and our adversaries that their actions are not as deniable as they&#8217;d like to think.

Second, we are proactive &#8211; using the full range of our authorities to disrupt national security cyber threats before a significant attack or intrusion can occur. This includes the innovative use of our legal tools beyond traditional criminal charges.

Just last month, the Justice Department and FBI conducted &#8220;Operation Medusa.&#8221; This was a technical operation to dismantle and effectively neutralize the &#8220;Snake&#8221; malware, one of the Russian government&#8217;s most sophisticated computer intrusion tools. The FSB had used versions of the Snake malware for nearly 20 years to steal sensitive information from hundreds of computer systems in at least 50 countries, including NATO governments. Through innovative use of our Rule 41 search warrant authority, as well as collaboration with private sector partners and numerous foreign governments, the Justice Department disabled one of the FSB&#8217;s most sensitive, complex espionage tools.

Last year, we conducted a court-approved operation to dismantle a GRU botnet that relied on compromised firewall security appliances. Working with the company that manufactured those devices, the FBI developed a court-authorized technical solution to delete the GRU&#8217;s malware and close the vulnerabilities in compromised devices.

We have also used our cryptocurrency tracing abilities and our seizure authorities to prevent over $100 million in ill-gotten crypto from being used by North Korea to support its missile programs. These efforts have focused both on hackers, who have stolen hundreds of millions of dollars&#8217; worth of cryptocurrency, and on IT workers who use online platforms to earn illegal revenue. By coordinating asset freezes and sanctions, the U.S. government has stopped the DPRK from accessing a huge portion of their illicit gains, much of which remains stranded on the blockchain.

Finally, we coordinate our efforts with interagency partners, foreign governments and the private sector to use the full force of tools &#8211; technical operations, sanctions, trade remedies and diplomatic efforts. For example, in the Iran indictments I mentioned a minute ago, we enhanced the impact of the public indictment by working with Treasury to impose sanctions connecting those defendants to the Islamic Revolutionary Guard Corps.

Intelligence also plays a key role. We share targeted threat intelligence gathered as a result of our investigations to empower private sector companies to defend themselves. For example, following the Colonial Pipeline attack, we were able to acquire information &#8211; using Section 702 of FISA &#8211; that verified the hacker&#8217;s identity and enabled the government to recover the majority of the ransom.

Our commitment to combating these threats using every tool we&#8217;ve got is making an impact. We are making it harder for hostile nations to maneuver and recruit by imposing accountability. We are denying our adversaries access to technical infrastructure and cutting off their funding. We&#8217;re disrupting the criminal ecosystem by making cybercrime and ransomware less lucrative and higher risk. We are helping the private sector defend itself more effectively with key intelligence and threat information. We&#8217;re marshaling the efforts of like-minded nations around the world on both diplomatic and law enforcement fronts.

As determined as our adversaries might be in escalating their brazen activities, they are learning that we are even more determined to protect the United States and our allies.

Since we first charged five members of the PLA in 2014, NSD has been leading the charge with just a handful of dedicated cyber prosecutors, operating on grit, coffee and a shoestring budget. And none of these cases would be possible without the close partnership of enterprising U.S. Attorneys&#8217; Offices. So, I am proud of the work being done in the National Security Division, in U.S. Attorneys&#8217; Offices around the country, at the FBI, and across the Department of Justice.

The cases and disruptions I discussed earlier did not come easy. They&#8217;re often fast-paced and span international boundaries; they involve highly technical data and often classified data and demand innovative legal approaches. These are actions that require dedicated time, attention, and expertise. Now, we are aggressively growing our national security cyber program.

Today, I am announcing that we are establishing a new National Security Cyber Section &#8211; NatSec Cyber, for short &#8211; within the National Security Division. This new, full litigating section &#8211; which now has the approval of Congress &#8211; will place our work on cyber threats on equal footing with NSD&#8217;s Counterterrorism Section and the Counterintelligence and Export Control Section.

This new section will allow NSD to increase the scale and speed of disruption campaigns and prosecutions of nation-state threat actors, state-sponsored cybercriminals, associated money launderers, and other cyber-enabled threats to national security.

The creation of a new section responds to the core findings in Deputy Attorney General Monaco&#8217;s Comprehensive Cyber Review, released in July 2022, that charted the evolving nature of the cyber threat. It will help fulfill a core pillar of the Biden Administration&#8217;s National Cybersecurity Strategy: to disrupt and dismantle threat actors by working across federal agencies.

NatSec Cyber will give us the horsepower and organizational structure we need to carry out key roles of the Department in this arena. NatSec Cyber prosecutors will be positioned to act quickly, as soon as the FBI or an IC partner identifies a cyber-enabled threat, and to support investigations and disruptions from the earliest stages.

Having prosecutors that are fully dedicated to national security cyber cases will deepen our expertise. It will enable us to better collaborate with our key partners, especially our colleagues in the Criminal Division&#8217;s Computer Crimes and Intellectual Property Section, which plays a particularly crucial role in ransomware and other criminal cases. And, in order to more closely integrate with the FBI&#8217;s Cyber Division, the NatSec Cyber Section will mirror that structure, organizing leadership by geographical threat actor.

The new section will also serve as a resource for prosecutors in U.S. Attorneys&#8217; Offices around the country. U.S. Attorneys&#8217; Offices, along with FBI field offices, represent the tip of the spear in confronting many of the threats in their districts. Responding to highly technical cyber threats often requires significant time and resources, which aren&#8217;t always possible with the demands on individual offices. NatSec Cyber will serve as an incubator, able to invest in the time-intensive and complex investigative work for early-stage cases.

The section will also allow prosecutors to work seamlessly with colleagues focused on the interagency policy process in the National Security Council. That process has become increasingly central to the effective deployment of the government&#8217;s cyber capabilities under the leadership of Deputy National Security Advisor for Cyber and Emerging Technologies Anne Neuberger.

Here&#8217;s the bottom line: Cybersecurity is a matter of national security. Our cyber adversaries are innovative and constantly adjusting their tactics to hide from our investigators and to overcome our network defenders.

NSD is committed to matching our adversaries by adjusting our tactics and organization to bring all of our tools, authorities and expertise to this fight.

</text></article><article><title>Federal Jury Convicts Three Defendants of Interstate Stalking of Chinese Nationals in the United States and Two Defendants of Acting or Conspiring to Act on Behalf of the People&#8217;s Republic of China</title><url>https://justice.gov//opa/pr/federal-jury-convicts-three-defendants-interstate-stalking-chinese-nationals-united-states</url><text>Earlier today, a federal jury in Brooklyn, New York, convicted three defendants on multiple counts of a superseding indictment charging them with acting and conspiring to act in the United States as illegal agents of the People&#8217;s Republic of China (PRC), without prior notification to the Attorney General.&#160;

Michael McMahon, 55, of Mahwah, New Jersey, was convicted of acting as an illegal agent of the PRC, conspiracy to commit interstate stalking and interstate stalking; Congying Zheng, 27, of Brooklyn, was convicted of conspiracy to commit interstate stalking and interstate stalking; and Zhu Yong aka Jason Zhu, 66, of Queens, New York, was convicted of conspiracy to act as an illegal agent of the PRC, acting as an illegal agent of the PRC, conspiracy to commit interstate stalking and interstate stalking.

According to court documents and evidence presented at trial, McMahon &#8211; a retired NYPD sergeant working as a private investigator &#8211; and Zhu knowingly acted at the direction of the PRC government officials to conduct surveillance and engage in a campaign to harass, stalk and coerce certain residents of the United States to return to the PRC as part of a global and extralegal repatriation effort known as &#8220;Operation Fox Hunt.&#8221; Zheng engaged in interstate stalking of the same victims, leaving a threatening note at their residence.&#160;

Today&#8217;s verdict follows a three-week trial before U.S. District Judge Pamela K. Chen. McMahon faces up to 20 years in prison, Zhu faces up to 25 years in prison, and Zheng faces up to 10 years in prison. A federal district court judge will determine any sentence after considering U.S. Sentencing Guidelines and other statutory factors.

&#8220;The defendants engaged in a campaign of harassment and coercion on behalf of the PRC to force the victim&#8217;s repatriation to China from the United States, including by threatening family members,&#8221; said Assistant Attorney General Matthew G. Olsen of the Justice Department&#8217;s National Security Division. &#8220;The Department of Justice will hold accountable those who would help repressive regimes violate the fundamental freedoms of people in the United States.&#8221;

&#8220;The jury&#8217;s verdict confirms that defendants McMahon and Zhu knowingly acted at the direction of a hostile foreign state to harass, intimidate and attempt to cause the involuntary return of a resident of the New York metropolitan area to the People&#8217;s Republic of China, and that defendant Zheng harassed and intimidated that same person and his family,&#8221; said U.S. Attorney Breon Peace for the Eastern District of New York. &#8220;It is particularly troubling that defendant Michael McMahon, a former sergeant in the New York City Police Department, engaged in surveillance, harassment, and stalking on behalf of a foreign power for money. We will remain steadfast in exposing and undermining efforts by the Chinese government to reach across our border and perpetrate transnational repression schemes targeting victims in the United States in violation of our laws.&#8221;

&#8220;The conviction of these three defendants &#8211; including a retired NYPD sergeant &#8211; is yet another powerful reminder of the Chinese government&#8217;s ongoing, pervasive, and illegal behavior here in the United States,&#8221; said Assistant Director Suzanne Turner of the FBI&#8217;s Counterintelligence Division. &#8220;At the direction of the PRC&#8217;s Ministry of Public Security, the defendants engaged in increasingly egregious efforts at repression, from stalking to outright threats and intimidation tactics undertaken at the victim&#8217;s family home. This will not be tolerated within our borders, plain and simple. If you or someone you know have been targeted in this manner, we urge you to contact the FBI &#8211; and to all those engaging in such repression tactics, stand forewarned.&#8221;

As proven at trial, between approximately 2016 and 2019, the defendants participated in an international campaign with members of the PRC government as part of &#8220;Operation Fox Hunt&#8221; to threaten, harass, surveil and intimidate John Doe #1 and his family, in order to force John Doe #1 and his wife, Jane Doe #1, to return to the PRC. In or around 2015, the PRC government caused the International Criminal Police Organization (Interpol), an inter-governmental law enforcement organization, to issue &#8220;Red Notices&#8221; for John Doe #1 and Jane Doe #1, alleging that both persons were wanted by the PRC government on corruption-related charges.

Zhu hired McMahon who obtained detailed information about John Doe #1, his wife, and his daughter from a law enforcement database and other government databases, then reported back to Zhu and others, including a PRC police officer, what he had learned. McMahon also conducted surveillance outside the New Jersey home of John Doe #1&#8217;s sister-in-law and provided Zhu and PRC officials with detailed reports of what he had observed. The operation was supervised and directed by several PRC officials, including co-conspirators Hu Ji, a PRC police officer with the Wuhan Public Security Bureau and Tu Lan, a PRC prosecutor with the Wuhan Procuratorate.

In April 2017, Tu Lan and Hu Ji transported John Doe #1&#8217;s then-82-year-old father from the PRC to the New Jersey home of John Doe #1&#8217;s sister-in-law to attempt to convince John Doe #1 to return to the PRC. The testimony established that John Doe #1&#8217;s father was brought by a PRC doctor and charged co-conspirator, Li Minjun, and that while John Doe #1&#8217;s father was in the United States, his daughter was threatened with jailing in the PRC. A co-conspirator conducted surveillance of the home during the visit, wearing night-vision goggles provided by the PRC doctor and the PRC prosecutor. McMahon tailed John Doe #1 from the meeting with his elderly father, back to his home, and provided John Doe #1&#8217;s address &#8211; which was previously unknown &#8211; to the PRC operatives.

In October 2016 and April 2017, McMahon emailed himself a China Daily News article titled &#8220;Interpol Launches Global Dragnet for 100 Chinese Fugitives,&#8221; which stated, &#8220;Amid the nation&#8217;s intensifying antigraft campaign, arrest warrants were issued by Interpol China for former State employees and others suspected of a wide range of corrupt practices. China Daily was authorized by the Chinese justice authorities to publish the information below.&#8221; The article provided a list of photographs and identifying information about Operation Fox Hunt targets by the PRC government, including those of John Doe #1 and Jane Doe #1.

On Sept. 4, 2018, Zheng drove to the New Jersey residence of John Doe #1 and Jane Doe #1 and pounded on the front door. He and a co-conspirator attempted to force open the door to the residence, then left a note that stated &#8220;If you are willing to go back to the mainland and spend 10 years in prison, your wife and children will be all right. That&#8217;s the end of this matter!&#8221;&#160;

Previously, three other defendants pleaded guilty in connection with their roles in the PRC-directed harassment and intimidation campaign.

Zebin pleaded guilty in March 2022 to interstate stalking conspiracy and is awaiting sentencing. Hongru Jin pleaded guilty in June 2021 to conspiring to act as an illegal agent of the PRC and interstate stalking conspiracy and is awaiting sentencing. Tu Lan, Hu Ji and Li Minjun are fugitives.

The FBI Newark Field Office investigated the case&#160;with valuable assistance provided by the State Department&#8217;s Diplomatic Security Service.

Assistant U.S. Attorneys Craig R. Heeren, Meredith A. Arfa and Irisa Chen for the Eastern District of New York and Trial Attorney Christine A. Bonomo of the National Security Division&#8217;s Counterintelligence and Export Control Section are in charge of the prosecution, with valuable assistance provided by Paralegal Specialist Mary Clare McMahon. &#160;

</text></article><article><title>Woman Pleads Guilty to Murder Conspiracy</title><url>https://justice.gov//opa/pr/woman-pleads-guilty-murder-conspiracy</url><text>An Illinois woman pleaded guilty today for her role in a conspiracy to murder her mother while they vacationed in Bali, Indonesia, in August 2014.&#160;

According to court documents, Heather Mack, 27, originally from Chicago, and her boyfriend, Tommy Schaefer, conspired to kill Mack&#8217;s mother while Mack and her mother vacationed in Bali. Mack arranged for Schaefer to travel to Bali using her mother&#8217;s credit card. After Schaefer arrived, Mack and Schaefer exchanged a series of text messages about how and when to kill Mack&#8217;s mother, which included a discussion about suffocating or beating the victim. Shortly after these text messages were exchanged, on Aug. 12, 2014, Schaefer entered her mother&#8217;s hotel room and, while Mack was present, brutally beat and killed Mack&#8217;s mother. Mack and Schaefer then placed the victim&#8217;s body into a suitcase and tried to leave the hotel in a taxi. When the driver of the taxi refused to accept their fare, Mack told hotel employees that she was going to go call her mother. Mack and Schaefer then fled the hotel and abandoned the suitcase containing the victim&#8217;s body in the taxicab. Mack and Schaefer were arrested by Indonesian police at another hotel in Bali the day after the murder.

In 2015, Mack and Schaefer were convicted in Indonesia of local criminal charges related to the murder. Mack was sentenced to 10 years in prison and released after serving seven years. Schaefer was sentenced to 18 years in prison and currently remains imprisoned in Indonesia. In November 2021, upon arrival in the United States, Mack was arrested on U.S. federal charges relating to the murder. Schaefer was also charged in the U.S. indictment, and those charges remain pending against him.

Mack pleaded guilty to one count of conspiracy to kill a U.S. national. She is scheduled to be sentenced on Dec. 18 and faces a maximum penalty of 28 years in prison. A federal district court judge will determine any sentence after considering the U.S. Sentencing Guidelines and other statutory factors.

Assistant Attorney General Kenneth A. Polite, Jr. of the Justice Department&#8217;s Criminal Division, Acting U.S. Attorney Morris Pasqual for the Northern District of Illinois, and Special Agent in Charge Robert W. &#8220;Wes&#8221; Wheeler Jr. of the FBI Chicago Field Office made the announcement.

Senior Trial Attorney Frank Rangoussis of the Criminal Division&#8217;s Human Rights and Special Prosecutions Section and Assistant U.S. Attorney Ann Marie Ursini for the Northern District of Illinois are prosecuting the case.&#160;

Valuable assistance was provided by the Justice Department&#8217;s Office of International Affairs, as well as the FBI Legal Attach&#233; Office in Jakarta, Indonesia.&#160;

An indictment is merely an allegation. All defendants are presumed innocent until proven guilty beyond a reasonable doubt in a court of law.

</text></article><article><title>Russian National Arrested and Charged with Conspiring to Commit LockBit Ransomware Attacks Against U.S. and Foreign Businesses</title><url>https://justice.gov//opa/pr/russian-national-arrested-and-charged-conspiring-commit-lockbit-ransomware-attacks-against-us</url><text>The Justice Department today announced charges against a Russian national for his involvement in deploying numerous LockBit ransomware and other cyberattacks against victim computer systems in the United States, Asia, Europe, and Africa.

Ruslan Magomedovich Astamirov (&#1040;&#1057;&#1058;&#1040;&#1052;&#1048;&#1056;&#1054;&#1042;, &#1056;&#1091;&#1089;&#1083;&#1072;&#1085; &#1052;&#1072;&#1075;&#1086;&#1084;&#1077;&#1076;&#1086;&#1074;&#1080;&#1095;&#1100;), 20, of Chechen Republic, will make his initial appearance later today.

&#8220;This LockBit-related arrest, the second in six months, underscores the Justice Department&#8217;s unwavering commitment to hold ransomware actors accountable,&#8221; said Deputy Attorney General Lisa O. Monaco. &#8220;In securing the arrest of a second Russian national affiliated with the LockBit ransomware, the Department has once again demonstrated the long arm of the law. We will continue to use every tool at our disposal to disrupt cybercrime, and while cybercriminals may continue to run, they ultimately cannot hide.&#8221;

According to a criminal complaint obtained in the District of New Jersey, from at least as early as August 2020 to March 2023, Astamirov allegedly participated in a conspiracy with other members of the LockBit ransomware campaign to commit wire fraud and to intentionally damage protected computers and make ransom demands through the use and deployment of ransomware. Specifically, Astamirov directly executed at least five attacks against victim computer systems in the United States and abroad. &#160;

&#8220;Astamirov is the third defendant charged by this office in the LockBit global ransomware campaign, and the second defendant to be apprehended,&#8221; said U.S. Attorney Philip R. Sellinger for the District of New Jersey. &#8220;The LockBit conspirators and any other ransomware perpetrators cannot hide behind imagined online anonymity. We will continue to work tirelessly with all our law enforcement partners to identify ransomware perpetrators and bring them to justice.&#8221;

According to the criminal complaint, the LockBit ransomware variant first appeared around January 2020. LockBit actors have executed over 1,400 attacks against victims in the United States and around the world, issuing over $100 million in ransom demands and receiving at least as much as tens of millions of dollars in actual ransom payments made in the form of bitcoin.

In furtherance of his LockBit-related activities, Astamirov owned, controlled, and used a variety of email addresses, Internet Protocol (IP) addresses, and other online provider accounts that allowed him and his co-conspirators to deploy LockBit ransomware and to communicate with their victims. Additionally, in at least one circumstance, law enforcement was able to trace a portion of a victim&#8217;s ransom payment to a virtual currency address in Astamirov&#8217;s control.

&#8220;The FBI is committed to pursuing ransomware actors like Astamirov, who have exploited vulnerable cyber ecosystems and harmed victims,&#8221; said FBI Deputy Director Paul Abbate. &#8220;We, in collaboration with our federal and international partners, are fully committed to&#160;the permanent dismantlement of these types of ransomware campaigns that intentionally target people and our private sector partners. We will continue to leverage every resource to prevent this type of malicious, criminal activity.&#8221;

Astamirov is charged with conspiring to commit wire fraud and conspiring to intentionally damage protected computers and to transmit ransom demands. If convicted, he faces a maximum penalty of 20 years in prison on the first charge and a maximum penalty of five years in prison on the second charge. Both charges are also punishable by a maximum fine of either $250,000 or twice the gain or loss from the offense, whichever is greatest.

This announcement follows LockBit-related charges in two other cases from the District of New Jersey. In November 2022, the department announced criminal charges against Mikhail Vasiliev, a dual Russian and Canadian national, who is currently in custody in Canada awaiting extradition to the United States. In May 2023, the department announced the indictment of Mikhail Pavlovich Matveev, aka Wazawaka, aka m1x, aka Boriselcin, aka Uhodiransomwar, for his alleged participation in separate conspiracies to deploy LockBit, Babuk, and Hive ransomware variants against victims in the United States and abroad.

The FBI Newark Field Office&#8217;s Cyber Crimes Task Force is investigating the case. The Jersey City Police Department, New Jersey State Police, Newark IRS Criminal Investigation, and the international partners from Europol&#8217;s European Cybercrime Centre, Eurojust, National Police Agency of Japan, France&#8217;s Gendarmerie Nationale Cyberspace Command (Cyber Crime Investigation Unit / C3N), National Crime Agency and South West Regional Organized Crime Unit of the United Kingdom, Kantonspolizei Z&#252;rich of Switzerland, Landeskriminalamt Schleswig-Holstein and the Bundeskriminalamt of Germany, and Swedish Police Authority of Sweden also provided valuable assistance.

Trial Attorney Jessica C. Peck and Jorge Gonzalez of the Criminal Division&#8217;s Computer Crime and Intellectual Property Section and Assistant U.S. Attorneys Andrew M. Trombly, Vinay Limbachia, and David E. Malagold for the District of New Jersey&#8217;s Cybercrime Unit in Newark are prosecuting the case.

The U.S. Attorney&#8217;s Office for the District of Arizona and the Justice Department&#8217;s Office of International Affairs also provided significant assistance.

Victims of LockBit ransomware should contact their local FBI field office and visit StopRansomware.gov for further information.

A criminal complaint is merely an allegation. All defendants are presumed innocent until proven guilty beyond a reasonable doubt in a court of law.

</text></article><article><title>Air National Guardsman Indicted for Unlawful Disclosure of Classified National Defense Information</title><url>https://justice.gov//opa/pr/air-national-guardsman-indicted-unlawful-disclosure-classified-national-defense-information</url><text>A member of the U.S. Air National Guard (USANG) stationed in Massachusetts was indicted today by a federal grand jury in Boston for allegedly retaining and transmitting classified national defense information on a social media platform beginning in or around 2022 and continuing until his arrest in April.

Jack Douglas Teixeira, 21, of North Dighton, Massachusetts, was indicted on six counts of willful retention and transmission of classified information relating to the national defense (National Defense Information). Teixeira was arrested on April 13, 2023, and charged by criminal complaint with retention and transmission of national defense information and unauthorized removal and retention of classified documents or materials. On May 19, 2023, U.S. District Court Magistrate Judge David H. Hennessy granted the government&#8217;s motion for detention. Teixeira remains in federal custody.

&#8220;As laid out in the indictment, Jack Teixeira was entrusted by the United States government with access to classified national defense information &#8212; including information that reasonably could be expected to cause exceptionally grave damage to national security if shared,&#8221; said Attorney General Merrick B. Garland. &#8220;Teixeira is charged with sharing information with users on a social media platform he knew were not entitled to receive it. In doing so, he is alleged to have violated U.S. law and endangered our national security.&#8221;

&#8220;Individuals granted security clearances are entrusted to protect classified information and safeguard our nation&#8217;s secrets. The allegations in today&#8217;s indictment reveal a serious violation of that trust,&#8221; said FBI Director Christopher Wray. &#8220;The FBI and our partners remain firm in our commitment to hold accountable those who endanger our national security and the security of our allies around the world.&#8221;

&#8220;The unauthorized removal, retention, and transmission of classified information jeopardizes our nation&#8217;s security. Individuals granted access to classified materials have a fundamental duty to safeguard the information for the safety of the United States, our active service members, its citizens, and its allies,&#8221; said Acting U.S. Attorney Joshua S. Levy for the District of Massachusetts. &#8220;We are committed to ensuring that those entrusted with sensitive national security information adhere to the law.&#8221;

According to the charging documents, Teixeira enlisted in the USANG in September 2019 and has held a Top Secret security clearance since 2021. It is alleged that, beginning in or around January 2022, Teixeira willfully, improperly, and unlawfully retained and transmitted National Defense Information classified as &#8220;TOP SECRET&#8221; or &#8220;SECRET&#8221; and/or Sensitive Compartmented Information, which he had reason to believe could be used to the injury of the United States or to the advantage of a foreign nation, on a social media platform to persons not authorized to receive such information.

According to the charging documents, Teixeira transmitted the classified National Defense Information on the social media platform in two ways. First, Teixeira allegedly accessed classified documents containing National Defense Information from a classified workstation at the Otis USANG Base and transcribed and transmitted the information in written paragraphs to other users on the social media platform. Teixeira also posted images of classified documents to the social media platform, which bore standard classification markings &#8211; including &#8220;SECRET,&#8221; &#8220;TOP SECRET,&#8221; and SCI designations &#8211; indicating that they contained highly classified United States government information. At least one of the documents containing national defense information was allegedly found in digital form in a particular account associated with Teixeira.

Each charge of unauthorized retention and transmission of national defense information provides for a sentence of up to 10 years in prison, up to three years of supervised release, and a fine of up to $250,000. A federal judge will determine any sentence after considering the U.S. Sentencing Guidelines and other statutory factors.

The FBI Boston and Washington Field Offices are&#160;investigating the case. The Naval Criminal Investigative Service and the Air Force Office of Special Investigations provided valuable assistance.

Assistant U.S. Attorneys Nadine Pellegrini, Jared C. Dolan, and Jason A. Casey for the District of Massachusetts and Trial Attorney Christina A. Clark of the National Security Division&#8217;s Counterintelligence and Export Control Section are prosecuting the case.

A criminal complaint is merely an allegation. All defendants are presumed innocent unless and until proven guilty beyond a reasonable doubt in a court of law.

</text></article><article><title>Oregon Man Pleads Guilty to Conspiring to Provide Material Support to ISIS</title><url>https://justice.gov//opa/pr/oregon-man-pleads-guilty-conspiring-provide-material-support-isis</url><text>An Oregon man pleaded guilty in federal court today for conspiring to provide material support to the Islamic State of Iraq and al-Sham (ISIS) by producing and distributing propaganda and recruiting materials online in coordination with ISIS members overseas.

Hawazen Sameer Mothafar, 33, an Iraqi national residing in Troutdale, Oregon, pleaded guilty to one count of conspiracy to provide material support to a designated foreign terrorist organization.

According to court documents, Mothafar immigrated to the U.S. from Iraq in 2014 and, since his arrival, has resided in Troutdale. An ISIS supporter since 2014, Mothafar was the co-founder of the Sunni Shield Foundation, a pro-ISIS media organization that created and published violent propaganda promoting ISIS ideology and objectives. In this role, Mothafar created the Sunni Shield&#8217;s first media product, a video of ISIS battle footage obtained from an official ISIS online platform intended to promote ISIS. In subsequent videos produced by Mothafar, he encouraged viewers to travel to Iraq and Syria to fight for ISIS and conduct attacks on behalf of the organization.

Mothafar and other members of the Sunni Shield obtained ISIS Central Media&#8217;s permission to begin publishing Al Anfal, an online newspaper promoting the Islamic State&#8217;s goals and advocating violent jihad. Mothafar oversaw planning and production of the publication while also serving as one of its graphic designers. Graphics designed by Mothafar for the publication incited readers to attack and kill Westerners and conduct knife attacks against ISIS enemies.

Mothafar communicated directly with ISIS Central Media officials in Iraq, from whom he regularly took instructions about media production. He represented the Sunni Shield in a private online group comprised of ISIS Central Media officials and representatives of other ISIS supporter groups. In this group, ISIS media officials would pass instructions to the supporter groups about official ISIS media campaigns. The supporter groups, including the Sunni Shield, would then prepare media materials to publish in support of the campaigns.

In addition to his work with the Sunni Shield, Mothafar aided other pro-ISIS media organizations and conspired with numerous ISIS associates in furtherance of his support to the terrorist organization. Mothafar provided graphic designs to the Khattab Media Foundation, assisted in the production of the Youth of the Caliphate magazine, published ISIS news on Nashr News Agency channels, worked with Fursan al-Rafa&#8217; (Knights of Uploading) to publish pro-ISIS material on various websites, and assisted the Saqri Foundation with designs. Mothafar also communicated with Abu Qaswara al-Shanqiti, a Specially Designated Global Terrorist imprisoned in West Africa, and connected Qaswara al-Shanqiti with two ISIS officials in hopes of aiding his release.

On Nov. 3, 2020, a federal grand jury in Portland returned a five-count indictment&#160;charging&#160;Mothafar with conspiring to provide material support to a designated foreign terrorist organization, providing and attempting to provide material support to a designated foreign terrorist organization, and making false statements in an immigration application and to a government agency.

Mothafar faces a maximum sentence of 20 years in prison, a $250,000 fine, and a life term of supervised release. Sentencing is scheduled for Jan. 11, 2024 before U.S. District Court Judge Marco A. Hern&#225;ndez.

Assistant Attorney General Matthew G. Olsen of the Justice Department&#8217;s National Security Division, U.S. Attorney Natalie K. Wight, and Assistant Director Robert R. Wells of the FBI Counterterrorism Division made the announcement.

The FBI Portland Field Office is investigating the case.

</text></article><article><title>Russian Nationals Charged With Hacking One Cryptocurrency Exchange and Illicitly Operating Another</title><url>https://justice.gov//opa/pr/russian-nationals-charged-hacking-one-cryptocurrency-exchange-and-illicitly-operating-another</url><text>The Justice Department unsealed charges related to the 2011 hack of the cryptocurrency exchange Mt. Gox and the operation of the illicit cryptocurrency exchange BTC-e.

According to court documents, Alexey Bilyuchenko, 43, and Aleksandr Verner, 29, both Russian nationals, are charged with conspiring to launder approximately 647,000 bitcoins from their hack of Mt. Gox. Bilyuchenko is also charged with conspiring with Alexander Vinnik to operate BTC-e from 2011 to 2017.

&#8220;This announcement marks an important milestone in two major cryptocurrency investigations. As alleged in the indictments, starting in 2011, Bilyuchenko and Verner stole a massive amount of cryptocurrency from Mt. Gox, contributing to the exchange&#8217;s ultimate insolvency. Armed with the ill-gotten gains from Mt. Gox, Bilyuchenko allegedly went on to help set up the notorious BTC-e virtual currency exchange, which laundered funds for cyber criminals worldwide,&#8221; said Assistant Attorney General Kenneth A. Polite, Jr. of the Justice Department&#8217;s Criminal Division. &#8220;These indictments highlight the department&#8217;s unwavering commitment to bring to justice bad actors in the cryptocurrency ecosystem and prevent the abuse of the financial system.&#8221;

&#8220;As cyber criminals have become more sophisticated in their methods of thievery, our career prosecutors and law enforcement partners, too, have become experts in the latest technologies being abused for malicious purposes,&#8221; said U.S. Attorney Damian Williams for the Southern District of New York. &#8220;As alleged, Alexey Bilyuchenko and Aleksandr Verner thought they could outsmart the law by using sophisticated hacks to steal and launder massive amounts of cryptocurrency, a novel technology at the time, but the charges unsealed demonstrate our ability to tenaciously pursue these alleged criminals, no matter how complex their schemes, until they are brought to justice.&#8221;

&#8220;For years, Bilyuchenko and his co-conspirators allegedly operated a digital currency exchange that enabled criminals around the world &#8211; including computer hackers, ransomware actors, narcotics rings, and corrupt public officials &#8211; to launder billions of dollars,&#8221; said U.S. Attorney Ismail J. Ramsey for the Northern District of California. &#8220;The Department of Justice will work tirelessly to identify cyber criminals, no matter where they are. And Bilyuchenko and his co-conspirators will learn that the Department of Justice has long arms and an even longer memory for crimes that harm our communities.&#8221;

Southern District of New York indictment

According to court documents unsealed in the Southern District of New York (SDNY), in or about September 2011, Bilyuchenko, Verner, and their co-conspirators allegedly gained unauthorized access to the server holding the cryptocurrency wallets for Mt. Gox. At the time, Mt. Gox was the largest Bitcoin exchange in existence, servicing thousands of users worldwide. Mt. Gox stored the cryptocurrency wallets containing its customers&#8217; bitcoin, and the corresponding private keys used to authorize bitcoin transfers from those wallets, on a computer server in Japan.

&#8220;The FBI will continue to work with our U.S. government and international partners to relentlessly pursue and disrupt malicious cyber actors wherever they may reside,&#8221; said Assistant Director Bryan Vorndran of the FBI&#8217;s Cyber Division. &#8220;When cyber criminals engage in fraudulent activity, such as hacking and illicitly operating cryptocurrency exchanges, it is critical that we impose cost on the bad actors and ensure they face justice.&#8221;

Bilyuchenko, Verner, and their co-conspirators allegedly used their unauthorized access to Mt. Gox&#8217;s server to fraudulently cause bitcoin to be transferred from Mt. Gox&#8217;s wallets to bitcoin addresses controlled by Bilyuchenko, Verner, and their co-conspirators. From September 2011 through at least May 2014, Bilyuchenko, Verner, and their co-conspirators allegedly caused the theft of at least approximately 647,000 bitcoins from Mt. Gox, representing the vast majority of the bitcoins belonging to Mt. Gox&#8217;s customers. Bilyuchenko, Verner, and their co-conspirators allegedly laundered the bulk of the bitcoins stolen through Mt. Gox principally through bitcoin addresses associated with accounts Bilyuchenko, Verner, and their co-conspirators controlled at two other online bitcoin exchanges.

&#8220;Cryptocurrency offers a new way for criminals to steal and launder money, but greed and deceit are nothing new,&#8221; said Chief Jim Lee of IRS Criminal Investigation (IRS-CI). &#8220;IRS-CI is specially equipped to follow the complex financial trail left by criminals, and we are dedicated to holding those accountable for crimes committed. IRS-CI is proud to stand with our law enforcement partners to announce this indictment.&#8221;

In furtherance of the money laundering scheme, in or about April 2012, Bilyuchenko, Verner, and their co-conspirators allegedly negotiated and entered into a fraudulent contract (the &#8220;Advertising Contract&#8221;) to provide purported advertising services to a Bitcoin brokerage service based in the Southern District of New York (the &#8220;New York Bitcoin Broker&#8221;). Under the guise of the Advertising Contract, in order to conceal and liquidate the bitcoins stolen from Mt. Gox, Bilyuchenko and Verner allegedly made regular requests to the owner and operator of the New York Bitcoin Broker to make large wire transfers into various offshore bank accounts, including in the names of shell corporations, controlled by Bilyuchenko, Verner, and their co-conspirators. In accordance with these requests, between in or about March 2012 and in or about April 2013, the New York Bitcoin Broker allegedly transferred more than approximately $6.6 million to overseas bank accounts controlled by Bilyuchenko, Verner, and their co-conspirators. In exchange for the wire transfers, the New York Bitcoin Broker allegedly received &#8220;credit&#8221; on Exchange-1, through which Bilyuchenko, Verner, and their co-conspirators allegedly laundered more than 300,000 of the bitcoins stolen from Mt. Gox.&#160; The fraudulent Advertising Contract with the New York Bitcoin Broker allegedly enabled Bilyuchenko, Verner, and their co-conspirators to conceal and liquidate bitcoins stolen through the Mt. Gox Hack.&#160;

Mt. Gox ceased operations in 2014 after the theft was revealed.&#160;

Northern District of California indictment

According to court documents unsealed in the Northern District of California (NDCA), Bilyuchenko allegedly worked with Vinnik and others to operate the BTC-e exchange from 2011 until it was shut down by law enforcement in July 2017. During that time period, BTC-e was one of the world&#8217;s largest cryptocurrency exchanges and was one of the primary ways by which cyber criminals around the world transferred, laundered, and stored the criminal proceeds of their illegal activities.

BTC-e served over one million users worldwide, moving millions of bitcoin worth of deposits and withdrawals, and processing billions of dollars&#8217; worth of transactions. BTC-e received criminal proceeds of numerous computer intrusions and hacking incidents, ransomware events, identity theft schemes, corrupt public officials, and narcotics distribution rings.

&#8220;The Secret Service has a long tradition of pursuing and bringing to justice those who aim to exploit our financial systems and target innocent victims,&#8221; said Special Agent in Charge William Mancino of the U.S. Secret Service&#8217;s Criminal Investigative Division. &#8220;Working together with our local, state, and federal law enforcement partners, we will continue to investigate criminal organizations that operate in the ever-evolving cyber domain.&#8221;

&#8220;Homeland Security Investigations (HSI) continues to investigate cyber criminals illicitly operating in virtual spaces, and we are proud to have worked collaboratively with our law enforcement partners to bring these two individuals to justice,&#8221; said Acting Executive Associate Director Katrina W. Berger of HSI. &#8220;Our special agents continue to investigate transnational criminal organizations operating in emerging technologies, leveraging our broad authorities to identify, and dismantle those behind sophisticated crypto-scams.&#8221;

The SDNY indictment charges Bilyuchenko and Verner with conspiracy to commit money laundering. The NDCA indictment charges Bilyuchenko with money laundering conspiracy and operating an unlicensed money services business.

The U.S. Attorney&#8217;s Office for the Southern District of New York&#8217;s Complex Frauds and Cybercrime Unit is handling the SDNY case. The FBI and IRS-CI are investigating the case and SDNY Assistant U.S. Attorney Olga I. Zverovich is prosecuting the case.

The Corporate and Securities Fraud Section of the U.S. Attorney&#8217;s Office for the Northern District of California and the Criminal Division&#8217;s Computer Crime and Intellectual Property Section (CCIPS) are handling the NDCA case. The FBI; IRS-CI Oakland Field Office and Cyber Crime Unit in Washington, D.C.; U.S. Secret Service Criminal Investigative Division; and HSI are investigating the case. CCIPS Trial Attorney C. Alden Pelker and NDCA Assistant U.S. Attorney Claudia Quiroz, both members of the National Cryptocurrency Enforcement Team, and NDCA Assistant U.S. Attorney Katherine Lloyd-Lovett are prosecuting the case. The Justice Department&#8217;s Office of International Affairs provided invaluable assistance.

A criminal indictment is merely an allegation. All defendants are presumed innocent until proven guilty beyond a reasonable doubt in a court of law.</text></article><article><title>Statement of Special Counsel Jack Smith</title><url>https://justice.gov//opa/video/statement-special-counsel-jack-smith</url><text>Statement of Special Counsel Jack Smith

Related:

Special Counsel&#8217;s Office &#8211; Jack Smith

Special Counsel Jack Smith Delivers Statement

Indictment, United States v. Donald J. Trump and Waltine Nauta, June 8, 2023

</text></article><article><title>Two Federal Bureau of Prisons Employees Charged with Violating the Civil Rights of an Inmate Resulting in His Death</title><url>https://justice.gov//opa/pr/two-federal-bureau-prisons-employees-charged-violating-civil-rights-inmate-resulting-his</url><text>A federal grand jury indicted a Bureau of Prisons (BOP) lieutenant and a BOP registered nurse yesterday with violating the civil rights of an inmate by showing deliberate indifference to the inmate&#8217;s serious medical needs, resulting in his death.&#160;

The indictment alleges that on Jan. 9, 2021, Lieutenant Shronda Covington, 47, of Chesterfield, Virginia, and Registered Nurse Tonya Farley, 52, of Chesterfield, Virginia, were on duty and working in their official capacities at the Federal Correctional Institution at Petersburg, Virginia. On that day, they allegedly each willfully failed to ensure that the inmate, a 47-year-old man identified as W.W., was provided with necessary medical care, resulting in W.W.&#8217;s death, even though each knew that W.W. had serious medical needs. Farley is also charged with writing a false report about the incident, and Covington and Farley are each charged with making false statements to federal agents about the incident.

The civil rights charges each carry a maximum penalty of life in prison, the false report charge carries a maximum penalty of twenty years in prison and each false statement charge carries a maximum penalty of five years in prison.&#160;

Assistant Attorney General Kristen Clarke of the Justice Department&#8217;s Civil Rights Division, U.S. Attorney Jessica D. Aber for the Eastern District of Virginia and Special Agent in Charge Russell W. Cunningham of the Justice Department&#8217;s Office of Inspector General (DOJ OIG) Washington Field Office made the announcement.

DOJ OIG investigated the case.&#160;

Special Litigation Counsel Kathryn E. Gilbert and Trial Attorney Matthew Tannenbaum of the Civil Rights Division&#8217;s Criminal Section and Assistant U.S. Attorney Thomas Garnett for the Eastern District of Virginia are prosecuting the case.

An indictment is merely an allegation. All defendants are presumed innocent until proven guilty beyond a reasonable doubt in a court of law.

</text></article><article><title>Jury Convicts Federal Correctional Officer for Sexual Abuse of Two Female Inmates</title><url>https://justice.gov//opa/pr/jury-convicts-federal-correctional-officer-sexual-abuse-two-female-inmates</url><text>A federal jury convicted a federal correctional officer of five counts involving sexually abusive conduct against two female victims who were serving prison sentences. U.S. District Judge Yvonne Gonzalez Rogers presided over the trial.

John Bellhouse, 40, formerly of Pleasanton, California, was initially charged with sexual abuse of an inmate on Feb. 17, 2022.&#160;A federal grand jury issued a superseding indictment on Sept. 29, 2022, charging Bellhouse with two counts of sexual abuse and three counts of abusive sexual contact. The charges involved conduct that was alleged to have occurred against two female inmates from December 2019 to December 2020.&#160;On Monday, a jury convicted Bellhouse of all counts.&#160;

&#8220;Correctional Officer Bellhouse committed an egregious breach of trust by using the cover of the BOP facility&#8217;s Safety Office to sexually abuse individuals in his custody,&#8221; said Deputy Attorney General Lisa O. Monaco. &#8220;This guilty verdict is yet another warning that any Bureau employee who abuses their authority will be held accountable.&#160;The Department of Justice is committed to rooting out sexual assault within the BOP and continuing to prioritize cases involving sexual abuse of individuals in BOP custody.&#8221;

&#8220;The heinous crimes in this case destroyed&#160;the sense of safety and security every human being is entitled to,&#8221; said FBI Deputy Director Paul Abbate.&#160;&#8220;While he was a federal corrections officer, the&#160;defendant sexually abused two victims in his care&#160;over the course of a year, an unimaginable violation of the most basic human rights. Today&#8217;s conviction demonstrates that the FBI remains unyielding&#160;in our protection of all people no matter where the crime occurs or who commits it.&#8221;

&#8220;Bellhouse violated vulnerable women under his custody and care, and a jury held him accountable for these despicable acts. Four other FCI Dublin employees, including the former Warden and Chaplain, have been convicted of sexually abusing inmates. Our investigation of sexual abuse at FCI Dublin remains ongoing, and we will continue to aggressively pursue justice for victims of sexual abuse at the hands of BOP employees,&#8221; said Inspector General Michael E. Horowitz.

&#8220;As an officer in a federal correctional facility, Bellhouse had an obligation to ensure the safety of all the persons serving their sentences,&#8221; said U.S. Attorney Ismail J. Ramsey for the Northern District of California. &#8220;Instead, Bellhouse used the power entrusted to him to serve his own corrupt purposes.&#160;The sexual abuse of inmates will not be tolerated, and Bellhouse will now face the consequences for committing his despicable crimes.&#8221;

Bellhouse was employed as a correctional officer at the Federal Correctional Institute in Dublin, California (FCI Dublin), an all-female low security federal correctional institution.&#160;Trial evidence showed that Bellhouse sexually abused and committed abusive sexual contact against a victim beginning December 2019 through October 2020.&#160;The victim was incarcerated and serving a prison sentence at FCI Dublin under Bellhouse&#8217;s custodial, supervisory, and disciplinary authority. The trial evidence demonstrated Bellhouse engaged in oral sex with the victim in the prison Safety Warehouse and Safety Office and that Bellhouse touched the victim&#8217;s vagina and breasts in the prison Safety Office.&#160;

The trial evidence also demonstrated Bellhouse committed abusive sexual contact against a second victim between October and December of 2020.&#160;Trial evidence showed that the acts occurred in the Safety Office at the FCI Dublin Camp.

Bellhouse was convicted of two counts of sexual abuse of a ward and three counts of abusive sexual conduct. Each count of sexual abuse carries a maximum term of 15 years in prison. Each count of abusive sexual conduct carries a maximum term of two years in prison. A federal district court judge will determine any sentence after considering the U.S. Sentencing Guidelines and other statutory factors.

Judge Gonzalez Rogers scheduled Bellhouse&#8217;s sentencing hearing for Aug. 30. Bellhouse remains out of custody pending his sentencing.

The DOJ OIG and FBI investigated the case.

Assistant U.S. Attorneys Molly Priedeman and Andrew Paulson for the Northern District of California are prosecuting the case, with the assistance of Madeline Wachs, Sara Slattery, and Leeya Kekona.

</text></article><article><title>Deputy Assistant Attorney General Arun G. Rao Delivers Remarks at the International Bar Association's 9th Annual World Life Sciences Conference</title><url>https://justice.gov//opa/speech/deputy-assistant-attorney-general-arun-g-rao-delivers-remarks-international-bar</url><text>Remarks as Delivered

Good morning. I appreciate the opportunity to speak with you today. Many thanks to the International Bar Association for the invitation, and to Anne Walsh for the kind introduction. I look forward hearing from conference participants about some of the challenges and opportunities that cross international boundaries.

Across the globe, the COVID-19 pandemic made clear what those attending this conference know well &#8211; that, when it comes to the health and safety of its citizens, no nation is isolated from its neighbors. Pharmaceutical companies and researchers in all corners of the globe fight the same diseases and wrestle with how to best utilize rapidly evolving technologies to improve lives. And the global nature of commerce means that products developed in one part of the world may be manufactured in another part of the world, using materials from yet another part of the world, and then are shipped to and used in, still, other parts of the world.

Today, I would like to share with you how the Consumer Protection Branch of the United States Department of Justice approaches its cases and initiatives &#8212; including matters that involve conduct occurring outside the United States &#8212; and also highlight a few important new policies that we expect will strengthen the department&#8217;s ability to investigate misconduct occurring outside the United States and help to protect consumers around the world.

Some of you might not be familiar with the branch or might not have encountered the Branch in some time &#8211; and so I&#8217;d like to begin by providing an overview of the Branch, including how the branch approaches its important work of protecting the health and safety of the public.

The Consumer Protection Branch was created over 50 years ago and began, like many consumer protection initiatives across the United States, as an offshoot of antitrust efforts. Over the past half-century, the size and portfolio of the Branch have grown. Today, the branch has over 100 attorneys &#8212; supported by paralegals, investigators, document analysts, and data scientists &#8212; who collectively tackle a range of misconduct impacting the health, safety, economic security, and identity integrity of members of the public. In furthering this mission, the branch relies on both civil actions &#8212; including those that enjoin wrongful behavior and seek monetary penalties &#8212; as well as criminal prosecutions.

The branch regularly conducts affirmative enforcement activity related to prescription drugs, medical devices, food safety, dietary supplements, tobacco and nicotine products, and opioids. In all these areas, we employ both civil and criminal tools.

In our work, we closely coordinate with U.S. Attorneys&#8217; Offices across the country, law enforcement agencies like the Federal Bureau of Investigation, the Drug Enforcement Administration (DEA) and the U.S. Postal Inspection Service and our valued agency partners, including the U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA). All these agencies help provide the branch with international support and assistance &#8211; in recognition of the fact that effective prevention and enforcement requires building and maintaining strong relationships around the world.

With respect to the branch&#8217;s work in the life sciences space, our investigations generally fall into two categories. Where the branch and its partners identify a pervasive problem or widespread misconduct related to certain categories of products or industries, we seek to attack that misconduct holistically, targeting a wide range of actors that potentially may be responsible for contributing to a particular problem. Other times, however, we focus on individual bad actors whose conduct may be harming consumers.

The branch&#8217;s past and current efforts related to opioids are illustrative. According to the World Health Organization, approximately one-half-million deaths worldwide are attributable to drug use, with more than 70% of those deaths related to opioids. In the United States, overdose deaths have risen sharply over the last decade, and a current estimate places the number of annual overdose deaths at approximately 100,000.

Seeking to combat this global crisis, the branch has endeavored to identify and hold accountable individual and corporate actors at every point in the supply chain, including manufacturers, distributors, and dispensers of opioids. These efforts have included complex civil lawsuits against multinational companies based in the United States &#8212; including a landmark ongoing lawsuit brought by the branch against Walmart in connection with dispensing and distribution practices at the company&#8217;s pharmacies. And in December 2022, the branch also sued one of the largest drug distributors in the United States, AmerisourceBergen, alleging that the company committed hundreds of thousands of violations of the Controlled Substances Act.

In addition to these civil lawsuits, the branch also has pursued criminal prosecutions, where appropriate. In October 2020, opioid manufacturer Purdue Pharma LP pleaded guilty to conspiracy to defraud the United States and to violate the anti-kickback statute. Specifically, Purdue admitted to impeding the Drug Enforcement Administration by representing that it maintained an effective anti-diversion program when, in fact, Purdue continued to market its opioid products to more than 100 health care providers whom the company had reason to believe were diverting opioids. Purdue also admitted that it reported misleading information to the DEA to boost Purdue&#8217;s manufacturing quotas. And Purdue acknowledged making payments to doctors through the company&#8217;s doctor speaker program to induce those doctors to write more prescriptions of Purdue&#8217;s opioid products.

The branch also has sought to hold accountable companies that attempt to profit from abuse treatments through deception. For example, in July 2019, global consumer goods conglomerate Reckitt Benckiser Group agreed to pay $1.4 billion to resolve its potential criminal and civil liability related to a federal investigation of the marketing of the opioid addiction treatment drug Suboxone. And a subsidiary of the company, Indivior Solutions, also pleaded guilty &#8211; admitting that it falsely promoted the film version of Suboxone to physicians, pharmacists, Medicaid administrators, and others across the country as less-divertible and less-abusable and safer around children, families and communities than other buprenorphine drugs, even though such claims had never been established.

More recently, as the nature of the opioid crisis has evolved, the branch and its law enforcement partners also have adapted and are now working to stem the flow of illicit fentanyl. The urgency of disrupting this activity is clear. Last year, the DEA and its partners seized over 50 million fake prescription pills &#8212; more than double the amount seized in 2021. This presents a global challenge: essential ingredients for illicit pills often come from different parts of the world, the illicit pills are sometimes manufactured in other parts of the world, and the illicit pills are then trafficked across international borders.

At the branch, we are once again taking a holistic view of this problem &#8211; seeking to identify corporate bad actors responsible for aiding the manufacture, distribution, and sale of illicit pills, including global e-commerce sites, social media platforms, and multinational chemical companies. And we are also examining the conduct of companies responsible for supplying narcotics traffickers with the equipment needed to make illicit pills, such as industrial pill presses and counterfeit dyes.

In recognition of the complexity of these matters, in March 2023, Associate Attorney General Vanita Gupta announced the creation of the Opioid Epidemic Civil Litigation Task Force, which formalizes and enhances coordination of the Department&#8217;s existing work and will also consider new initiatives. Because of the scope and duration of the crisis, the task force includes U.S. Attorneys&#8217; Offices, the Consumer Protection Branch and the Civil Division&#8217;s Commercial Litigation Branch, the Drug Enforcement Administration, and other department components. The task force will steer the department&#8217;s civil litigation efforts involving actors alleged to have contributed to the opioid epidemic.

The branch also has remained focused on global enforcement efforts related to dietary supplements, including those marketed to the public as purportedly safe workout or weight loss supplements, but that frequently include ingredients capable of causing serious harm (including liver damage). Our investigations have revealed that ingredients for these products often have been imported into the United States from abroad using deception.

For example, last year the founder and operator of a Florida-based supplement retailer was sentenced to 54 months in prison, following his conviction for lying to consumers by falsely characterizing certain products as safe and legal dietary supplements. In addition, the defendant falsely represented that the unsafe products were made in &#8220;FDA approved&#8221; registered facilities and in compliance with required regulations, when in fact they were not. He also admitted to directing the fraudulent importation of raw ingredients for products from China, to ignoring injury reports made by consumers, and to failing to notify the FDA of such complaints, even when required by law.

In another matter brought by the branch in Texas, two Chinese nationals involved in importing raw ingredients for dietary supplements were convicted in connection with their participation in a scheme to sell mislabeled dietary supplements. The branch was able to prosecute this matter partially due to information provided by a confidential government informant. The defendants were arrested while attending a dietary supplement trade show in Las Vegas, and one defendant ultimately admitted to making false statements to FDA&#8217;s import division regarding a shipment of synthetic stimulants entering the United States.

And in a matter brought by the branch in California, the branch secured criminal charges against an import company and four individuals allegedly responsible for smuggling dietary supplement ingredients into the United States from China for use in consumer products. According to the indictment, the defendants assembled a false shipment designed to fool the FDA into believing that the company had destroyed substances that the FDA had blocked from distribution. But in reality, the company had already shipped the forbidden products, and instead, presented mislabeled substitutes to the FDA for destruction. The indictment further alleges that, in connection with this scheme, the defendants prepared fraudulent documents, including false certificates of analysis and false labels and submitted those fraudulent documents to the FDA when they suspected that an ingredient would be denied entry or would trigger inquiries from the FDA and Customs and Border Protection inspectors. These documents falsely declared the substances to be sucralose, melatonin, or other legal ingredients &#8211; and thereby served to conceal the actual contents, which included dangerous designer steroids and stimulants.

As with the branch&#8217;s efforts to combat fraud in the dietary supplements space, investigations involving the manufacturing of lifesaving drugs increasingly cross international boundaries. In conducting these investigations, the branch benefits greatly from our strong relationship with FDA, whose dedicated employees strive to protect public health around the world.

One noteworthy recent matter involved an FDA inspection of a manufacturing facility in India that led to the discovery of concerning issues associated with a cancer drug. In March 2021, Indian drug manufacturer Fresenius Kabi Oncology Limited, or FKOL, pleaded guilty to concealing and destroying records prior to an FDA plant inspection and ultimately paid $50 million in fines. FKOL owned and operated a manufacturing plant in Kalyani, West Bengal, India, that manufactured active pharmaceutical ingredients used in various cancer drug products. Prior to an inspection of the Kalyani facility, FKOL plant management directed employees to remove certain records from the premises and delete other records from computers &#8211; records that would have revealed that FKOL was manufacturing drug ingredients in contravention of FDA requirements. Kalyani plant employees removed computers, hardcopy documents, and other materials from the premises and deleted spreadsheets that contained evidence of the plant&#8217;s violative practices.

Using the Mutual Legal Assistance Treaty process, investigators traveled to India and heard directly from witnesses with firsthand knowledge of the misconduct. The Central Bureau of Investigation in India also provided invaluable assistance to U.S. authorities during the investigation.

As a result of these efforts, FKOL has been ordered to develop and implement a compliance and ethics program designed to prevent, detect, and correct violations of United States law relating to FKOL&#8217;s manufacture of cancer drugs intended for terminally-ill patients.

Another recent case involving the branch demonstrates the globally interconnected nature of the medical products industry. In 2021, Avanos, a U.S.-based multinational medical device corporation, entered into a deferred prosecution agreement with the Department of Justice, in which the company agreed to pay $22 million to resolve a criminal charge related to fraudulent misbranding of its MicroCool surgical gowns.

Surgical gowns are evaluated based upon how well they provide a barrier between the health care provider and potential contaminants. Specifically, gowns are rated from one to four, with four being reserved for gowns intended for surgeries and other high-risk medical procedures on patients suspected of having infectious diseases. Level four gowns protect both patients and health care workers from potential blood-borne pathogens. These products must pass certain tests on all critical areas of the gown where direct contact with blood and other fluids are most likely to occur.

The specific products involved in this case were manufactured into finished gowns at a plant in Honduras. As part of that process, the gown sleeves were sealed using machines that were highly variable and unstable &#8211; and, as a result, the operators of the machines were unable to consistently ensure that sleeves were properly sealed. And if they were not properly sealed, the sleeves could develop cracks or holes, or even come apart entirely. Unsurprisingly, the gowns repeatedly failed liquid-penetration monitoring testing.

Nevertheless, Avanos employees misrepresented MicroCool surgical gowns as meeting Level four standards, in multiple direct communications with hospital customers. &#160;Concerningly, certain customers had sought assurances because they needed to obtain gowns for use in responding to an Ebola virus outbreak &#8212; a disease that is carried via bodily fluids and which carries an average fatality rate of 50%. Avanos ultimately sold approximately $9 million worth of misbranded MicroCool surgical gowns to customers located both in the United States and abroad.

Under the terms of the deferred prosecution agreement, Avanos was ordered to pay $22 million, including a victim compensation payment of almost $9 million, a criminal monetary penalty of more than $12.5 million dollars, and a disgorgement payment of almost $700,000. Avanos also agreed to strengthen its compliance program and to abide by specific reporting requirements, which require the company to submit yearly reports to the government regarding the status of Avanos&#8217;s enhancements to its compliance program and internal controls, its policies and procedures aimed at deterring and detecting violations of the Food, Drug and Cosmetic Act and U.S. fraud laws, and the status of its remediation efforts.

The Avanos resolution, which was a joint effort between the branch, the Criminal Division&#8217;s Fraud Section, the U.S. Attorney&#8217;s Office for the Northern District of Texas, and FDA&#8217;s Office of Criminal Investigations, specifically noted the factors considered by the government in reaching the resolution. These included the nature and seriousness of the offense conduct and Avanos&#8217;s failure to timely and voluntarily self-disclose the misconduct. The government credited the fact that Avanos fully cooperated, conducted an internal investigation, promptly responded to requests from the department, assisted in making foreign-based employees available for interviews, and provided documents located in a foreign jurisdiction.

The failure to timely and voluntarily self-disclose misconduct was an important factor in the Avanos resolution. Since that matter was resolved, the department has made important revisions to the department&#8217;s corporate criminal enforcement policies and practices, including to the parameters for the voluntary self-disclosure of misconduct and cooperation credit.&#160; In September 2022, Deputy Attorney General Lisa Monaco announced that every department component responsible for prosecuting corporate crime would be required &#8220;to review its policies on corporate voluntary self-disclosure, and if the component lacks a formal, written policy to incentivize such self-disclosure, it must draft and publicly share such a policy.&#8221;

With the goal of making the benefits of voluntary self-disclosure &#8220;clear and predictable,&#8221; the Deputy Attorney General directed that all department components implement formalized policies setting forth expectations regarding:



The timeliness of a voluntary self-disclosure;

The requirement that the disclosure be accompanied by timely preservation, collection, and production of relevant documents and/or information;

The types of information and facts that must be provided as part of the disclosure process;

The benefits a corporation can expect to receive if it meets the standards for voluntary self-disclosure; and

Aggravating factors that would require a guilty plea even if the corporation voluntarily and timely self-disclosed, such as where the misconduct was deeply pervasive throughout the company.



Consistent with the Deputy Attorney General&#8217;s directive, earlier this year the Consumer Protection Branch released its voluntary disclosure policy. Absent aggravating factors, the Branch will not seek a guilty plea if a company has voluntarily self-disclosed to the Branch, fully cooperated, and timely and appropriately remediated the criminal conduct. But disclosure must be accompanied by timely preservation, collection, and production of relevant documents. And a company must disclose all relevant facts known at the time of the disclosure, including facts relating to individuals involved in the misconduct.&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;

As the Deputy Attorney General has noted, department components have not issued &#8220;cookie-cutter&#8221; policies. Rather, the Consumer Protection Branch carefully considered its unique mission when developing its policy, which encourages voluntary self-disclosure regarding potential violations involving the manufacture, distribution, sale, or marketing of products regulated by, or conduct under the jurisdiction of the FDA, the Consumer Products Safety Commission, the Federal Trade Commission, or the National Highway Transportation Safety Administration, as well as potential misconduct involving failures to report to, or misrepresentations to, those agencies.&#160;

The potential aggravating factors also have been carefully calibrated to address the Branch&#8217;s focus on health and safety and consumer fraud. Examples of such aggravating factors include:



Conduct that places consumers at significant risk of death or serious bodily injury; and

Conduct that intentionally or willfully targets older adults, immigrants, veterans and servicemembers, or other vulnerable victims.



Our policy is available on the Consumer Protection Branch&#8217;s webpage and contains an email address to which disclosures can be submitted.&#160;

All of these voluntary self-disclosure policies are part of a broader effort to ensure that companies and individuals engaged in misconduct are held accountable as expeditiously as possible.

The branch also is increasing its scrutiny of repeat offenders &#8211; in particular, wrongdoing involving the same personnel or management as the current misconduct.

Similarly, facts that indicate broader weakness in a company&#8217;s compliance culture or practices are likely to result in a more severe resolution than situations where a company has a track record of compliance and problems are promptly and appropriately addressed. Having a corporate culture that promotes ethical behavior matters, and the Department encourages companies to consider implementing compensation policies, including as to clawbacks, that are structured to incentivize compliant behavior and deter misconduct.

In conclusion, we are hopeful that these new policies will help to advance important investigations involving documents and witnesses located outside the United States and will encourage corporate leaders to invest in effective compliance programs.&#160;&#160;

And speaking of investments, thank you for investing your time and energy to travel to Washington and engage with your colleagues at this conference. I am grateful to the International Bar Association for providing me with the opportunity to speak with you this morning. Thank you.

</text></article><article><title>Foreign National Charged for $1.8M Wire Fraud and Money Laundering Scheme</title><url>https://justice.gov//opa/pr/foreign-national-charged-18m-wire-fraud-and-money-laundering-scheme</url><text>An indictment was unsealed today in the Central District of California charging a California businessman for allegedly soliciting investments under false pretenses and using investors&#8217; funds to support his own lavish lifestyle.

According to court documents, Amadou Kane Diallo, 44, a Senegalese national and resident of Laguna Niguel, was the CEO of two California-based companies: Virtual Advisors LLC and Liquide Inc. Diallo allegedly solicited investments in his companies from at least 11 individuals for purported business opportunities in technology, health care, real estate, home ownership, and service to the African diaspora. Diallo allegedly made various false representations, including that investor funds would be spent to further investors&#8217; interests, or not be spent at all, and instead used as &#8220;skin in the game&#8221; to attract institutional investors. Diallo is also alleged to have lied to potential investors, claiming that he had raised hundreds of millions of dollars for another investment firm and its real estate investment fund when, in fact, he had never raised any such funds.

Diallo allegedly caused at least 11 victim-investors to pay him, Virtual Advisors, and Liquide, more than $1.8 million. Contrary to his representations to investors, Diallo allegedly used their money to fund his own extravagant lifestyle, including making rent payments on his home; paying for luxury vehicles; buying clothes and fancy dinners; joining fitness clubs and spas; and hosting lavish events for foreign government officials.

Diallo is charged with 19 counts of wire fraud and two counts of money laundering. If convicted, he faces a maximum penalty of 20 years in prison on each of the wire fraud counts and a maximum penalty of 10 years in prison on each of the money laundering counts.

Assistant Attorney General Kenneth A. Polite, Jr. of the Justice Department&#8217;s Criminal Division, U.S. Attorney Martin Estrada for the Central District of California, Assistant Director Luis M. Quesada of the FBI&#8217;s Criminal Investigative Division, and Assistant Director in Charge Donald Alway of the FBI Los Angeles Field Office made the announcement.

The FBI is investigating the case.

Trial Attorney William E. Schurmann of the Criminal Division&#8217;s Fraud Section and Special Assistant U.S. Attorney Ryan G. Adams for the Central District of California are prosecuting the case.

If you believe you are a victim of Mr. Diallo&#8217;s conduct, please contact the Fraud Section&#8217;s Victim Witness Unit toll-free at (888) 549-3945 or by email at victimassistance.fraud@usdoj.gov.

An indictment is merely an allegation. All defendants are presumed innocent until proven guilty beyond a reasonable doubt in a court of law.

</text></article><article><title>Former New Mexico House of Representatives Candidate Charged for Shooting Spree</title><url>https://justice.gov//opa/pr/former-new-mexico-house-representatives-candidate-charged-shooting-spree</url><text>An indictment was unsealed today in the District of New Mexico charging a former candidate for the New Mexico House of Representatives for a shooting spree targeting the homes of four elected officials.

According to court documents, Solomon Pe&#241;a, 40, ran for District 14 of the New Mexico House of Representatives during the November 2022 mid-term elections. After his November 2022 electoral defeat, Pe&#241;a allegedly organized the shootings on the homes of two Bernalillo County commissioners and two New Mexico state legislators. The shootings, one of which involved a machine gun, were carried out between Dec. 4, 2022, and Jan. 3, with assistance from co-conspirators Demetrio Trujillo, 41; Jose Trujillo, 22; and others.&#160;

Before the shootings, Pe&#241;a visited the homes of at least three Bernalillo County commissioners and allegedly urged them not to certify the election results, claiming that the election had been &#8220;rigged&#8221; against him. Following the Bernalillo County board of commissioners&#8217; certification of the vote, Pe&#241;a allegedly hired others to conduct the shootings and carried out at least one of the shootings himself. At least three of the shootings occurred while children and other relatives of the victims were at home.&#160;&#160;&#160;

&#8220;There is no room in our democracy for politically motivated violence, especially when it is used to undermine election results,&#8221; said Assistant Attorney General Kenneth A. Polite, Jr. of the Justice Department&#8217;s Criminal Division. &#8220;As alleged, Solomon Pe&#241;a orchestrated four shootings at the homes of elected officials, in part because of their refusal to overturn his election defeat. Such violent actions target not only the homes and families of elected officials, but also our election system as a whole. The department will not hesitate to hold individuals accountable for acts of politically motivated violence.&#8221;

&#8220;In America, the integrity of our voting system is sacrosanct,&#8221; said U.S. Attorney Alexander M.M. Uballez for the District of New Mexico. &#8220;These charges strike at the heart of our democracy. Voters, candidates, and election officials must be free to exercise their rights and do their jobs safely and free from fear, intimidation, or influence, and with confidence that law enforcement and prosecuting offices will lead the charge when someone tries to silence the will of the people. To those who try to sow division, chaos, and fear into our democratic process, these charges should send a message that we are unified, organized, and undaunted.&#8221;&#160;&#160;&#160;

&#8220;The FBI and our partners are committed to ensuring violent crime investigations remain a priority,&#8221; said Assistant Director Luis Quesada of the FBI&#8217;s Criminal Investigative Division. &#8220;We will continue to pursue justice in cases like these in the name of safety for the American people.&#8221;

Pe&#241;a, Demetrio Trujillo, and Jose Trujillo are charged with conspiracy, interference with federally protected activities, and several firearms offenses, including the use of a machine gun. If convicted, Pe&#241;a faces a mandatory minimum of 60 years in prison. Jose Trujillo was also charged with possession with intent to distribute fentanyl and firearms offenses, including possession of a machine gun.

The FBI and the Albuquerque Police Department investigated the case.

Senior Litigation Counsel Victor R. Salgado of the Criminal Division&#8217;s Public Integrity Section and Assistant U.S. Attorneys Jeremy Pe&#241;a and Patrick E. Cordova for the District of New Mexico are prosecuting the case.

An indictment is merely an allegation. All defendants are presumed innocent until proven guilty beyond a reasonable doubt in a court of law.

</text></article><article><title>Kansas Man Indicted for Using Guns, Death Threats and Racial Slurs to Intimidate Black People</title><url>https://justice.gov//opa/pr/kansas-man-indicted-using-guns-death-threats-and-racial-slurs-intimidate-black-people</url><text>A Kansas man was indicted by a federal grand jury for using guns, death threats and racial slurs to intimidate Black people and interfere with multiple federally-protected rights.

The indictment alleges that, on July 27, 2022, Austin Schoemann, 30, of Wichita, brandished a firearm and used racial slurs in order to threaten two Black juveniles, Victims 1 and 2, while they were entering a QuikTrip gasoline station. In addition to intimidating and interfering with the two young men, Schoemann used his firearm to threaten a Black adult, Victim-3, who intervened in support of the juveniles&#8217; federally-protected right to be free from racial discrimination when visiting a gasoline station. The indictment also charges Schoemann with using a firearm during and in relation to these crimes of violence.

The indictment further alleges that beginning in January 2022 and continuing through August 2022, Schoemann interfered with the federally-protected housing rights of a white woman, Victim-4, by making threats to hurt or kill any Black people who visited her home. The indictment alleges that Schoemann made many of these threats in-person, and that he would stand outside of Victim-4&#8217;s house and shout threats and racial slurs on occasions when he believed she had Black visitors in her house or planned to do so. Schoemann is also charged with two violations of using the internet to distribute videos and messages to Victim-4&#8217;s family members and others in which he repeatedly threatened to shoot and kill Black people. &#160;

Schoemann faces a maximum penalty of 10 years in prison for the firearms charges, a maximum penalty of five years in prison for distribution of threating messages online and a mandatory minimum of seven years in prison for brandishing a firearm during and in relation to a crime of violence.&#160;

Assistant Attorney General Kristen Clarke of the Justice Department&#8217;s Civil Rights Division, U.S. Attorney Kate E. Brubacher for the District of Kansas and Special Agent in Charge Charles Dayoub of the FBI Kansas City Field Office made the announcement.&#160;

The FBI Kansas City Field Office investigated the case. &#160;

Assistant U.S. Attorney Aaron Smith for the District of Kansas and Trial Attorney Thomas Johnson of the Civil Rights Division&#8217;s Criminal Section are prosecuting the case.&#160;

An indictment is merely an allegation. All defendants are innocent until proven guilty beyond a reasonable doubt in a court of law.

</text></article><article><title>Bodybuilding Coach Arrested for Child Exploitation</title><url>https://justice.gov//opa/pr/bodybuilding-coach-arrested-child-exploitation</url><text>A bodybuilding coach was arrested today in Charlottesville, Virginia, for multiple child exploitation offenses.&#160;

According to court documents, between 2013 and April 2020, Elliott Simon Atwell, 33, of Charlottesville, allegedly enticed and coerced at least six minors to engage in sexually explicit conduct in order to produce recordings of the conduct. Atwell also allegedly enticed a minor to engage in criminal sexual activity and possessed images of minors &#8211; including prepubescent minors and minors under 12 years of age &#8211; who were engaged in sexually explicit conduct.&#160;

Atwell is charged with four counts of sexual exploitation of a minor, one count of enticement of a minor, and one count of possession of child pornography. If convicted, he faces a mandatory minimum sentence of 15 years and up to life in prison.

Assistant Attorney General Kenneth A. Polite, Jr. of the Justice Department&#8217;s Criminal Division, U.S. Attorney Christopher R. Kavanaugh for the Western District of Virginia, and Special Agent in Charge Stanley M. Meador of the FBI Richmond Field Office made the announcement.

The FBI is investigating the case.

Trial Attorney Jessica L. Urban of the Criminal Division&#8217;s Child Exploitation and Obscenity Section (CEOS) and Assistant U.S. Attorney Melanie Smith for the Western District of Virginia are prosecuting the case.

This case was brought as part of Project Safe Childhood, a nationwide initiative to combat the epidemic of child sexual exploitation and abuse, launched in May 2006 by the Department of Justice. Led by U.S. Attorneys&#8217; Offices and CEOS, Project Safe Childhood marshals federal, state, and local resources to better locate, apprehend, and prosecute individuals who exploit children via the internet, as well as to identify and rescue victims. For more information about Project Safe Childhood, please visit www.justice.gov/psc.

Any individuals who believe they or someone they know may have been victimized by Atwell are encouraged to contact the FBI at 1-800-CALL-FBI.

An indictment is merely an allegation. All defendants are presumed innocent until proven guilty beyond a reasonable doubt in a court of law.

</text></article><article><title>Two Utah Men Charged with Federal Hate Crime Offense</title><url>https://justice.gov//opa/pr/two-utah-men-charged-federal-hate-crime-offense</url><text>Two Utah men were charged with a federal hate crime April 26 following the return of an indictment by a federal grand jury in Salt Lake City, Utah.

According to the indictment, Nathan Thomas, 22, and Sebastian West, 22, both of Payson, allegedly assaulted a person identified by the initials D.J. because of D.J.&#8217;s actual and perceived race.

Assistant Attorney General Kristen Clarke of the Justice Department&#8217;s Civil Rights Division, U.S. Attorney Trina A. Higgins for the District of Utah and Acting Special Agent in Charge Cheyvoryea Gibson of the FBI Salt Lake City Field Office made the announcement.

The FBI Salt Lake City Field Office is investigating the case.

Assistant U.S. Attorneys Drew Yeates and Andrea Martinez for the District of Utah and Trial Attorney Andrew Manns of the Civil Rights Division&#8217;s Criminal Section are prosecuting the case.

</text></article><article><title>San Diego Restaurant Owners Charged with COVID-Relief Fraud and Money Laundering</title><url>https://justice.gov//opa/pr/san-diego-restaurant-owners-charged-covid-relief-fraud-and-money-laundering</url><text>A federal grand jury in San Diego returned an indictment on May 19 charging a California man and woman with conspiracy to commit wire fraud, wire fraud, and money laundering.

According to the indictment, Leronce Suel and Ravae Smith owned Rockstar Dough LLC and Chicken Feed LLC, both of which operated a series of restaurants in the San Diego area. From March 2020 to June 2022 Suel and Smith allegedly conspired to underreport over $1.7 million in gross receipts on Rockstar Dough LLC&#8217;s 2020 corporate tax return (From 1120S) filed with the IRS in order to qualify for the COVID-related Paycheck Protection Program and Restaurant Revitalization Funding loans. Suel and Smith also allegedly made materially false certifications on loan applications regarding the use of the money. The indictment charges that Suel and Smith made substantial cash withdrawals from their business bank accounts to launder the fraudulently obtained funds. As part of the conspiracy, Suel and Smith allegedly concealed more than $2.4 million in cash at their residence.

Suel and Smith made their initial court appearance yesterday before U.S. Magistrate Judge William V. Gallo of the U.S. District Court for the Southern District of California. If convicted, they face a maximum penalty of 30 years in prison for wire fraud and conspiracy to commit wire fraud and 10 years in prison for money laundering. A federal district court judge will determine any sentence after considering the U.S. Sentencing Guidelines and other statutory factors.

Acting Deputy Assistant Attorney General Stuart M. Goldberg of the Justice Department&#8217;s Tax Division and U.S. Attorney Randy S. Grossman for the Southern District of California made the announcement.

&#8220;During an unprecedented public health emergency, the United States provided these loan programs to deliver economic relief to Americans,&#8221; said U.S. Attorney Randy Grossman for the Southern District of California. &#8220;This office will investigate and prosecute those who exploited the global pandemic to unjustly enrich themselves. We encourage anyone with information regarding individuals who have engaged in COVID-relief fraud to come forward.&#8221; Grossman thanked the prosecution team and the investigative agency for their excellent work on this case.

&#8220;The CARES act was passed to aid those in need and provide much needed relief during the Covid-19 pandemic. Unfortunately, there are individuals and organizations who took advantage and targeted these programs to steal funds,&#8221; said Special Agent in Charge Tyler Hatcher of the Los Angeles Field Office. &#8220;Submitting false returns in support of a fraudulent loan application is a crime.&#160; IRS-CI is committed to aggressively investigating these crimes and bringing those to justice who stole funds and targeted relief programs during the pandemic.&#8221;

The IRS-Criminal Investigation are investigating the case.

Trial Attorney Julia Rugg of the Justice Department&#8217;s Tax Division and Assistant U.S. Attorney Christopher Beeler of the Southern District of California are prosecuting the case.

An indictment is merely an allegation and all defendants are presumed innocent until proven guilty beyond a reasonable doubt in a court of law.

</text></article><article><title>Federal Correctional Officer Charged with Aggravated Sexual Abuse</title><url>https://justice.gov//opa/pr/federal-correctional-officer-charged-aggravated-sexual-abuse</url><text>A federal correctional officer at the Federal Correctional Institution, Dublin (FCI Dublin) made his first appearance before the Northern District of California after a federal grand jury returned a 12-count indictment charging him for sexually abusing three female inmates in his custody.

According to the indictment, Darrell Wayne Smith, 54, now residing in Florida, was employed at FCI Dublin as a correctional officer when he engaged in sexual acts and sexual contact with three female inmates who were then serving prison sentences. The indictment describes 12 incidents between May 2019 and May 2021 during which Smith allegedly engaged in illegal sexual contact and acts with his victims, including digitally penetrating a victim&#8217;s anus by use of force.

&#8220;The charges announced today are the latest in the Justice Department&#8217;s campaign to root out sexual misconduct within the Bureau of Prisons,&#8221; said Deputy Attorney General Lisa O. Monaco. &#8220;As alleged, Darrell Smith exploited his authority to sexually abuse three vulnerable victims in custody at FCI Dublin. To enforce the BOP&#8217;s dual mission of providing a safe, humane environment for those in custody while preparing them to return to society, we will hold accountable all BOP personnel who abuse their authority.&#8221;

&#8220;For years, the defendant allegedly used his position of authority, as a federal corrections officer, to commit unspeakable acts of abuse&#160;and violence against multiple victims in a correctional institution,&#8221; said FBI Deputy Director Paul Abbate. &#8220;The FBI and our law enforcement partners are committed to aggressively pursuing those who violate the civil rights of others, no matter their rank or title. Nothing can undo the pain inflicted on the victims, but we hope today&#8217;s indictment is a further step towards justice.&#8221;

&#8220;The Department of Justice Office of the Inspector General is committed to bringing to justice every single BOP employee at FCI Dublin who sexually abused inmates.&#160;To date, those efforts have already included arrests and convictions of FCI Dublin&#8217;s former Warden and Chaplain,&#8221; said Inspector General Michael E. Horowitz. &#8220;Today&#8217;s indictment alleges brazen and violent sexual assault by Smith and alleges abuse of multiple inmates over several years. As evidenced by these charges, the OIG and FBI investigation remains ongoing, and we will continue to aggressively investigate allegations of abuse at FCI Dublin and across the Federal Bureau of Prisons.&#8221;

&#8220;This indictment shocks the conscience of anyone reading it,&#8221; said U.S. Attorney Ismail J. Ramsey for the Northern District of California. &#8220;The alleged conduct falls far below the minimum standards of decency required &#8211; much less, the standards of integrity expected &#8211; of any Bureau of Prisons employee. Rest assured, the Department will root out any such conduct and prosecute all persons who are responsible.&#8221;

Each of the alleged victims is identified in the indictment by initials and was in official detention and under Smith&#8217;s custodial, supervisory, and disciplinary authority at the time of the alleged illegal conduct. In addition, each count in the indictment corresponds with one encounter during which Smith allegedly engaged in unlawful sexual acts or contact with one of the victims.

Smith is charged with five counts of sexual abuse of a ward, six counts of abusive sexual contact, and one count of aggravated sexual abuse.

Smith faces a maximum of life in prison if convicted of the aggravated sexual abuse, a maximum of 15 years of in prison for each count of sexual abuse of a ward, and a maximum of two years in prison for each count of abusive sexual contact. In addition, as part of any sentence, the court may order a term of supervised release, a fine of up to $250,000 for each count, restitution, and additional assessments. A federal district judge will determine sentencing after considering the U.S. Sentencing Guidelines and other statutory factors.

Smith was arrested on May 11 and made his initial federal court appearance in the Northern District of Florida on the same day. Smith made his initial Northern District of California appearance this morning before U.S. Magistrate Judge Kandis A. Westmore. Smith&#8217;s next federal court appearance is scheduled for July 10.

DOJ OIG and the FBI investigated the case.

Assistant U.S. Attorneys Molly Priedeman and Andrew Paulson for the Northern District of California are prosecuting the case, with the assistance of Leeya Kekona.

An indictment is merely an allegation. All defendants are innocent until proven guilty beyond a reasonable doubt in a court of law.

</text></article><article><title>U.S. Law Enforcement Disrupts Networks Used to Transfer Fraud Proceeds, Taking Over 4,000 Actions in Fifth Campaign</title><url>https://justice.gov//opa/pr/us-law-enforcement-disrupts-networks-used-transfer-fraud-proceeds-taking-over-4000-actions</url><text>The Justice Department, FBI, U.S. Postal Inspection Service (USPIS), and other federal law enforcement agencies announced today the completion of a three-month campaign that disrupted networks used by foreign fraudsters to obtain fraud proceeds. Multiple law enforcement actions addressed conduct by individuals sometimes referred to as &#8220;money mules,&#8221; who have been providing critical services to fraudsters by receiving money from fraud victims and forwarding the fraud proceeds to the perpetrators (many of whom are based overseas). Some individuals knew they were facilitating fraud, while others first interacted with fraudsters as victims and may have been unaware that their activity furthered criminal activity.

Over approximately the last three months, law enforcement took over 4,000 actions against individuals responsible for facilitating a range of fraud schemes. These schemes included those that targeted consumers, such as lottery fraud and romance scams, as well as those that targeted businesses or pandemic funds.

The thousands of actions taken by law enforcement &#8212; which ranged from criminal prosecutions to civil actions, to warning letters &#8212; were designed to punish those who knowingly assisted fraudsters and to advise those who may have been unknowingly helping fraudsters that their conduct furthered crime. These actions are intended to deter overseas fraudsters from relying on U.S.-based individuals to facilitate schemes and thereby reduce the harm caused by foreign fraud operations.

This year&#8217;s effort marked the fifth U.S. law enforcement campaign disrupting these money transmitting networks. Since the first campaign, during which approximately 400 actions were taken by law enforcement, agencies have collectively taken over 12,000 actions. Investigations have shown that disrupting money transmitting networks has impeded fraudsters&#8217; abilities to receive funds, thereby reducing fraud victimization. These campaigns are part of a&#160;global effort&#160;to tackle money transmitting networks linked to illegal activity.

&#8220;Law enforcement is committed to reducing fraud using every tool at our disposal.&#160;Our efforts to disrupt networks used to transfer fraud proceeds, to educate the public about elder fraud, and to prosecute those involved in these schemes have stymied fraudsters,&#8221; said Associate Attorney General Vanita Gupta. &#8220;This initiative demonstrates what can be achieved through focused efforts and&#160;vigorous enforcement.&#8221;

&#8220;The money mule campaign was an effort to educate the public, disrupt criminal enterprises, and provide feedback to financial institutions who go to great lengths to implement anti-money laundering programs,&#8221; said Assistant Director Luis Quesada of the FBI&#8217;s Criminal Investigative Division. &#8220;The FBI values the partnership of the Justice Department's Consumer Protection Branch, USPIS, and other federal agencies who work together to disrupt criminal enterprises conducting fraud and money laundering schemes.&#8221;

&#8220;Anyone can be approached to be a money mule, but criminals often target students, those looking for work, and those on dating websites,&#8221; said USPIS Inspector in Charge Eric Shen of the Criminal Investigations Group. &#8220;When those individuals use the U.S. Mail to send or receive funds from fraudsters, postal inspectors are quick to step in and put a stop to money mule activities.&#8221;

This year&#8217;s effort was coordinated by the Justice Department's Consumer Protection Branch, FBI and USPIS, which were joined by Homeland Security Investigations, the Department of Labor Office of Inspector General and the Small Business Administration Office of Inspector General. Participating agencies collectively served over 4,000 letters warning individuals that their activities are facilitating fraud. These letters outlined the potential consequences for continuing to transmit illegally acquired funds. Participating agencies also filed 12 civil or administrative actions. Additionally, more than 25 individuals were criminally charged for knowingly receiving and forwarding victim funds or otherwise laundering fraud proceeds.





The U.S. Attorney&#8217;s Office for the District Massachusetts&#160;charged&#160;a defendant for using his accounting and &#8220;virtual CFO&#8221; business as a front to launder the proceeds of internet fraud schemes. As part of the alleged conspiracy, the defendant created dozens of shell companies and used those shell companies to open business bank accounts in Rhode Island and Massachusetts, through which the defendant laundered the criminal proceeds for his clients in exchange for fees. In total, since 2019, the defendant is alleged to have opened approximately 80 bank accounts (purportedly on behalf of 65 different companies), laundering approximately $35 million.





The U.S. Attorney&#8217;s Office for the Western District of North Carolina&#160;charged&#160;an individual for facilitating an international, multimillion-dollar tech support fraud. The indictment alleged that the defendant agreed to obtain payment-processing services in his name to process victim payments and laundered the proceeds domestically and internationally to bank accounts located in India, receiving 3% of the revenue in return.





The U.S. Attorneys' Offices for the Central District of California and the District of Nebraska charged individuals who, despite warnings from law enforcement, continued facilitating fraud. In the Central District of California, an individual was&#160;charged&#160;for her role in receiving funds from fraud victims, including victims of business email compromises. According to the charges, the defendant opened 11 bank accounts at seven separate financial institutions in furtherance of the scheme. In the District of Nebraska, two individuals were charged for facilitating a lottery fraud scheme, including by receiving cashier&#8217;s checks in the mail.





As in past years, participating agencies are working to raise awareness about how fraudsters recruit and use individuals to assist their fraud operations. Federal agencies conducted outreach to the public and industry, and also expanded partnerships with local, state, and foreign law enforcement agencies. The Commodities Futures Trading Commission released a&#160;public awareness message&#160;about how fraudsters use and recruit people to facilitate romance fraud and &#8220;wrong number&#8221; text message scams, where fraudsters strike up conversations touting their wealth and success in trading crypto assets, over-the-counter foreign currency, or gold contracts to try and convince consumers to &#8220;invest&#8221; in crypto assets.

The agencies involved in this effort urge consumers to be on the lookout for signs someone is trying to recruit them to receive and transmit fraud proceeds. Do not agree to receive money or checks mailed to you or sent to your bank account for someone you have met over the phone or online. Do not open a bank or cryptocurrency account at someone else&#8217;s direction. Fraudsters will lie to persuade you to help them. They may falsely tell you that they are helping you get a lottery prize, initiate a purported romantic relationship and then tell you that they need money, or pretend to offer you a job, an opportunity to invest in a business venture, or the chance to help in a charitable effort.

For more information on this initiative, please visit www.justice.gov/civil/consumer-protection-branch/money-mule-initiative.

Information about the Department of Justice&#8217;s Elder Fraud Initiative is available at www.justice.gov/elderjustice. If you or someone you know is age 60 or older and has been a victim of financial fraud, help is available at the National Elder Fraud Hotline: 1-833-FRAUD-11 (1-833-372-8311).&#160;&#160;&#160;

Information about the Justice Department's COVID-19 Fraud Enforcement Task Force is available at&#160;www.justice.gov/coronavirus.

For more information about the Consumer Protection Branch and its enforcement efforts, visit its website at&#160;www.justice.gov/civil/consumer-protection-branch.

A criminal indictment is merely an allegation. All defendants are presumed innocent until proven guilty beyond a reasonable doubt in a court of law.

</text></article><article><title>Foreign National Pleads Guilty to Role in International Human Smuggling and Cocaine Distribution Scheme</title><url>https://justice.gov//opa/pr/foreign-national-pleads-guilty-role-international-human-smuggling-and-cocaine-distribution-0</url><text>Honduran national pleaded guilty yesterday to his role in a scheme to illegally bring Honduran nationals to, and to distribute cocaine in, the United States.

According to court documents, Darrell Martinez, 41, and six co-conspirators schemed to bring Honduran nationals and cocaine from Honduras to the United States. In February 2022, Martinez and his co-conspirators attempted to illegally bring 23 Honduran nationals and at least 24 kilograms of cocaine from Utila, Honduras, to Cocodrie, Louisiana, by boat. At some point, the vessel developed engine trouble in the Gulf of Mexico. Martinez and his co-conspirators then chartered a boat and attempted to bring fuel to the disabled vessel so that it could complete its journey to the United States. Shortly thereafter, the U.S. Coast Guard located the vessel adrift approximately 95 miles off the coast of Grand Isle, Louisiana, and towed it to shore.

Martinez pleaded guilty to conspiracy to unlawfully bring aliens to the United States for financial gain and conspiracy to distribute five kilograms or more of cocaine hydrochloride. He is scheduled to be sentenced on Sept. 14 and faces a maximum penalty of life in prison. A federal district court judge will determine his sentence after considering the U.S. Sentencing Guidelines and other statutory factors.

On March 30, Josue Flores-Villeda, Martinez&#8217;s co-conspirator, pleaded guilty to his role in the scheme.

Assistant Attorney General Kenneth A. Polite, Jr. of the Justice Department&#8217;s Criminal Division, U.S. Attorney Duane A. Evans for the Eastern District of Louisiana, and Special Agent in Charge David Denton of the Homeland Security Investigations (HSI) New Orleans Field Office made the announcement.

HSI Houma, Louisiana, is investigating the case, with assistance from HSI Pittsburgh, HSI Atlanta, and the Louisiana Bureau of Investigation. The U.S. Coast Guard Investigative Service, U.S. Customs and Border Protection (CBP) Air and Marine Operations, Louisiana State Police, Pennsylvania State Police, the North Huntington Township Police, and the Terrebonne Parish Sheriff&#8217;s Office provided valuable assistance in the investigation.

Acting Deputy Chief Rami Badawy of the Criminal Division&#8217;s Human Rights and Special Prosecutions Section (HRSP) and Assistant U.S. Attorneys Carter Guice and Ben Myers for the Eastern District of Louisiana are prosecuting the case.

The investigation is being conducted under Joint Task Force Alpha (JTFA) which was established by Attorney General Merrick B. Garland in June 2021 to marshal the investigative and prosecutorial resources of the Department of Justice, in partnership with the Department of Homeland Security (DHS), to enhance U.S. enforcement efforts against the most prolific and dangerous human smuggling and trafficking groups operating in Mexico and the Northern Triangle Countries of Guatemala, El Salvador, and Honduras.

Since its creation, JTFA has successfully increased coordination and collaboration between the Justice Department, DHS, and other interagency law enforcement participants, and with foreign law enforcement partners, including El Salvador, Guatemala, Honduras, and Mexico; targeted those organizations who have the most impact on the United States; and coordinated significant smuggling indictments and extradition efforts in U.S. Attorneys&#8217; Offices across the country. JTFA is comprised of detailees from southwest border U.S. Attorneys&#8217; Offices, including the Southern District of Texas, the Western District of Texas, the District of New Mexico, the District of Arizona, and the Southern District of California, and dedicated support for the program is also provided by numerous components of the Criminal Division that are part of JTFA &#8211; led by HRSP and supported by the Office of Prosecutorial Development, Assistance, and Training (OPDAT), the Narcotic and Dangerous Drug Section (NDDS), the Money Laundering and Asset Recovery Section (MLARS), the Office of Enforcement Operations (OEO), the Justice Department&#8217;s Office of International Affairs (OIA), and the Organized Crime and Gang Section (OCGS). JTFA is made possible by substantial law enforcement investment from the DHS, FBI, DEA, and other partners.

The investigation is also supported by the Organized Crime Drug Enforcement Task Forces (OCDETF) and the Extraterritorial Criminal Travel Strike Force (ECT) program, a joint partnership between the Justice Department&#8217;s Criminal Division and HSI.&#160;The ECT program focuses on human smuggling networks that may present particular national security or public safety risks, or present grave humanitarian concerns.&#160;ECT has dedicated investigative, intelligence, and prosecutorial resources.&#160;ECT coordinates and receives assistance from other U.S. government agencies and foreign law enforcement authorities.

</text></article><article><title>Man Charged for Alleged Participation in $45M CoinDeal Investment Fraud Scheme Involving Over 10,000 Victims</title><url>https://justice.gov//opa/pr/man-charged-alleged-participation-45m-coindeal-investment-fraud-scheme-involving-over-10000</url><text>A Nevada man has been charged for his alleged participation in CoinDeal, an investment fraud scheme that defrauded more than 10,000 victims of over $45 million.

Bryan Lee, 57, of Las Vegas, will make his initial appearance in federal court today in Las Vegas.

According to court documents, Lee allegedly conspired with Neil Chandran and others to defraud investors in companies that Chandran controlled. The companies operated under the banner of &#8220;ViRSE,&#8221; and included Free Vi Lab, Studio Vi Inc., ViDelivery Inc., ViMarket Inc., and Skalex USA Inc., among others. The companies were supposedly developing virtual-world technologies, including their own cryptocurrency, for use in a metaverse. Chandran allegedly misled investors by falsely promising extremely high returns on the premise that his companies were about to be acquired by a consortium of wealthy buyers. As further alleged, Lee was the nominee owner and director of ViMarket, and took direction from Chandran for how to disburse investor funds received into ViMarket&#8217;s bank accounts. Lee and Chandran allegedly misappropriated millions of dollars of investor funds and spent it on luxury cars and real estate.

Lee is charged by indictment with one count of conspiracy, two counts of mail fraud, one count of wire fraud, and three counts of engaging in monetary transactions in criminally derived property. If convicted, Lee faces up to 20 years in prison for each of the wire fraud, mail fraud, and conspiracy counts, and up to 10 years in prison for each count of engaging in unlawful monetary transactions.

Chandran was arrested in June 2022 and charged for his alleged role in the scheme. Michael Glaspie, who fraudulently marketed the investment with Chandran&#8217;s companies under the name &#8220;CoinDeal,&#8221; pleaded guilty to one count of wire fraud in February 2023 and is scheduled to be sentenced on June 16.

Assistant Attorney General Kenneth A. Polite, Jr. of the Justice Department&#8217;s Criminal Division, U.S. Attorney Steven A. Russell for the District of Nebraska, Assistant Director Luis Quesada of the FBI&#8217;s Criminal Investigative Division, and Assistant Director in Charge David Sundberg of the FBI Washington Field Office made the announcement.

The FBI Washington Field Office is investigating the case with significant assistance provided by the FBI Las Vegas and Omaha Field Offices.

Assistant Chief William E. Johnston and Trial Attorney Tian Huang of the Criminal Division&#8217;s Fraud Section and Assistant U.S. Attorney Donald Kleine for the District of Nebraska are prosecuting the case. Senior Policy Advisor Darrin McCullough of the Criminal Division&#8217;s Money Laundering and Asset Recovery Section is handling forfeiture.

All investor victims of this fraud are encouraged to visit the webpage www.justice.gov/criminal-vns/case/united-states-v-neil-chandran-united-states-v-michael-glaspie to identify themselves as potential victims and obtain more information on their rights as victims, including the opportunity to submit a victim impact statement.

An indictment is merely an allegation. All defendants are presumed innocent until proven guilty beyond a reasonable doubt in a court of law.

</text></article><article><title>MS-13 Gang Member Sentenced for Racketeering Conspiracy and Murders</title><url>https://justice.gov//opa/pr/ms-13-gang-member-sentenced-racketeering-conspiracy-and-murders</url><text>A Maryland man was sentenced today to 28 years in prison for his part in a racketeering conspiracy, including two murders, related to his participation in La Mara Salvatrucha&#160;(MS-13).

According to court documents, from at least August 2018 through July 2021, Franklyn Edgardo Sanchez, aka Freddy, aka Magic, aka Miclo, aka Delinquente, 25, of Adelphi, was a member of MS-13, a transnational criminal enterprise and one of the largest street gangs in the United States that is composed primarily of immigrants or descendants from El Salvador and other central American countries. Sanchez was a member and associate of Weedams Locos Salvatrucha (WLS), an MS-13 clique operating primarily in Adelphi.

As part of the conspiracy, MS-13 members are required to commit acts of violence to maintain membership and discipline within the gang as well as against rival gangs. One of the principal rules of MS-13 is that its members must attack and kill rivals, known as &#8220;chavalas,&#8221; whenever possible. Participation in criminal activity by a member, particularly in violent acts directed at rival gangs or as directed by gang leadership, increases the respect accorded to that member, resulting in that member maintaining or increasing his position in the gang and opens the door to promotion to a leadership position.&#160;

On Feb. 23, 2020, at the direction of an MS-13 leader, Sanchez and co-defendant Hernan Yanes-Rivera, aka Recio, shot and killed a former WLS member (Victim-1), in retaliation for the victim&#8217;s suspected cooperation with law enforcement. As a result of his participation in the murder, Sanchez was promoted within the hierarchy of MS-13.

On Aug. 8, 2020, Sanchez and several WLS members agreed to murder another individual (described in the indictment as Victim 4), who was suspected of cooperating with law enforcement and to whom Sanchez owed a debt. After driving to a wooded area in Prince George&#8217;s County, Maryland, WLS leader Brayan Alexander Torres, aka Spooky, called Victim 4 and told him to come to the wooded area to participate in a disciplinary beating of Sanchez, even though the gang intended to murder Victim 4. When Victim 4 arrived, Sanchez and another MS-13 member shot Victim 4. Sanchez then stabbed Victim 4 with a knife.&#160;

To prevent the discovery of DNA or other evidence and to hinder the investigation and prosecution of Victim 4&#8217;s murder, Torres called other WLS members, including Agustino Eugenio Rivas Rodriguez, aka Terrible, and ordered them to bring shovels to the wooded area, where they dug a hole and buried Victim 4&#8217;s body.

Sanchez also participated in money laundering by transferring gang funds to MS-13 members and associates in El Salvador.

Sanchez, Torres, Yanes-Rivera, and Rivas Rodriguez all previously pleaded guilty to racketeering conspiracy. By the terms of their plea agreements, Torres faces 28 years in prison, Yanes-Rivera faces 22 years in prison, and Rivas Rodriguez faces 16 years in prison. Torres is scheduled to be sentenced on Aug. 31, Yanes-Rivera is scheduled to be sentenced on July 28, and Rivas Rodriguez is scheduled to be sentenced on July 21.

Assistant Attorney General Kenneth A. Polite, Jr. of the Justice Department&#8217;s Criminal Division, U.S. Attorney Erek L. Barron for the District of Maryland, Assistant Director Luis Quesada of the FBI's Criminal Investigative Division, Special Agent in Charge Thomas J. Sobocinski of the FBI Baltimore Field Office, Special Agent in Charge James C. Harris of the Homeland Security Investigations (HSI) Baltimore Field Office, and Chief Malik Aziz of the Prince George&#8217;s County Police Department made the announcement.

The FBI, HSI, and Prince George&#8217;s County Police Department investigated the case, with assistance from the Montgomery County Police Department and U.S. Immigration and Customs Enforcement.

Trial Attorneys Brendan Woods and Christopher Taylor of the Criminal Division&#8217;s Organized Crime and Gang Section and Assistant U.S. Attorney Joel Crespo for the District of Maryland prosecuted the case.

This case is part of Project Safe Neighborhoods (PSN), a program bringing together all levels of law enforcement and the communities they serve to reduce violent crime and make our neighborhoods safer for everyone. PSN, an evidence-based program proven to be effective at reducing violent crime, is the centerpiece of the Department of Justice&#8217;s violent crime reduction efforts. Through PSN, a broad spectrum of stakeholders work together to identify the most pressing violent crime problems in the community and develop comprehensive solutions to address them. As part of this strategy, PSN focuses enforcement efforts on the most violent offenders and partners with locally based prevention and reentry programs for lasting reductions in crime.

This case is also part of an Organized Crime Drug Enforcement Task Force (OCDETF) investigation. OCDETF identifies, disrupts, and dismantles the highest-level criminal organizations that threaten the United States using a prosecutor-led, intelligence-driven, multi-agency approach that leverages the strengths of federal, state, and local law enforcement agencies against criminal networks.&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;

</text></article><article><title>Judge Imposes Eight Consecutive Life Sentences Plus 260 Years in Prison for ISIS-Inspired 2017 Murder of Eight Victims and Attempted Murder of 18 Others in NYC Truck Attack</title><url>https://justice.gov//opa/pr/judge-imposes-eight-consecutive-life-sentences-plus-260-years-prison-isis-inspired-2017</url><text>Sayfullo Saipov, 34, of Uzbekistan, was sentenced to eight consecutive life sentences, two concurrent life sentences, and a consecutive sentence of 260 years in prison for carrying out a terrorist attack on Oct. 31, 2017, in the name of the Islamic State of Iraq and al-Sham (ISIS), in which Saipov used a truck to murder eight victims and injure many more on a bike path in lower Manhattan.

On Jan. 26, a jury convicted Saipov of all 28 counts in the indictment, which charged Saipov with murder for the purpose of gaining entrance to a racketeering enterprise (ISIS); assault with a dangerous weapon and attempted murder for the purpose of gaining entrance to a racketeering enterprise (ISIS); providing material support to a designated foreign terrorist organization (ISIS) resulting in death; and damage and destruction to a motor vehicle resulting in death. On March 13, 2023, the same jury was unable to reach a unanimous verdict on whether Saipov should be sentenced to death, resulting in a mandatory sentence of life in prison.

&#8220;Today&#8217;s sentence means that Sayfullo Saipov will spend the rest of his life in federal prison for brutally murdering eight innocent victims during his carefully calculated ISIS terrorist attack,&#8221; said Attorney General Merrick B. Garland. &#8220;The Department of Justice honors the victims, their families, and the survivors of this horrific attack. We will continue to vigorously defend the American people from threats of terrorism and will work tirelessly to bring those who perpetrate terrorist attacks to justice.&#8221;

&#8220;Although it has been more than five years since Sayfullo Saipov carried out this horrific, senseless attack in the name of ISIS, the FBI never relented in our pursuit of justice for the victims and their loved ones,&#8221; said FBI Director Christopher Wray. &#8220;This case demonstrates the FBI&#8217;s steadfast commitment to working with our law enforcement partners to hold accountable those who commit acts of violence inspired by terrorist groups.&#8221;

&#8220;In March 2023, a jury determined that Sayfullo Saipov would spend the rest of his life in prison for his heinous crimes. Today, the court issued the maximum possible penalty on each count of conviction and ordered that eight of Saipov&#8217;s life sentences along with 260 years in prison will run consecutively to the other sentences imposed,&#8221; said U.S. Attorney Damian Williams for the Southern District of New York. &#8220;These eight life sentences account for the eight lives Saipov stole when he committed his vicious ISIS attack. The 260 years in prison constitutes the maximum penalty for the 18 attempted murders Saipov cruelly committed, which included the attempted murders of four children. More than just holding Saipov accountable for his depraved crimes, the proceedings today gave further voice to the victims. More than 20&#160;victims and family members addressed the Court and confronted Saipov. They bravely and boldly shared their pain and devastation. While we cannot make these victims whole after what Saipov stole from them, this office along with our partners in the Department of Justice and the FBI are proud to have served the victims and sought justice on their behalf.&#8221;&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;

As set forth in public documents in the case and statements made during court proceedings:

On Halloween afternoon in 2017, Saipov used a 6,000-pound truck to strike more than 20 innocent people on the Hudson River Bike Path in lower Manhattan. Saipov killed eight of his victims and critically injured many others, including a 14-year-old child. Saipov&#8217;s surviving victims suffered amputations, serious brain injuries, life-altering physical injuries, and significant psychological trauma. Saipov committed his attack after years of devotion to the brutal terrorist organization ISIS and after months of careful planning. In the weeks before his attack, for example, Saipov rented a truck to practice maneuvering it so that he could hit as many people as possible. Saipov brought a note to the attack with the ISIS flag and rallying cry written on it. After his attack, while in custody at a hospital, Saipov told the FBI that he committed the attack in response to calls from the leader of ISIS and that he was proud of what he had done. Saipov smiled when describing his attack and sought to hang the ISIS flag in his hospital room.

After the attack, ISIS praised Saipov as an Islamic State soldier and called his attack one of the most prominent attacks in the United States. In the years since his attack, Saipov continued to demonstrate his devotion to ISIS, including though statements in court, recorded telephone calls, and writings seized from his prison cell. In prison, Saipov also made statements confirming his continued belief that enemies of ISIS should be eliminated and threatening to cut the heads off of corrections officers. At the liability and sentencing phases of trial, many of Saipov&#8217;s victims and their family members bravely described the terror he caused and the pain and suffering they continue to endure.

While the jury determined that Saipov would be sentenced to life in prison on six counts of conviction, Judge Broderick sentenced Saipov to the statutory maximum penalty on each count of conviction and ordered that Saipov&#8217;s sentences on the counts of conviction charging him with murder and attempted murder of particular victims would run consecutively to all other sentences imposed. In total, Saipov was sentenced to eight consecutive life sentences, 260 years in prison to run consecutively, and two additional life sentences to run concurrently to each other and to all other sentences imposed. The judge will issue an order concerning restitution to victims at a later date.

More than 20 victims and family members delivered emotional and powerful victim impact statements at Saipov&#8217;s sentencing.

The FBI&#8217;s New York Joint Terrorism Task Force, which consists of investigators and analysts from the FBI, the New York City Police Department, and over 50 other federal, state, and local agencies investigated the case. The Department of Homeland Security&#8217;s Homeland Security Investigations; the Justice Department&#8217;s National Security Division&#8217;s Counterterrorism Section and Criminal Division&#8217;s Capital Case Section and Organized Crime and Gang Section provided valuable assistance, as did the Justice Department&#8217;s Office of Enforcement Operations and Office of International Affairs.

Assistant U.S. Attorneys Amanda L. Houle, Jason A. Richman, Alexander Li, and Andrew Dember for the Southern District of New York, with the assistance of Paralegal Specialist Daniel Sitko, and Trial Attorney John Cella of the National Security Division&#8217;s Counterterrorism Section and Trial Attorney Michael Warbel of the&#160;Criminal Division&#8217;s Capital Case Section prosecuted the case.

</text></article><article><title>Justice Department Announces Five Cases as Part of Recently Launched Disruptive Technology Strike Force</title><url>https://justice.gov//opa/gallery/justice-department-announces-five-cases-part-recently-launched-disruptive-technology</url><text>On Tuesday May 16th, 2023 Assistant Attorney General for National Security Matthew G. Olsen and Assistant Secretary for Export Enforcement Matthew S. Axelrod of the Commerce Department led a press conference to announce the first charges and arrests in connection with the Disruptive Technology Strike Force. Launched earlier in 2023 by Deputy Attorney General Lisa O. Monaco, the Strike Force is a joint venture between the Justice and Commerce Departments to target illicit actors, strengthen supply chains, and protect critical technological assets from being acquired or used by nation-state adversaries.

</text></article><article><title>Justice Department Announces Five Cases as Part of Recently Launched Disruptive Technology Strike Force</title><url>https://justice.gov//opa/pr/justice-department-announces-five-cases-part-recently-launched-disruptive-technology-strike</url><text>The Justice Department today announced criminal charges in five cases and four arrests from five different U.S. Attorney&#8217;s offices in connection with the recently launched multi-agency Disruptive Technology Strike Force.

The Disruptive Technology Strike Force is co-led by the Departments of Justice and Commerce to counter efforts by hostile nation-states to illicitly acquire sensitive U.S. technology to advance their authoritarian regimes and facilitate human rights abuses. The Strike Force&#8217;s work has led to the unsealing of charges against multiple defendants in five cases accused of crimes including export violations, smuggling and theft of trade secrets.

Two of these cases involve the disruption of alleged procurement networks created to help the Russian military and intelligence services obtain sensitive technology in violation of U.S. laws. In the Eastern District of New York, a Greek national was arrested on May 9 for federal crimes in connection with allegedly acquiring more than 10 different types of sensitive technologies on behalf of the Russian government and serving as a procurement agent for two Russian Specially Designated Nationals (SDNs) operating on behalf of Russia&#8217;s intelligence services. In the District of Arizona, two Russian nationals were arrested for their involvement in a procurement scheme to supply multiple Russian commercial airline companies &#8211; which were subject to bans from engaging in certain type of commercial transactions &#8211; with export-controlled parts and components, including braking technology.

Two of the other cases announced today charge former software engineers with stealing software and hardware source code from U.S. tech companies in order to market it to Chinese competitors. In the Central District of California, a senior software engineer was arrested on May 5 for theft of trade secrets for allegedly stealing source code used in metrology software which is used in &#8220;smart&#8221; automotive manufacturing equipment. The defendant then allegedly marketed the stolen technology to multiple Chinese companies. In the Northern District of California, a citizen of the People&#8217;s Republic of China (PRC) and former Apple engineer is accused of allegedly stealing thousands of documents containing the source code for software and hardware pertaining to Apple&#8217;s autonomous vehicle technology. This defendant fled to China and is believed to be working for a PRC-based autonomous vehicle competitor.

The fifth and final case involves a Chinese procurement network established to provide Iran with materials used in weapons of mass destruction (WMDs) and ballistic missiles. In the Southern District of New York, a PRC national is charged with allegedly participating in a scheme to use his employer to conduct transactions with a U.S. financial institution for the benefit of a purported Iranian entity, as part of an effort to provide isostatic graphite, a material used in the production of WMDs, to Iran.

&#8220;These charges demonstrate the Justice Department&#8217;s commitment to preventing sensitive technology from falling into the hands of foreign adversaries, including Russia, China, and Iran,&#8221; said Assistant Attorney General Matthew G. Olsen of the Justice Department&#8217;s National Security Division. &#8220;We will not tolerate those who would violate U.S. laws to allow authoritarian regimes and other hostile nations to use advanced technology to threaten U.S. national security and undermine democratic values around the world.&#8221;

&#8220;Protecting sensitive American technology &#8211; like source code for &#8216;smart&#8217; automotive manufacturing equipment or items used to develop quantum cryptography &#8211; from being illegally acquired by our adversaries is why we stood up the Disruptive Technology Strike Force,&#8221; said Matthew S. Axelrod, Assistant Secretary for Export Enforcement at the Department of Commerce. &#8220;The Strike Force actions announced today reflect the core mission of our Export Enforcement team &#8211; keeping our country&#8217;s most sensitive technologies out of the world&#8217;s most dangerous hands.&#8221;&#160;

&#8220;The theft of technology and trade secrets from U.S. companies is a threat to our economic and national security,&#8221; said Assistant Director Suzanne Turner of the FBI&#8217;s Counterintelligence Division. &#8220;The charges announced today aren&#8217;t the only instances of foreign adversaries trying to steal our technology. Combating the illegal transfer of technology is one of the FBI&#8217;s highest priorities, and we will continue to work with our federal partners, including the Department of Commerce, to investigate those who steal U.S. technology to ultimately use it in weapons that threaten us and our allies.&#8221;

&#8220;The protection of sensitive U.S. technologies has been and continues to be a top priority for HSI,&#8221; said Assistant Director James Mancuso of Homeland Security Investigations. &#8220;HSI and the partners of the Strike Force will ensure that the U.S. maintains its technologic edge to protect the economic and national security interests of the United States. The Strike Force will be relentless in its pursuit of bad actors that attempt the theft of any sensitive U.S. technologies.&#8221;

United States v. Bogonikolos,&#160;Eastern District of New York

A criminal complaint was unsealed today in federal court in Brooklyn charging Dr. Nikolaos &#8220;Nikos&#8221; Bogonikolos, 59, of Athens, Greece, with wire fraud conspiracy and smuggling. Bogonikolos was arrested in Paris on May 9 and remains in custody pending the resolution of extradition proceedings.

&#8220;As alleged, while ostensibly operating as a defense contractor for NATO and other ally countries, the defendant and his Aratos Group were double dealing, helping to fuel Russia&#8217;s war effort and their development of next generation weapons,&#8221; said U.S. Attorney Breon Peace for the Eastern District of New York. &#8220;Our office continues to work tirelessly to ensure that disruptive technologies do not fall into the wrong hands.&#8221;

As alleged in the complaint, the defendant headed the Aratos Group (Aratos), a collection of defense and technology companies in the Netherlands and Greece, which are both member countries of the North Atlantic Treaty Organization (NATO). According to Aratos&#8217;s website, the companies&#8217; areas of expertise included space technologies, homeland security, blockchain, and counter-drone systems. One of Aratos&#8217; subsidiaries, Aratos Systems BV, was a finalist in the NATO Innovation Challenge for space applications in 2021 for a proposal involving the use of artificial intelligence and blockchain technology for satellites and spacecraft. The defendant presented himself having experience advising the European Parliament and &#8220;governments worldwide,&#8221; and Aratos supplied defense equipment and related technologies to countries in the Middle East, Africa and Asia. &#160;

However, as alleged in the complaint, since 2017 the defendant has been involved in smuggling U.S.-origin military and dual-use technologies to Russia in violation of U.S. law. These highly regulated and sensitive components included advanced electronics and sophisticated testing equipment used in military applications, including quantum cryptography and nuclear weapons testing, as well as tactical battlefield equipment. The defendant claimed that these items were to be used by Aratos, when in reality they were reshipped and sent to Russia in violation of U.S. law. Some of the Russian end users included nuclear and quantum research facilities, as well as Military Unit 33949, part of the Russian Foreign Intelligence Service, known as the SVR.

As described in the complaint, many of these orders were solicited by Serniya Engineering and Sertal LLC (the Serniya Network), Moscow-based companies that operate under the direction of Russian intelligence services. Following Russia&#8217;s invasion of Ukraine in February 2022, the U.S. Department of the Treasury&#8217;s Office of Foreign Assets Control (OFAC) and the Department of Commerce (DOC) Bureau of Industry and Security (BIS) levied sanctions against Serniya, Sertal, and several individuals and companies used in the scheme, calling them &#8220;instrumental to the Russian Federation&#8217;s war machine.&#8221;

As alleged in the complaint, the defendant was recruited as a procurement agent for Russia in 2017. In an email message with a Serniya affiliate, on Dec. 27, 2017, the defendant was told to come to Moscow alone &#8220;since the agenda will be a very sensitive one.&#8221; Regarding one subsequent order, the defendant advised that he would falsify an export license, saying &#8220;I sign that the items are only for Netherlands ;) . . . Sensitive case . . . For the same reason I cannot press the [U.S.] supplier.&#8221; The defendant also signed several false end use statements and provided them to U.S. companies, certifying that Aratos was the end user of the requested items, that Aratos would not reexport the goods elsewhere, and that the goods would not be used for weapons development.

The FBI New York Field Office is investigating the case.

Assistant U.S. Attorney Artie McConnell and Trial Attorney Scott A. Claffee of the National Security Division&#8217;s Counterintelligence and Export Control Section are prosecuting the case, with assistance provided by Litigation Analyst Ben Richmond.

The Justice Department&#8217;s Office of International Affairs provided valuable support to the investigation. The United States thanks French authorities for their assistance.

The investigation was also coordinated through the Justice Department&#8217;s Task Force KleptoCapture, an interagency law enforcement task force dedicated to enforcing sanctions, export controls and economic countermeasures imposed in response to Russia&#8217;s unprovoked military invasion of Ukraine. For more on the work of Task Force KleptoCapture, see&#160;here.

United States v. Besedin and Patsulya,&#160;District of Arizona

On May 11, two Russian nationals, Oleg Sergeyevich Patsulya and Vasilii Sergeyevich Besedin were arrested in the District of Arizona and charged via criminal complaint with conspiracy to violate the Export Control Reform Act (ECRA) and conspiracy to commit international money laundering.

The complaint alleges that Patsulya and Besedin, both of whom reside in Miami-Dade County, Florida, used their Florida limited liability company, MIC P&amp;I, LLC, and worked with others to evade U.S. export laws and regulations to send aircraft parts to Russian airline companies. The complaint alleges that Patsulya and Besedin fielded requests for parts directly from the Russian airlines &#8212; many of which were already subject to increased export sanctions as a result of Russia&#8217;s further invasion of Ukraine &#8212; and then used intermediary companies and foreign bank accounts in third-party countries to mask the true identity of the customers and the source of payments. Patsulya and Besedin then approached aircraft parts suppliers in the United States, lied about who their customers were, and lied about where the parts would be going. In furtherance of their criminal conspiracy, Patsulya and Besedin traveled to the District of Arizona in September 2022 and attempted to purchase export-controlled aircraft brake systems from an Arizona aircraft parts supply company.

If convicted, the defendants face up to 20 years in prison for violating the ECRA and up to 20 years in prison for conspiring to commit international money laundering.

The BIS Phoenix Field Office and the FBI Phoenix Field Office are conducting the joint investigation. The BIS Boston Field Office, FBI Miami Field Office, HSI Phoenix Field Office, Customs and Border Protection-Phoenix Field Office, and the U.S. Marshals Office in Miami provided valuable assistance.

Assistant U.S. Attorneys Todd M. Allison and William G. Voit for the District of Arizona and Trial Attorney Christopher M. Rigali of the National Security Division&#8217;s Counterintelligence and Export Control Section are prosecuting the case. The U.S. Attorney&#8217;s Office for the Southern District of Florida provided valuable assistance.

The investigation was also coordinated through the Justice Department&#8217;s Task Force KleptoCapture, an interagency law enforcement task force dedicated to enforcing sanctions, export controls and economic imposed in response to Russia&#8217;s unprovoked military invasion of Ukraine.

United States v. Li,&#160;Central District of California

A California man was arrested on May 6 in the Central District of California on criminal charges related to his alleged theft of sensitive technologies from his Southern California-based employers and use of them to market his own competing company to businesses in the PRC.

According to court documents, Liming Li, 64, of Rancho Cucamonga, stole trade secrets belonging to two of his former employers based in Southern California then used them to build his own competing business in China.

Li was arrested at Ontario International Airport on May 6 after arriving on a flight from Taiwan pursuant to a criminal complaint that charges him with theft of trade secrets. Since his arrest, Li has been in federal custody, and he has a detention hearing scheduled for May 22.

&#8220;Li stole thousands of files of sensitive technology that did not belong to him and used it to help foreign companies build competing technology &#8211; technology that could be used in the manufacture of nuclear submarines and military aircraft,&#8221; said U.S. Attorney Martin Estrada for the Central District of California. &#8220;Protecting our nation&#8217;s national security is paramount, and my office will aggressively investigate and prosecute those who misappropriate sensitive intellectual property to the benefit of foreign actors.&#8221;

According to an affidavit filed with the complaint, from 1996 to November 2019, Li worked in various engineering, management, and software development roles for two companies in Southern California software businesses. The companies are identified in court documents as &#8220;Company #1&#8221; and &#8220;Company #2.&#8221;

These software programs are related to high precision measurement studies interpretation and point cloud technology, which often are used in making 3D models. They can be used in various sensitive manufacturing contexts, including manufacturing parts for nuclear submarines and military aircraft, and are subject to U.S. export controls for national security, nuclear nonproliferation and anti-terrorism reasons. As a result of its military application, federal law mandates that this software cannot be exported to the PRC without a license from the Department of Commerce.

Li worked for Company #1 from 1996 to 2018 and then worked at Company #2 from 2018 until November 2019. Shortly before beginning his employment with the Company #2, Li and his wife established their own business, JSL Innovations, which was based out of their Rancho Cucamonga home.

After Company #2 terminated Li, company security discovered that Li was using his company-issued laptop to attempt to download files from Company #2&#8217;s root directory onto his personal external hard drive, according to the complaint affidavit. Company security searched Li&#8217;s company-issued laptop and found a folder labeled &#8220;ChinaGovernment.&#8221; That folder allegedly contained numerous documents showing Li&#8217;s efforts to participate in the PRC&#8217;s Thousand Talents Program and to use JSL Innovations to provide services and technology to PRC business and government entities related to the export-controlled and trade secret technology that Li took from his former employers in Southern California.

In March 2020, Li entered into an agreement with a PRC-based manufacturing company to serve as its chief technology officer. Li&#8217;s agreement with this employer required him to spend at least six months per year in the PRC.

Six months later, FBI agents executed a search warrant at Li&#8217;s home and found numerous digital devices containing millions of files belonging to Company #1 and Company #2 and containing the source code for those companies&#8217; proprietary software, the complaint alleges. Although the source code files had been developed by and belonged to these companies, some of the files had been moved into folders labeled &#8220;JSL&#8221; or &#8220;JSL Projects.&#8221;

Both Company #1 and Company #2 derive significant value from the secrecy of their proprietary software source code and take extensive steps to protect the source code from discovery by competitors.

If convicted, Li faces a statutory maximum sentence of 10 years in federal prison.

The FBI is investigating this matter with substantial assistance from the Department of Commerce BIS.

Assistant U.S. Attorneys Solomon Kim of the Terrorism and Export Crimes Section; David Ryan, Chief of the Terrorism and Export Crimes Section; Aaron Frumkin of the Cyber and Intellectual Property Crime Section; and Trial Attorney Stephen Marzen of the National Security Division&#8217;s Counterintelligence and Export Control Section are prosecuting the case.

United States v. Wang,&#160;Northern District of California

Today, a federal court in the Northern District of California unsealed an indictment of former Apple Incorporated (Apple) employee Weibao Wang, 35, formerly of Mountain View, California, for charges related to his alleged theft and attempted theft of trade secrets in connection with a scheme to access, download, and steal Apple technology related to autonomous systems.

According to the indictment, Apple hired Wang to work as a software engineer beginning in March 2016. The indictment describes how Wang signed a confidentiality agreement with Apple. The indictment further states that Apple provided Wang with in-person secrecy training that covered the appropriate handling of confidential material and established rules prohibiting the transfer and transmission of the company&#8217;s intellectual property without Apple&#8217;s consent. Wang was assigned to work with a team at Apple that designed and developed hardware and software for autonomous systems, which can have a variety of applications, such as self-driving cars.

According to the indictment, in November 2017, Wang signed a letter accepting an offer of full-time employment as a staff engineer with the U.S.-based subsidiary of a company headquartered in the PRC. The parent company is described in the indictment as &#8220;COMPANY ONE&#8221; and allegedly was working to develop self-driving cars. The indictment alleges Wang waited more than four months after signing the new employment agreement before informing Apple that he was resigning.

After Wang&#8217;s last day at Apple on April 16, 2018, Apple representatives reviewed access logs documenting historical activity on Apple&#8217;s network. Apple identified Wang as having accessed large amounts of sensitive proprietary and confidential information in the days leading up to his departure from Apple.

The indictment describes the June 27, 2018, search by law enforcement of Wang&#8217;s Mountain View residence and the discovery of large quantities of data taken from Apple prior to his departure. Wang was present during the search and told agents he had no plans to travel. Nevertheless, Wang purchased a one-way plane ticket from San Francisco International Airport to Guangzhou, China and boarded a flight that night.

The indictment describes six categories of trade secrets that Wang allegedly stole, or attempted to steal, and charges him with one count for each category.

Wang faces a maximum statutory sentence of 10 years in prison and a fine in the amount of $250,000 (or twice the gross gain or loss resulting from the scheme) for each count of theft or attempted theft of trade secrets.&#160;

The FBI is investigating the case.

Assistant U.S. Attorneys Sloan Heffron and Marissa Harris for the Northern District of California are prosecuting the case. Within the National Security Division, this matter is being handled by Brendan Geary of the National Security Division&#8217;s Counterintelligence and Export Control Section.

United States v. Xiangjiang Qiao,&#160;Southern District of New York

Today, a federal court in the Southern District of New York unsealed an indictment charging Xiangjiang Qiao aka Joe Hansen, 39, of the People&#8217;s Republic of China with sanctions evasion, money laundering, and bank fraud offenses based on Qiao&#8217;s alleged participation in a scheme to use a sanctioned Chinese company to provide materials used in the production of WMDs to Iran, in exchange for payments made through the U.S. financial system. Qiao is at large in China.

&#8220;As alleged, Xiangjiang Qiao conspired to send isostatic graphite to Iran, in violation of U.S. sanctions. Isostatic graphite is a high-tech material used in the nose tips of intercontinental ballistic missiles,&#8221; said U.S. Attorney Damian Williams for the Southern District of New York. &#8220;The Iranian regime of terror and repression, and those who facilitate it, pose a grave threat to our national security. This office will continue to work relentlessly to bring to justice those who advance the interests of the Iranian regime and thereby threaten the safety and security of the American people.&#8221;

According to court documents, Qiao is a Chinese national and an employee of the China-based company Sinotech Dalian Carbon and Graphite Manufacturing Corporation (Sinotech Dalian). Sinotech Dalian is part of a network of Chinese companies involved in the proliferation of WMDs and that, in particular, provide assistance in the procurement of materials for Iran&#8217;s ballistic missile program. In 2014, OFAC sanctioned Sinotech Dalian, adding the company to OFAC&#8217;s SDN and Blocked Persons list, explaining that Sinotech Dalian is part of a network of China-based entities used to proliferate WMDs and, specifically, to aid Iranian ballistic missile procurement. Sinotech Dalian&#8217;s inclusion on the SDN list prohibits it from using the U.S. financial system to conduct transactions without authorization from OFAC. Qiao is an associate of Li Fangwei, aka Karl Lee, who managed the Sinotech Dalian network of companies and was&#160;charged&#160;in 2014 with sanctions evasion and other offenses based on his alleged illicit activities as a principal contributor to Iran&#8217;s ballistic missile program through China-based entities.

In willful violation of U.S. sanctions on Iran and Sinotech Dalian, between at least March 2019 and September 2022, Qiao participated in a scheme to use Sinotech Dalian, including through transactions involving the U.S. financial system, to supply isostatic graphite to Iran for the production of WMDs. Isostatic graphite is a type of graphite with an ultra-fine grain that is used in the manufacture of WMDs. In particular, isostatic graphite is used in the manufacture of rocket nozzles and reentry vehicle nose tips in intercontinental ballistic missiles. Qiao further took steps to conceal Sinotech Dalian&#8217;s involvement in the transaction by creating a bank account in the name of a front company to receive two transfers from a U.S. bank totaling over $15,000 as part of his efforts to facilitate the supply of isostatic graphite to Iran.

Qiao is charged with one count of conspiracy to violate U.S. sanctions against Iran and Sinotech Dalian, in violation of the International Emergency Economic Powers Act (IEEPA), which carries a maximum sentence of 20 years in prison; two counts of violating the IEEPA, which each carry a maximum sentence of 20 years in prison; one count of conspiracy to commit bank fraud, which carries a maximum sentence of 30 years in prison; two counts of attempted bank fraud, which each carry a maximum sentence of 30 years in prison; one count of conspiracy to commit money laundering, which carries a maximum sentence of 20 years in prison; and two counts of money laundering, which each carry a maximum sentence of 20 years in prison.

The FBI New York Field Office and Counterintelligence Division are investigating the case.

Assistant U.S. Attorneys Gillian S. Grossman and Nicholas S. Bradley for the Southern District of New York are prosecuting the case. Within the National Security Division, this matter is being handled by Trial Attorney S. Derek Shugert of the Counterintelligence and Export Control Section.

*&#160;&#160; *&#160;&#160; *

Today&#8217;s actions were coordinated through the Disruptive Technology Strike Force, an interagency law enforcement strike force co-led by the Departments of Justice and Commerce designed to target illicit actors, protect supply chains, and prevent critical technology from being acquired by authoritarian regimes and hostile nation-states. Under the leadership of the Assistant Attorney General for National Security and the Assistant Secretary of Commerce for Export Enforcement, the Strike Force leverages tools and authorities across the U.S. Government to enhance the criminal and administrative enforcement of export control laws.

An indictment, complaint or criminal information is merely an allegation. All defendants are presumed innocent until proven guilty beyond a reasonable doubt in a court of law.

</text></article><article><title>Russian National Charged with Ransomware Attacks Against Critical Infrastructure</title><url>https://justice.gov//opa/pr/russian-national-charged-ransomware-attacks-against-critical-infrastructure</url><text>The Justice Department today unsealed two indictments charging a Russian national and resident with using three different ransomware variants to attack numerous victims throughout the United States, including law enforcement agencies in Washington, D.C. and New Jersey, as well as victims in healthcare and other sectors nationwide.

According to the indictment obtained in the District of New Jersey, from at least as early as 2020, Mikhail Pavlovich Matveev, aka Wazawaka, aka m1x, aka Boriselcin, aka Uhodiransomwar, allegedly participated in conspiracies to deploy three ransomware variants. These variants are known as LockBit, Babuk, and Hive, and Matveev transmitted ransom demands in connection with each. The perpetrators behind each of these variants, including Matveev, have allegedly used these types of ransomware to attack thousands of victims in the United States and around the world. These victims include law enforcement and other government agencies, hospitals, and schools. Total ransom demands allegedly made by the members of these three global ransomware campaigns to their victims amount to as much as $400 million, while total victim ransom payments amount to as much as $200 million.

&#8220;From his home base in Russia, Matveev allegedly used multiple ransomware variants to attack critical infrastructure around the world, including hospitals, government agencies, and victims in other sectors,&#8221; said Assistant Attorney General Kenneth A. Polite, Jr. of the Justice Department&#8217;s Criminal Division. &#8220;These international crimes demand a coordinated response. We will not relent in imposing consequences on the most egregious actors in the cybercrime ecosystem.&#8221;

On or about June 25, 2020, Matveev and his LockBit coconspirators allegedly deployed LockBit ransomware against a law enforcement agency in Passaic County, New Jersey. Additionally, on or about May 27, 2022, Matveev and his Hive coconspirators allegedly deployed Hive against a nonprofit behavioral healthcare organization headquartered in Mercer County, New Jersey. On April 26, 2021, Matveev and his Babuk coconspirators allegedly deployed Babuk against the Metropolitan Police Department in Washington, D.C.

&#8220;From Russia and hiding behind multiple aliases, Matveev is alleged to have used these ransomware strains to encrypt and hold hostage for ransom the data of numerous victims, including hospitals, schools, nonprofits, and law enforcement agencies, like the Metropolitan Police Department in Washington, D.C.,&#8221; said U.S. Attorney Philip R. Sellinger for the District of New Jersey. &#8220;Thanks to the extraordinary investigative work of prosecutors from my office and our FBI partners, Matveev no longer hides in the shadows &#8211; we have publicly identified his criminal acts and charged him with multiple federal crimes. Let today&#8217;s charges be a reminder to cybercriminals everywhere &#8211; my office is devoted to combatting cybercrime and will spare no resources in bringing to justice those who use ransomware attacks to target victims.&#8221;&#160;

According to the indictment obtained in the District of Columbia, between April 21, 2021, and May 9, 2021, Matveev allegedly participated in conspiracies to deploy Babuk and to transmit a ransom demand. Specifically, on April 26, 2021, Matveev and his Babuk co-conspirators allegedly deployed Babuk ransomware against the Metropolitan Police Department in Washington, D.C., and then threatened to disclose sensitive information to the public unless a payment was made.

&#8220;Data theft and extortion attempts by ransomware groups are corrosive, cynical attacks on key institutions and the good people behind them as they go about their business and serve the public,&#8221; said U.S. Attorney Matthew M. Graves for the District of Columbia. &#8220;Whether these criminals target law enforcement, other government agencies, or private companies like health care providers, we will use every tool at our disposal to prosecute and punish such offenses. Thanks to exceptional work by our partners here, we identified and charged this culprit.&#8221;

&#8220;The FBI is steadfast in our commitment to disrupting cybercriminals like Matveev,&#8221; said Assistant Director Bryan Vorndran of the FBI&#8217;s Cyber Division. &#8220;The FBI will continue to impose costs on cyber adversaries through our joint collaboration with our private sector and international partners, and we will not tolerate these criminal acts against American citizens.&#8221;

The LockBit ransomware variant first appeared around January 2020. LockBit actors have executed over 1,400 attacks against victims in the United States and around the world, issuing over $100 million in ransom demands and receiving over $75 million in ransom payments.

The Babuk ransomware variant first appeared around December 2020. Babuk actors executed over 65 attacks against victims in the United States and around the world, issuing over $49 million in ransom demands and receiving as much as $13 million in ransom payments.

Since June 2021, the Hive ransomware group has targeted more than 1,400 victims around the world and received as much as $120 million in ransom payments.

The LockBit, Babuk, and Hive ransomware variants operated in the same general manner: first, the ransomware actors would identify and unlawfully access vulnerable computer systems, sometimes through their own hacking, or by purchasing stolen access credentials from others. Second, the actors would deploy the ransomware variant within the victim computer system, allowing the actors to encrypt and steal data thereon. Next, the actors would send a ransom note to the victim demanding a payment in exchange for decrypting the victim&#8217;s data or refraining from sharing it publicly. Finally, the ransomware actors would negotiate a ransom amount with each victim willing to pay. If a victim did not pay, ransomware actors would often post that victim&#8217;s data on a public website, often called a data leak site. &#160;

Matveev is charged with conspiring to transmit ransom demands, conspiring to damage protected computers, and intentionally damaging protected computers. If convicted, he faces over 20 years in prison.&#160;

The FBI Newark Field Office&#8217;s Cyber Crimes Task Force is investigating the case with valuable assistance from the Jersey City Police Department, New Jersey State Police, Newark IRS Criminal Investigation, and international partners from European Cyber Crime Centre of Europol, National Police Agency of Japan, Gendarmerie Nationale Cyberspace Command of France, National Crime Agency and South West Regional Organized Crime Unit of the United Kingdom, Kantonspolizei Z&#252;rich of Switzerland, High-Tech Crime Unit of the Dutch Police Services Agency of the Netherlands, Bundeskriminalamt and Landeskriminalamt of Germany, Mossos d'Esquadra Police Department of Spain, Norwegian Police Service of Norway, and Swedish Police Authority of Sweden.

Trial Attorneys Jessica C. Peck, Benjamin Proctor, and Jorge Gonzalez of the Criminal Division&#8217;s Computer Crime and Intellectual Property Section (CCIPS); Assistant U.S. Attorneys Andrew M. Trombly and David E. Malagold for the District of New Jersey&#8217;s Cybercrime Unit in Newark; and Assistant U.S. Attorney Elizabeth Aloi for the District of Columbia&#8217;s Fraud, Public Corruption, and Civil Rights Section are prosecuting the case.

The FBI Tampa Field Office and Orlando Resident Agency, along with Assistant U.S. Attorney Chauncey Bratt for the Middle District of Florida and CCIPS Trial Attorneys Christen Gallagher and Alison Zitron, made critical contributions to the case. The FBI Washington Field Office and Metropolitan Police Department also provided valuable assistance.

The Justice Department&#8217;s Office of International Affairs and National Security Division also provided significant assistance.

Victims of LockBit, Babuk, or Hive ransomware should contact their local FBI field office for further information. For additional information on ransomware, including the LockBit, Babuk, and Hive variants, please visit StopRansomware.gov.

Additionally, the U.S. Department of the Treasury&#8217;s Office of Foreign Assets Control (OFAC) today announced that it is designating the defendant for his role in launching ransomware attacks against U.S. law enforcement, businesses, and critical infrastructure.

Finally, the Department of State has also announced an award of up to $10 million for information that leads to the arrest and/or conviction of this defendant. Information that may be eligible for this award can be submitted at tips.fbi.gov. Congress established the Transnational Organized Crime Rewards Program in 2013 to support law enforcement efforts to dismantle transnational criminal organizations and bring their leaders and members to justice. The Department of State&#8217;s Bureau of International Narcotics and Law Enforcement Affairs manages the program in coordination with other U.S. federal agencies.

An indictment is merely an allegation. All defendants are presumed innocent until proven guilty beyond a reasonable doubt in a court of law.

</text></article><article><title>Coal Broker Charged with Filing False Returns and Obstructing the IRS</title><url>https://justice.gov//opa/pr/coal-broker-charged-filing-false-returns-and-obstructing-irs</url><text>A federal grand jury in Charlotte, North Carolina, returned an indictment today charging a man with filing false individual tax returns and attempting to obstruct an IRS audit and criminal investigation.&#160; &#160;

According to the indictment, Vondie Brunty owned and operated West Star Management&#160;Inc. (WSM), a company that, from 2005 to April 2015, co-owned a coal brokerage business through which WSM received income on behalf of Brunty. Brunty allegedly caused WSM to surrender its ownership of the coal brokerage in approximately April 2015, but he allegedly continued to earn income through WSM by, among other things, hauling coal for the coal brokerage and selling timber rights to a lumber business.

The indictment alleges that, despite earning income, Brunty did not file personal tax returns for 2011 through 2013.&#160;During an IRS audit of the unfiled returns, Brunty allegedly made multiple false and misleading statements and did so again during an interview with IRS criminal investigators. The indictment further charges that, after learning of the criminal investigation, Brunty late-filed a 2014 tax return in January 2021 and a 2015 tax return in August 2021, both of which allegedly underreported his income.

Brunty faces a maximum penalty of three years in prison for obstructing the IRS and for each false return count. A federal district court judge will determine any sentence after considering the U.S. Sentencing Guidelines and other statutory factors.

Acting Deputy Assistant Attorney General Stuart M. Goldberg of the Justice Department&#8217;s Tax Division and U.S. Attorney Dena J. King for the Western District of North Carolina made the announcement.

IRS-Criminal Investigation is investigating the case.

Trial Attorneys Ashley Stein and Alexander Effendi of the Justice Department&#8217;s Tax Division and Assistant U.S. Attorney Caryn Finley of the Western District of North Carolina are prosecuting the case.

An indictment is merely an allegation and all defendants are presumed innocent until proven guilty beyond a reasonable doubt in a court of law.

</text></article><article><title>Massachusetts Man Indicted for Acting as an Illegal Agent of the People&#8217;s Republic of China</title><url>https://justice.gov//opa/pr/massachusetts-man-indicted-acting-illegal-agent-people-s-republic-china</url><text>A Massachusetts man was arrested on May 9 for allegedly acting as an agent of the People&#8217;s Republic of China (PRC) without providing notification to the U.S. Attorney General.

Litang Liang, 63, of Brighton, was indicted on one count of acting as an agent of a foreign government without providing notification to the U.S. Attorney General and one count of conspiracy to act as an agent of a foreign government without providing notification to the U.S. Attorney General.

&#8220;We will not tolerate the PRC&#8217;s efforts to interfere with public discourse and threaten civic participation in the United States,&#8221; said Assistant Attorney General Matthew G. Olsen of the Justice Department&#8217;s National Security Division. &#8220;This case demonstrates, once again, the lengths that the PRC government, including its Ministry of Public Security, will go to target people in the U.S. who exercise their rights to speak out against the PRC.&#8221;

&#8220;The Department of Justice will protect these individual rights and protect our country against those who seek to unlawfully act on behalf of foreign governments while within our borders,&#8221; said U.S. Attorney Rachael S. Rollins for the District of Massachusetts. &#8220;We allege that Mr. Liang engaged in a series of acts on behalf of the PRC government including providing information on Boston-area residents, organizations and dissidents to PRC government officials &#8211; potentially placing people at risk here in Massachusetts and abroad. Attempts to repress constitutionally protected rights here in the United States will never be tolerated. Anyone who infringes upon those rights on American soil will be identified and held to account.&#8221;

&#8220;The United States requires agents of foreign countries to register with our government, and for good reason &#8211; in such cases, those agents often act against the interests of the United States,&#8221; said Assistant Director Suzanne Turner of the FBI Counterintelligence Division. &#8220;The FBI is not going to stand by and allow undeclared agents of the People&#8217;s Republic of China to operate in our country unchecked. We will continue to steadfastly enforce the law of the land, uncovering these efforts and holding accountable all those who work with foreign governments to violate our laws.&#8221;

According to the charging documents, from in or around 2018 through at least 2022, Liang acted within the United States as an agent of the PRC government by allegedly providing PRC government officials with information on Boston-area individuals and organizations; organizing a counter-protest against pro-democracy dissidents; providing photographs of and information about dissidents to PRC government officials; and providing the names of potential recruits to the PRC&#8217;s Ministry of Public Security. At no point did Liang notify the U.S. Attorney General that he was acting as a PRC government agent.

Specifically, beginning in or around 2018, Liang allegedly provided information about Chinese individuals and organizations in the Boston area to PRC government officials &#8211; including PRC officials formerly in the United States, the Ministry of Public Security, and the United Front Work Department, an entity which reports directly to the Central Committee of the Chinese Communist Party (CCP) and works to further the CCP&#8217;s goals.

It is alleged that Liang provided PRC government officials with information regarding members and leaders of Boston-area, Chinese family associations and community organizations with pro-Taiwan leanings. Additionally, it is alleged that Liang sent information regarding anti-PRC dissidents to PRC officials including: identification of an individual he accused of having &#8220;sabotaged&#8221; PRC flags in Boston&#8217;s Chinatown in October 2018; video of a dissident attending the &#8220;Boston Stands with Hong Kong&#8221; march in August 2019; and photographs of anti-PRC dissidents in front of the Boston Public Library in September 2019.

The charge of acting as an agent of a foreign government without providing notification to the U.S. Attorney General provides for a sentence of up to 10 years in prison, three years supervised release, and a fine of up to $250,000. The charge of conspiracy to act as an agent of a foreign government without providing notification to the U.S. Attorney General provides for a sentence of up to five years in prison, three years supervised release, and a fine of up to $250,000. Sentences are imposed by a federal district court judge based upon the U.S. Sentencing Guidelines and statutes which govern the determination of a sentence in a criminal case.

Assistant U.S. Attorney Timothy H. Kistner for the District of Massachusetts is prosecuting the case. Valuable assistance was provided by Trial Attorney Elizabeth Abraham of the Justice Department&#8217;s Counterintelligence and Export Control Section.

The details contained in the charging documents are allegations. The defendant is presumed innocent unless and until proven guilty beyond a reasonable doubt in a court of law.

</text></article><article><title>Georgia Couple Charged with Labor Trafficking Conspiracy, Forced Labor and Alien Smuggling</title><url>https://justice.gov//opa/pr/georgia-couple-charged-labor-trafficking-conspiracy-forced-labor-and-alien-smuggling</url><text>A 16-count indictment was unsealed today charging a Georgia husband and wife with conspiring to commit labor trafficking, in addition to forced labor and alien smuggling, in connection with their operation of two Mexican restaurants, Sabor A Mexico at 805 Floy Farr Parkway, Fayetteville, Georgia, and Sabor A Mexico at 7860B Ella Lane, Fairburn, Georgia.&#160;

According to the indictment, between March 2021 and October 2022, Efrain Gonzalez, 40, and Estella Gonzalez, 34, both of Peachtree City, conspired to commit labor trafficking. The indictment alleges that the couple used force, threats of force, coercion and abuse of law and legal process to compel victims to engage in forced labor. The indictment further alleges that the couple engaged in alien smuggling for commercial gain, alleging five counts of alien smuggling against Efrain Gonzalez and one count against Estella Gonzalez.&#160;

The charge of forced labor carries a maximum of 20 years in prison, up to five years of supervised release, and a fine of up to $250,000. A federal district court judge will determine any sentence after considering U.S. Sentencing Guidelines and other statutory factors.

Assistant Attorney General Kristen Clarke of the Justice Department&#8217;s Civil Rights Division, U.S. Attorney Ryan K. Buchanan for the Northern District of Georgia, and Acting Special Agent in Charge Travis Picknard&#160;of HSI Atlanta made the announcement.

Assistant U.S. Attorney Annalise Peters and Trial Attorney Kate Hill of the Civil Rights Division&#8217;s Human Trafficking Prosecution Unit are prosecuting the case.&#160;

Anyone who believes that they may have been a victim of this case or may have relevant information to share is asked to &#160;call the HSI tip line at 866-DHS-2423.&#160;

If you or someone you know is a victim of human trafficking, please call the National Human Trafficking Hotline at 1-888-373-7888.

An indictment is merely an allegation. All defendants are presumed innocent until proven guilty beyond a reasonable doubt in a court of law.

</text></article><article><title>Delaware Man and Woman Charged with Sex and Labor Trafficking of 13 Victims</title><url>https://justice.gov//opa/pr/delaware-man-and-woman-charged-sex-and-labor-trafficking-13-victims</url><text>A federal grand jury in the District of Delaware returned an indictment charging a Delaware man and woman with sex trafficking, labor trafficking and related charges. The defendants are charged with aiding and abetting one another in committing sex trafficking and forced labor trafficking against 13 victims.

The indictment alleges that from 2014 through 2020, Clifton H. Gibbs, 66, and Brooke D. Waters, 44, of Lewes, recruited, harbored, transported and compelled nine victims to engage in commercial sex acts under the threat that they would suffer serious harm if they did not comply. The indictment further alleges that from 2016 through 2020, Gibbs and Waters obtained the labor and services of six victims under the threat of suffering serious harm if they did not comply. Finally, the indictment alleges that Gibbs and Waters transported three victims across state lines for the purpose of criminal sexual activity.

The sex trafficking charges carry a mandatory minimum penalty of 15 years in prison and a maximum of life imprisonment. The forced labor charges carry a maximum sentence of 20 years in prison. The interstate transportation for the purposes of criminal sexual activity charges carry a maximum sentence of 10 years in prison.

Assistant Attorney General Kristen Clarke of the Justice Department&#8217;s Civil Rights Division, U.S. Attorney David C. Weiss for the District of Delaware, Assistant Attorney General Kenneth Polite, Jr. of the Justice Department&#8217;s Criminal Division, Special Agent in Charge William S. Walker of the Department of Homeland Security&#8217;s Homeland Security Investigations (HSI) Philadelphia and Special Agent in Charge James C. Harris of HSI Baltimore made the announcement. The Delaware State Police, led by Colonel Melissa Zebley, provided valuable assistance in the investigation.

Assistant U.S. Attorney Briana Knox for the District of Delaware, Trial Attorney Rebekah J. Bailey of the Civil Rights Division&#8217;s Human Trafficking Prosecution Unit and Trial Attorney Caylee Campbell of the Criminal Division&#8217;s Money Laundering and Asset Recovery Section are prosecuting the case, with assistance from Senior Financial Investigator Kathryn Montemorra of the Money Laundering Section&#8217;s Special Financial Investigations Unit.

Anyone who believes that they may have been a victim of this case or may have relevant information to share is asked to call the HSI tip line at 866-DHS-2423.

If you or someone you know is a victim of human trafficking, please call the National Human Trafficking Hotline at 1-888-373-7888.

An indictment is merely an allegation. All defendants are presumed innocent until proven guilty beyond a reasonable doubt in a court of law.

</text></article><article><title>Two Men Indicted for Environmental Crimes Committed in the Jobos Bay National Estuarine Research Reserve and Las Mareas Community of Salinas, Puerto Rico</title><url>https://justice.gov//opa/pr/two-men-indicted-environmental-crimes-committed-jobos-bay-national-estuarine-research-reserve</url><text>Today, in the District of Puerto Rico, a federal grand jury returned two separate indictments charging Luis Enrique Rodriguez Sanchez and Pedro Luis Bones Torres with violations of the Clean Water Act and the Rivers and Harbors Act related to the illegal construction and deposit of material into the wetlands and waters of the United States in the area of the Jobos Bay National Estuarine Research Reserve (JBNERR) and Las Mareas community of Salinas, Puerto Rico.

According to the indictments, from approximately January 2020 through October 2022, Luis Enrique Rodriguez Sanchez (Rodriguez Sanchez) and Pedro Luis Bones Torres (Bones Torres) knowingly discharged fill material from excavation and earth moving equipment into the wetlands and waters of the United States in violation of the Clean Water Act. Further, both Rodriguez Sanchez and Bones Torres are charged with building structures within the navigable waters of the United States without authorization of the Secretary of the Army, in violation of the Rivers and Harbors Act. These activities occurred in the coastal waters and wetlands of the Las Mareas community and JBNERR in Salinas, Puerto Rico.

&#8220;These cases demonstrate our commitment to protecting wetland ecosystems, which have many public and environmental benefits,&#8221; said Assistant Attorney General Todd Kim of the Justice Department&#8217;s Environment and Natural Resources Division. &#8220;Coastal wetlands protect communities from storm surges and hurricanes, protect vulnerable species from exploitation, stabilize estuaries and provide natural water filtration that improves water quality.&#8221;

&#8220;The U.S. Attorney&#8217;s Office is committed to enforcing federal environmental protection laws and to holding violators responsible for the harm that they cause,&#8221; said U.S. Attorney W. Stephen Muldrow for the District of Puerto Rico. &#8220;These laws play an important role in protecting the animals, resources, and habitats within Puerto Rico, the Las Mareas community, and the Jobos Bay National Estuarine Research Reserve. The unpermitted construction, pollution, and fill within the protected waters of the United States also poses flooding and hurricane mitigation concerns for surrounding communities. As such, they are a priority for federal environmental enforcement efforts.&#8221;&#160;

&#8220;Today&#8217;s actions send a clear signal that the Department of Commerce Office of Inspector General (DOC-OIG) is dedicated to investigating potential fraud, waste and abuse in projects receiving funding from the National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA),&#8221; said Special Agent in Charge Jeffrey Lysaght of the DOC-OIG. &#8220;DOC-OIG greatly appreciates the cooperative efforts of our prosecutorial and law enforcement partners as we seek to enforce laws protecting the environment and natural beauty of Puerto Rico.&#8221;&#160;

The Clean Water Act was enacted by Congress in 1972 to protect and maintain the integrity of the waters of the United States. The Clean Water Act&#8217;s main purpose is to ensure the restoration and maintenance of the chemical, physical and biological integrity of the nation&#8217;s waters. It prohibits the discharge of any pollutant and fill material into waters of the United States except when a permit is obtained from the United States.

The Rivers and Harbors Act was originally enacted in 1899 and is generally considered the oldest environmental law in the United States. It serves to regulate and protect the navigable waters of the United States and prohibits the un-permitted construction of structures within those waters. Both the Clean Water Act and the Rivers and Harbors Act protect the coastal waters within the JBNERR.

The JBNERR was designated as a National Estuarine Research Reserve by the NOAA in 1981 and is comprised of approximately 2,800 acres of coastal ecosystems in the Southern coastal plain of Puerto Rico. The JBNERR contains mangrove islands, mangrove forests, tidal wetlands, coral reefs, lagoons, salt flats, dry forest and seagrass beds. It is also home to the endangered brown pelican, peregrine falcon, hawksbill turtle and West Indian manatee. The JBNERR is owned and operated by the Puerto Rico Department of Natural and Environmental Resources (PR-DNER).

Both Rodriguez Sanchez and Bones Torres were arrested and are scheduled to appear today before Magistrate Judge Bruce J. McGiverin of the U.S. District Court for the District of Puerto Rico for their respective initial appearances. If convicted, the defendants face up to four years in prison, as well as fines and injunctive relief to remove violative structures.

Various federal agencies are involved in this ongoing investigation related to environmental crimes in the JBNERR and Las Mareas community, including the Environmental Protection Agency Criminal Investigation Division (EPA-CID), FBI, U.S. Department of the Army Criminal Investigation Division (Army-CID), DOC-OIG, NOAA&#8217;s Office of Law Enforcement (NOAA-OLE), and U.S. Fish and Wildlife Service Office of Law Enforcement (FW-OLE).

The case is being prosecuted by Senior Trial Attorney Patrick M. Duggan of the Environment and Natural Resources Division&#8217;s Environmental Crimes Section and Assistant U.S. Attorney Seth A. Erbe, Environmental Litigation Coordinator for the District of Puerto Rico.

An indictment is merely an allegation, and all defendants are presumed innocent until proven guilty beyond a reasonable doubt in a court of law.

</text></article><article><title>Nevada Man Charged with Federal Hate Crimes for Irvine Taiwanese Presbyterian Church Shooting</title><url>https://justice.gov//opa/pr/nevada-man-charged-federal-hate-crimes-irvine-taiwanese-presbyterian-church-shooting</url><text>A Nevada man has been charged with 98 counts of federal hate crimes and weapons and explosives offenses, including the murder of one person and attempted murder of 44 others, for his actions during the shooting and attempted bombing at the Irvine Taiwanese Presbyterian Church on May 15, 2022.

David Chou, 69, of Las Vegas, killed one person and attempted to kill 44 others using firearms and explosive devices that he carried inside the Irvine Taiwanese Presbyterian Church in Southern California, according to the indictment returned Wednesday by a federal grand jury in Santa Ana, California. In addition to the victim who Chou fatally shot, five others were injured by gunfire. Chou allegedly acted because of the victims&#8217; national origin and religion, and he intentionally obstructed the victims&#8217; religious exercise.&#160;&#160;&#160;&#160;

Specifically, the indictment charges Chou with 98 violations of federal law:



45 counts of obstructing free exercise of religious beliefs by force, which resulted in the death of one person, included attempts to kill 44 others, and involved the use of a firearm and attempted use of explosives and fire;

45 counts of violating the Matthew Shepard and James Byrd Jr. Hate Crimes Prevention Act by attacking the church congregants because of their actual or perceived Taiwanese national origin and Presbyterian faith;

One count of attempting to damage or destroy a building used in interstate commerce by means of fire and explosives;

One count of carrying explosives during the commission of a federal felony offense; and

Six counts of using a firearm during the commission of a crime of violence.



If convicted, Chou faces a maximum penalty of death or life in prison without parole. He is currently in state custody pending state criminal charges.

Assistant Attorney General Kristen Clarke of the Justice Department&#8217;s Civil Rights Division, U.S. Attorney Martin Estrada for the Central District of California and Los Angeles FBI Assistant Director in Charge Donald Alway made the announcement. The FBI would like to acknowledge the considerable assistance of the Orange County Sheriff's Department.

The FBI Los Angeles Field Office, the Orange County Sheriff&#8217;s Department and the ATF investigated the case.

Assistant U.S. Attorneys Greg Scally and Susan Har for the Central District of California and Special Litigation Counsel Michael J. Songer of the Civil Rights Division&#8217;s Criminal Section are prosecuting the case.&#160; &#160;&#160;

An indictment is merely an accusation.&#160;All defendants are presumed innocent until proven guilty beyond a reasonable doubt in a court of law.&#160; 

</text></article><article><title>Foreign National Charged with Immigration Fraud and Human Smuggling Conspiracy</title><url>https://justice.gov//opa/pr/foreign-national-charged-immigration-fraud-and-human-smuggling-conspiracy</url><text>An indictment was unsealed today charging an Iranian national with leading a visa fraud scheme to facilitate the illegal entry of individuals from Iran into the United States.

According to court documents, Hesam Fatehi Peykani, 38, allegedly organized, led, and worked with others in his Iranian-based smuggling network to facilitate the entry of Iranian citizens into the United States under false pretenses. Peykani allegedly carried out his scheme by charging Iranian citizens between $1,000 to $30,000 to submit or cause to be submitted tourist visa applications with false information on their behalf at a nearby U.S. consulate or embassy. The purportedly false information made the Iranian citizens appear to have strong ties to Iran to increase the likelihood of receiving a U.S. tourist visa, even when the applicants intended to remain in the United States permanently. Peykani allegedly coached the applicants to repeat the lies on their tourist visa application during their visa interview at a U.S. consulate or embassy. On one or more occasions, Peykani allegedly provided fraudulent documents to the Iranian citizens to support the lies in their visa application during their visa interview.

&#8220;Hesam Fatehi Peykani is alleged to have fraudulently facilitated the entry of Iranian citizens into the United States when they were not entitled to otherwise do so &#8211; enriching himself in the process, by charging large fees for his services,&#8221; said Assistant Attorney General Kenneth A. Polite, Jr. of the Justice Department&#8217;s Criminal Division. &#8220;As this case demonstrates, the department continues to identify, investigate, and prosecute those who seek to profit from conduct that undermines our system of legal immigration.&#8221;

&#8220;Peykani allegedly exploited individuals and the U.S. immigration system through his visa scheme, trading on lies and fake documents to facilitate the illegal entry of Iranian citizens into the United States under false pretenses,&#8221; said U.S. Attorney Jessica D. Aber for the Eastern District of Virginia. &#8220;We are committed to holding accountable those who seek personal monetary gain by compromising and undermining the integrity of the immigration process.&#8221;

&#8220;This case represents the finest efforts of cooperative law enforcement,&#8221; said Supervisory Special Agent Gregory Batman of the U.S. Department of State&#8217;s Diplomatic Security Service (DSS). &#8220;DSS pursued investigative leads which led to disrupting and dismantling human smuggling operations. These crimes threaten the national security of the United States and the trustworthiness of our visa process.&#8221;

&#8220;Hesam Fatehi Peykani is allegedly part of a larger Iranian smuggling network that purportedly lined their own pockets by cheating Iranian citizens out of thousands of dollars and lying to the U.S. government,&#8221; said Special Agent in Charge Derek W. Gordon of the Homeland Security Investigations (HSI) Washington, D.C., Field Office. &#8220;They allegedly enabled Iranians to enter the U.S. under fictitious pretenses. HSI Washington cannot allow such breaches of security to happen without consequences. We are constantly looking to reinforce our nation&#8217;s security in order to provide safety for the American people.&#8221;

Peykani is charged with conspiracy to defraud the United States and commit visa fraud, visa fraud, conspiracy to encourage and induce an alien to come to the United States for profit, and encouraging and inducing an alien to come to the United States for profit. If convicted, he faces a maximum penalty of 10 years in prison.

The DSS Criminal Fraud Investigations Branch is investigating the case, with assistance from the HSI Washington D.C., Field Office, and is supported by the Extraterritorial Criminal Travel Strike Force (ECT) program, a joint partnership between the Justice Department&#8217;s Criminal Division and HSI. The ECT program focuses on human smuggling networks that may present national security or public safety risks, or present grave humanitarian concerns. ECT has dedicated investigative, intelligence, and prosecutorial resources. ECT coordinates and receives assistance from other U.S. government agencies and foreign law enforcement authorities.

Trial Attorney Clayton O&#8217;Connor of the Criminal Division's Human Rights and Special Prosecutions Section and Assistant U.S. Attorney Raizza Ty for&#160;the Eastern District of Virginia are prosecuting the case.

An indictment is merely an allegation. All defendants are presumed innocent until proven guilty beyond a reasonable doubt in a court of law.

</text></article><article><title>Foreign National Extradited to the United States for Kidnapping and Assaulting U.S. Army Soldiers in Colombia</title><url>https://justice.gov//opa/pr/foreign-national-extradited-united-states-kidnapping-and-assaulting-us-army-soldiers-colombia</url><text>A Colombian national has been extradited from Colombia to the United States to face charges related to kidnapping and assaulting two U.S. Army soldiers who were on temporary duty in Bogota, Colombia.

Jeffersson Arango Castellanos made his initial court appearance today in the U.S. District Court for the Southern District of Florida.&#160;

According to court documents, Arango and his co-conspirators targeted, incapacitated, and kidnapped two U.S. soldiers in Bogota. The two victims were in an entertainment district in Bogota watching a sporting event on the evening of March 5, 2020. While at a pub in Bogota, the two victims lost consciousness until the following day, by which point they had been separated. Medical examinations later confirmed the presence of benzodiazepines in their systems. The defendants are alleged to have targeted the two victims at the pub, incapacitated them with drugs, and kidnapped them to acquire the victims&#8217; valuables and credit and debit card information.

Arango and his co-conspirators are each charged with kidnapping an internationally protected person, conspiracy to kidnap an internationally protected person, assaulting an internationally protected person, and conspiracy to assault an internationally protected person. If convicted, they each face a maximum penalty of life in prison.

Assistant Attorney General Kenneth A. Polite, Jr. of the Justice Department&#8217;s Criminal Division, U.S. Attorney Markenzy Lapointe for the Southern District of Florida, and Special Agent in Charge Jeffrey B. Veltri of the FBI Miami Field Office made the announcement.

The Justice Department&#8217;s Office of International Affairs, the Narcotic and Dangerous Drug Section&#8217;s Judicial Attach&#233; Office in Bogota, and the U.S. Marshals Service provided significant assistance in securing the arrest and extradition of the defendant.&#160;The United States also thanks Colombian law enforcement authorities for their valuable assistance.

Trial Attorneys Clayton O&#8217;Connor and Elizabeth Nielson of the Criminal Division&#8217;s Human Rights and Special Prosecutions Section and Assistant U.S. Attorney Dayron Silverio for the Southern District of Florida are prosecuting the case.

An indictment is merely an allegation. All defendants are presumed innocent until proven guilty beyond a reasonable doubt in a court of law.

</text></article></articles>